<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Osteoporosis in men: an Endocrine Society clinical practice guideline.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Watts NB, Adler RA, Bilezikian JP, Drake MT, Eastell R, Orwoll ES, Finkelstein JS. Osteoporosis in men: an Endocrine Society clinical practice guideline. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jun;97(6):1802-22. [203 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22675062&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Bone mineral density studies  (88.98); General physical examination  (89.7); Osteoporosis, unspecified  (733.00)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Absorptiometry, Photon ; Androgen Antagonists ; Antibodies, Monoclonal ; Biological Markers ; Blood Cell Count ; Bone Density ; Calcium, Dietary ; Diphosphonates ; Drug Therapy ; Electrophoresis ; Exercise ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Hypogonadism ; Life Style ; Liver Function Tests ; Medical History Taking ; Osteoporosis ; Physical Examination ; Prostatic Neoplasms ; Smoking Cessation ; Spinal Fractures ; Teriparatide ; Testosterone ; Thyroid Function Tests ; Vitamin D "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Alkaline phosphatase measurement ; Androgen Antagonists ; Biological Markers ; blood cell count ; Bone Density ; Bone Mineral Density Test ; Calcium, Dietary ; Cessation of smoking ; complete blood count ; Creatinine measurement ; denosumab ; Diphosphonates ; Exercise ; Free Testosterone Measurement ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Life Style ; Liver Function Tests ; Monoclonal Antibodies ; Osteoporosis ; Parathyroid hormone measurement ; Pharmacotherapy ; Phosphate measurement ; physical examination ; Prostatic Neoplasms ; Serum calcium measurement ; Spinal Fractures ; Teriparatide ; Testosterone ; Thyroid Function Tests ; Total Testosterone Measurement ; Vitamin D ; Vitamin D measurement "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: biological markers ; denosumab ; osteoporosis ; therapeutic testosterone "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: 24 hour urine calcium output measurement  (313492004); Alkaline phosphatase measurement  (88810008); Antiandrogen  (103024009); Antiandrogen  (346324007); Blood cell count  (88308000); Complete blood count  (26604007); Creatinine measurement  (70901006); Denosumab  (446321003); Denosumab  (446457007); Diphosphonate  (372907000); Diphosphonate  (96281001); Drug therapy  (416608005); Education about alcohol consumption  (281078001); Electrophoresis  (703450007); Electrophoresis  (814007); Exercise  (183301007); Exercise  (256235009); Exercise  (61686008); Fracture of vertebral column  (50448004); Glomerular filtration rate  (80274001); Hypogonadism  (48130008); Life style  (134436002); Life style  (60134006); Liver function tests - general  (26958001); Liver function tests - general  (271552009); Monoclonal antibody  (49616005); Neoplasm of prostate  (126906006); Osteoporosis  (64859006); Parathyroid hormone measurement  (3352000); Phosphate measurement  (104866001); Physical assessment  (302199004); Physical assessment  (5880005); Physical assessment  (81375008); Protein electrophoresis  (82962001); Serum calcium measurement  (271240001); Teriparatide  (398823001); Teriparatide  (425438001); Testosterone  (109033004); Testosterone  (43688007); Testosterone measurement, total  (85470006); Testosterone measurement, unbound  (20436004); Thyroid panel  (35650009); Urine protein electrophoresis  (73718004); Vitamin D  (11563006); Vitamin D  (30178006); Vitamin D measurement  (83729008)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="394" OrdBy="200" Name="Regulatory Alert"><Field FieldID="154" OrdBy="205" ID="395" Name="FDA Warning/Regulatory Alert" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline references a drug(s) for which important revised regulatory and/or warning information has been released.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/SafetyAlertsforHumanMedicalProducts/ucm436280.htm&quot; title=&quot;FDA Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;March 3, 2015 &amp;ndash; Testosterone Products&lt;/a&gt;: The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) is requiring that the manufacturers of all approved prescription testosterone products change their labeling to clarify the approved uses of these medications. FDA is also requiring these manufacturers to add information to the labeling about a possible increased risk of heart attacks and strokes in patients taking testosterone. FDA cautions that prescription testosterone products are approved only for men who have low testosterone levels caused by certain medical conditions. The benefit and safety of these medications have not been established for the treatment of low testosterone levels due to aging, even if a man's symptoms seem related to low testosterone.&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Osteoporosis and osteoporosis-related fractures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Risk Assessment" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Endocrinology" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Geriatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Nutrition" /><FieldValue Value="Orthopedic Surgery" /><FieldValue Value="Radiology" /><FieldValue Value="Rheumatology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Allied Health Personnel" /><FieldValue Value="Health Care Providers" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To formulate practice guidelines for the management of osteoporosis in men&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Men at risk of osteoporosis:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Higher risk men (aged &amp;ge;70) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Men aged 50&amp;ndash;69 who have risk factors (e.g., low body weight, prior fracture as an adult, smoking, etc.) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation/Risk Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Assessment of risk factors for osteoporosis (age, fracture history, comorbidity, lifestyle) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Assessment of bone mineral density using dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;DXA of the spine and hip &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Forearm DXA in certain cases &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Complete patient history and physical examination &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Laboratory evaluation (serum calcium, phosphate, creatinine [with estimated glomerular filtration rate], alkaline phosphatase, liver function, 25-hydroxyvitamin D [25(OH)D], total testosterone, complete blood count, and 24-h urinary calcium excretion) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Additional testing including calculated free or bioavailable testosterone, serum protein electrophoresis with free &amp;kappa; and &amp;lambda; light chains and/or urine protein electrophoresis, tissue transglutaminase antibodies (for celiac disease), thyroid function tests, and parathyroid hormone (PTH) levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vertebral fracture assessment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treatment/Management&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Lifestyle changes&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Calcium and vitamin D supplementation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Increased weight-bearing exercise &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Limiting alcohol &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Smoking cessation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Pharmacological therapy for men at high risk for fracture &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Selection of pharmacologic therapy&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Bisphosphonates &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Teriparatide &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Denosumab &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Testosterone &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Considerations for management of hypogonadal men &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Considerations for management of men with prostate cancer receiving androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Monitoring therapy using DXA and measuring a bone turnover marker &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Predictive value of risk factors associated with osteoporosis and fracture &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Positive improvements in bone mass density (BMD) and other biochemical markers associated with bone health &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reduction of fractures &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Endocrine Society's Task Force commissioned two systematic reviews (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field) to support their guidelines on Osteoporosis in Men.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Factors for Low Bone Mass-Related Fractures in Men: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eligibility Criteria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Studies eligible for inclusion in this review were original articles describing analytic studies (observational cohort, case-control, or randomized controlled trials) that reported a relative risk measure (such as relative risk, odds ratio, or hazard ratio) for a risk factor (variables that increases risk) for bone loss or low bone mineral density (BMD)-related fractures in adult males.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An expert reference librarian and study authors with expertise in conducting systematic reviews developed the search strategy. Search was performed on MEDLINE and EMBASE through the Ovid interface; Cochrane CENTRAL, ISI Web of Science, and Scopus from 1950 through February 2010. Controlled vocabularies and text words were used for: 1) osteoporosis, bone density, bone resorption, osteolysis, and bone fractures; 2) testing for bone loss (low bone mass, BMD, dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry, bone loss, and bone turnover), screening; and 3) known risk factors (such as long-term usage of corticosteroids). In addition, terms indicating risk, such as &quot;relative risk&quot; and &quot;odds ratio&quot; were also included. The focus was on population, community, longitudinal, cohort, or observational studies as well as clinical trials, especially those including adult men. The same general strategy using text words was applied to Web of Science and Scopus. In addition, the authors reviewed the reference sections of eligible studies and available reviews and requested potentially eligible studies from content experts. The detailed search strategy used is available in the Supplemental Data (published on The Endocrine Society's Journals Online web site at &lt;a href=&quot;http://jcem.endojournals.org&quot; title=&quot;Endocrine Society's Journal Web site&quot;&gt;http://jcem.endojournals.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pairs of reviewers independently evaluated the eligibility criteria of titles and abstracts and of eligible full text articles using standardized and piloted electronic forms using an online reference management system (Distiller SR, Ottawa, Canada). Data extraction was done using similar methodology with adequate inter-reviewer agreement greater than 0.80.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Comparative Effectiveness of Drug Treatments to Prevent Fragility Fractures: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-Analysis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eligibility Criteria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Trials eligible for inclusion in this review were: 1) randomized controlled trials; 2) trials that enrolled patients with established or at risk for osteoporosis; 3) trials that compared one or more of the interventions of interest to each other or to placebo; and 4) trials that measured the outcomes of interest, i.e., fragility fractures (vertebral, hip, and nonvertebral fractures). The interventions of interest were: bisphosphonates (alendronate, risedronate, zoledronate, and ibandronate), PTH 1-34 (teriparatide), selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERM) such as raloxifene or bazedoxifene, denosumab, and calcium and vitamin D. The task force decided to not include calcitonin because its fracture-preventing effect is generally considered to be very weak (5) and supported by low-quality evidence, and because it is not commonly used for modern long-term preventive therapy. Pamidronate, etidronate, strontium and lasofoxifene were also not included in this review because they are not approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of osteoporosis, the main focus of the guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An expert reference librarian and study authors with expertise in conducting systematic reviews developed the search strategy. An exploratory literature search identified recent and well-conducted systematic reviews about this topic. A previously published report that pooled data from trials that evaluated the effect of vitamin D and calcium on fractures was used as an index publication to identify these trials. Another previously published study also compared bisphosphonates, SERM, and PTH 1-34. The literature search of this latter study was updated through March 2010 because their search was done in November 2007. Subsequently, the literature search was updated through December 9, 2012. Additional searches were also conducted using the names of individual drugs as text words. MEDLINE and EMBASE were searched through the Ovid interface; the Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (CENTRAL), ISI Web of Science, and Scopus were also searched. The search was not limited by sex of study participants included or language of the publication. In MEDLINE and EMBASE, the controlled hierarchical vocabularies (MeSH and EMTREE) were used with the explode function to maximize sensitivity (osteoporosis, osteopenia, fractures, bone, bone density conservation agents, and drug categories). The Cochrane validated search filter was employed for identifying randomized controlled trials in both MEDLINE and EMBASE. The MEDLINE search strategy was adapted to search EMBASE and CENTRAL using a combination of text words and subject headings. ISI Web of Science and Scopus were searched using only text words. Recent trials without fracture data and trials in which the drugs of interest were given to treat bone metastases were excluded. The latter group of studies was not within the scope of this review because enrolled patients did not necessarily have low bone mineral density and the outcomes were pathological rather than fragility fractures. A recent trial in which the majority of patients received bisphosphonate therapy for an average of 3 yr before the beginning of the trial was also excluded. The detailed search strategy is available in the Supplemental Data.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pairs of reviewers independently evaluated eligibility of candidate titles and abstracts. When at least one reviewer determined an article was potentially eligible, the full text version was retrieved and pairs of reviewers assessed its eligibility. Standardized and piloted electronic forms using an online reference management system (Distiller SR, Ottawa, Canada) were employed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Factors for Low Bone Mass-Related Fractures in Men: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The search identified 1251 candidate references, of which 55 studies were deemed eligible.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparative Effectiveness of Drug Treatments to Prevent Fragility Fractures: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A total of 116 studies provided data for the meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality of Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+OOO&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes very low quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;++OO&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes low quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+++O&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes moderate quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;++++&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes high quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials" /><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Risk Factors for Low Bone Mass-Related Fractures in Men: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers appraised the quality of the included observational studies focusing on the adjustment for confounding, how study cohorts were selected, and how outcomes were assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta-Analyses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers estimated odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals (CI) and pooled across studies using a random effect model. They quantified inconsistency using the I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; statistic, which describes the proportion of heterogeneity across studies that is not due to chance, thus describing the extent of true inconsistency in results across trials. I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; less than 25% and I2 more than 50% reflect small and large inconsistency, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subgroup and Sensitivity Analyses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To explore causes of inconsistency, subgroup analyses were specified &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; according to the following factors: 1) adequate adjustment to multiple risk factors [age and body mass index (BMI) at a minimum] &lt;em&gt;vs&lt;/em&gt;. inadequate or no adjustment; 2) location of fracture site (hip, vertebrae, or other); and 3) hypogonadism type (drug-induced &lt;em&gt;vs&lt;/em&gt;. not). Publication bias was assessed by inspecting funnel plots for each outcome and performing Egger's regression test.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Comparative Effectiveness of Drug Treatments to Prevent Fragility Fractures: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-Analysis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Extraction and Quality Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pairs of reviewers extracted data in duplicate, with disagreements resolved by discussion and consensus. Study selection and data extraction (focusing on judgment of quality indicators) had adequate chance-adjusted interreviewer agreement above 0.80. Reviewers evaluated the quality of trials using elements from the Cochrane risk of bias tool focusing on allocation concealment, blinding (patients, investigators, data collectors, and outcome assessors), outcome assessment, loss to follow-up (attrition), and the extent of prognostic balance of study arms at the start of the study. The quality of evidence was judged using the GRADE framework (Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statistical Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Direct head-to-head comparisons were conducted using a random effects model to estimate pooled odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) incorporating within- and between-study heterogeneity. Reviewers assessed publication bias by examining funnel plots symmetry and by conducting Egger's regression test. Heterogeneity was assessed using the I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; statistic, which represents the proportion of heterogeneity that is not due to chance (but rather due to real differences across studies' populations and interventions). I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; values over 50% indicate substantial heterogeneity. Direct comparisons were performed using the Comprehensive Meta-analysis version 2 software package (Biostat Inc., Englewood, NJ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To incorporate indirect comparisons, reviewers conducted random-effects network meta-analyses using Markov chain Monte Carlo methods in WinBUGS 1.4.3 (MRC Biostatistics Unit, Cambridge, UK) following methods described by Lu and Ades. Reviewers modeled the comparative effectiveness of any two treatments as a function of each treatment relative to the reference treatment (i.e., placebo in this study). This approach assumes &quot;consistency&quot; of treatment effects across all included trials&amp;mdash;that is, the direct and indirect estimates of effect for each pair-wise comparison do not disagree beyond chance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers evaluated inconsistency by comparing the estimates from the direct comparisons and those from the indirect comparisons for the magnitude and direction of the point estimates and the extent of overlap of CI. The posterior distribution of all parameters was estimated using noninformative (i.e., vague, flat) priors to limit inference to data derived from the trials at hand (i.e., no assumptions were made about the efficacy of these drugs from data external to the 116 trials included in this systematic review). Reviewers updated three Markov chain Monte Carlo chains with 60,000 simulated draws after a burn in of 30,000 iterations using the same seed number (seed = 1000) for all chains. The pair-wise OR and 95% credible interval were reported and adjusted for multiple arm trials.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The probability that each drug was the most efficacious regimen was estimated by calculating the OR for each drug compared with an arbitrary common comparison drug (which was placebo in most cases due to the minimal number of head-to-head trials), and counting the proportion of iterations of the Markov chain in which each drug had the largest&amp;nbsp;OR in reducing fracture risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force was composed of a chair, selected by the Clinical Guidelines Subcommittee of The Endocrine Society, five additional experts, and a methodologist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force used the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) system to describe the strength of recommendations and evidence quality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consensus was guided by systematic reviews of evidence and discussions through a series of conference calls, e-mails, and one in-person meeting. An initial draft was prepared by the chair of the Task Force and was reviewed successively by The Endocrine Society's Clinical Guidelines Subcommittee and Clinical Affairs Core Committee; representatives of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research (ASBMR), European Calcified Tissue Society (ECTS), European Society of Endocrinology (ESE), and International Society for Clinical Densitometry (ISCD); and members at large. At each stage, the Task Force received written comments and incorporated needed changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strength of Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; - Indicates a strong recommendation and is associated with the phrase &quot;The Task Force recommends.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; - Denotes a weak recommendation and is associated with the phrase &quot;The Task Force suggests.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developers reviewed published cost analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drafts of the guideline were reviewed successively by The Endocrine Society's Clinical Guidelines Subcommittee and Clinical Affairs Core Committee; representatives of American Society for Bone and Mineral Research (ASBMR), European Calcified Tissue Society (ECTS), European Society of Endocrinology (ESE), International Society for Clinical Densitometry (ISCD); and members at large. At each stage, the Task Force received written comments and incorporated needed changes. The reviewed document was approved by The Endocrine Society Council before submission for peer review to the Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definitions for the quality of the evidence (+OOO, ++OO, +++O, and ++++); the strength of the recommendation (1 or 2); and the difference between a &quot;recommendation&quot; and a &quot;suggestion&quot; are provided at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests testing men at increased risk for osteoporosis by measurement of bone mineral density (BMD). Age 70 is a sufficient risk factor. Younger men (aged 50&amp;ndash;69) should be tested if additional risk factors are present. A history of fracture after age 50 is a particularly important indication for evaluation. Other reasons for testing men aged 50&amp;ndash;69 include diseases/conditions such as delayed puberty, hypogonadism, hyperparathyroidism, hyperthyroidism, or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; drugs such as glucocorticoids or gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonists; life choices such as alcohol abuse or smoking; or other causes of secondary osteoporosis. FRAX, Garvan, or other fracture risk calculators can improve the assessment of fracture risk and the selection of patients for treatment. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) of the spine and hip in men at risk for osteoporosis. (1|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests measuring forearm DXA (1/3 or 33% radius) when spine or hip BMD cannot be interpreted and for men with hyperparathyroidism or receiving androgen-deprivation therapy (ADT) for prostate cancer. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests a complete history and physical examination for men being evaluated for osteoporosis or considered for pharmacological treatment (e.g., those with low BMD and/or high fracture risk). Important information includes medications used, chronic diseases, alcohol or tobacco abuse, falls and/or fractures as an adult, and family history of osteoporosis. Physical examination should assess patient height in comparison with maximum height, kyphosis, balance, mobility, overall frailty, and evidence of causes of secondary osteoporosis, including testicular atrophy, signs of hyperthyroidism, and evidence of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Men for whom bisphosphonate therapy is considered should have an examination of the teeth. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests measuring serum calcium, phosphate, creatinine (with estimated glomerular filtration rate), alkaline phosphatase, liver function, 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25[OH]D), total testosterone, complete blood count, and 24-h urinary calcium (creatinine and sodium) excretion in men being evaluated for osteoporosis or considered for pharmacological treatment with bone-active agents. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If history or physical examination suggests a specific cause of osteoporosis, further testing should be done. Depending on the findings of the history and physical examination, such testing may include (but is not limited to) calculated free or bioavailable testosterone (using measurements of sex hormone-binding globulin [SHBG]), serum protein electrophoresis with free &amp;kappa; and &amp;lambda; light chains and/or urine protein electrophoresis, tissue transglutaminase antibodies (for celiac disease), thyroid function tests, and parathyroid hormone (PTH) levels. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In men with low bone mass (osteopenia) or osteoporosis who might have previously undiagnosed vertebral fractures, the Task Force recommends vertebral fracture assessment (VFA) using DXA equipment. If VFA is not available or is technically limited, lateral spine radiographs should be considered. (1|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifestyle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends that men with or at risk for osteoporosis consume 1000&amp;ndash;1200 mg calcium daily, ideally from dietary sources, with calcium supplements added if dietary calcium is insufficient. (1|+++O)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests that men with low vitamin D levels (&amp;lt;30 ng/ml [75 nmol/liter]) receive vitamin D supplementation to achieve blood 25(OH)D levels of at least 30 ng/ml (75 nmol/liter). (2|+++O)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests that men at risk of osteoporosis participate in weight-bearing activities for 30&amp;ndash;40 min per session, three to four sessions per week. (2|+OOO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests that men at risk of osteoporosis who consume three or more units of alcohol per day reduce their alcohol intake. (2|+OOO )&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends that men at risk of osteoporosis who smoke cease smoking. (1|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selection of Men for Treatment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;All Men&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends pharmacological therapy for men at high risk for fracture including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Men who have had a hip or vertebral fracture without major trauma. (1|+++O) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Men who have not experienced a spine or hip fracture but whose BMD of the spine, femoral neck, and/or total hip is 2.5 standard deviations (SD) or more below the mean of normal young white males. (1|++OO) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;In the United States, men who have a T-score between &amp;ndash;1.0 and &amp;ndash;2.5 in the spine, femoral neck, or total hip plus a 10-yr risk of experiencing any fracture &amp;ge;20% or 10-yr risk of hip fracture &amp;ge;3% using FRAX; further studies will be needed to determine appropriate intervention levels using other fracture risk assessment algorithms. For men outside the U.S., region-specific guidelines should be consulted. (1|++OO) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Men who are receiving long-term glucocorticoid therapy in pharmacological doses (e.g., prednisone or equivalent &amp;gt;7.5 mg/d), according to the 2010 guidelines of the American Society of Rheumatology. (1|++OO) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selection of Therapeutic Agent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends that men at high risk of fracture be treated with medication approved by regulatory agencies such as the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) or the European Union (EU) European Medicines Agency (EMA) (at the time of this writing, alendronate, risedronate, zoledronic acid, and teriparatide; also denosumab for men receiving ADT for prostate cancer) and that the selection of therapeutic agent be individualized based on factors including fracture history, severity of osteoporosis (T scores), the risk for hip fracture, patterns of BMD (i.e., whether BMD is worse at sites where cortical bone [e.g., 1/3 radius] or trabecular bone [e.g., spine] predominate), comorbid conditions (e.g., peptic ulcer disease, gastroesophageal reflux, malabsorption syndromes, malignancy, etc.), cost, and other factors. In men with a recent hip fracture, the Task Force suggests treatment with zoledronic acid. When teriparatide is administered, the Task Force suggests that it not be given with concomitant antiresorptive therapy. Agents that have not been approved by regulatory agencies for treatment of osteoporosis in men (calcitonin, ibandronate, strontium ranelate, etc.) should be used only if the approved agents for male osteoporosis cannot be administered. (1|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Management of Hypogonadal Men at High Risk of Fracture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For men at high risk of fracture who are receiving testosterone therapy, the Task Force suggests adding an agent with proven antifracture efficacy (e.g., a bisphosphonate or teriparatide). (2|+OOO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests testosterone therapy in lieu of a &quot;bone drug&quot; for men at borderline high risk for fracture who have serum testosterone levels below 200 ng/dl (6.9 nmol/ liter) on more than one determination, if accompanied by signs or symptoms of androgen deficiency (e.g., low libido, unexplained chronic fatigue, loss of body hair, hot flushes, etc.) or &quot;organic&quot; hypogonadism (e.g., due to hypothalamic, pituitary, or specific testicular disorder). If testosterone treatment does not alleviate symptoms of androgen deficiency after 3&amp;ndash;6 months, it should be discontinued and other therapy considered. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests testosterone therapy for men at high risk for fracture with testosterone levels below 200 ng/dl (6.9 nmol/liter) who lack standard indications for testosterone therapy but who have contraindications to approved pharmacological agents for osteoporosis. (2|++OO)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Men with Prostate Cancer Receiving ADT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force recommends pharmacological treatment for osteoporosis for men with prostate cancer receiving ADT who have a high risk of fracture. (1|+++O)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Therapy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests that clinicians monitor BMD by DXA at the spine and hip every 1&amp;ndash;2 yr to assess the response to treatment. If BMD appears to reach a plateau, the frequency of BMD measurements may be reduced.(2|+++O)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force suggests that clinicians consider measuring a bone turnover marker (BTM) at 3&amp;ndash;6 months after initiation of treatment using a bone resorption marker (such as serum C-telopeptide of type I collagen [CTX] or serum or urine N-telopeptide of type I collagen [NTX]) for antiresorptive therapy and a bone formation marker (such as serum procollagen I N-propeptide [PINP]) for anabolic therapy. (2|+++O)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality of Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+OOO&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes very low quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;++OO&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes low quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+++O&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes moderate quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;++++&lt;/strong&gt; Denotes high quality evidence&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strength of Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; - Indicates a strong recommendation and is associated with the phrase &quot;The Task Force recommends.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; - Denotes a weak recommendation and is associated with the phrase &quot;The Task Force suggests.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is specifically stated for&amp;nbsp;each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Improved identification, diagnostic evaluation and monitoring of men at risk of osteoporosis and fracture &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reduction of fracture risk through lifestyle changes and pharmacological treatments &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Because concomitant antiresorptive therapy seems to reduce the efficacy of teriparatide, increase costs, and expose patients to additional potential side effects, it should be discontinued when teriparatide is administered. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Potential safety concerns with bisphosphonates include osteonecrosis of the jaw and atypical femur fractures &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A meta-analysis showed that calcium supplements may be associated with an increased risk of myocardial infarction but no other cardiovascular end points or death in women. This finding has not been confirmed in men. In older women, calcium supplementation increases the risk of kidney stones. The prevalence of kidney stones is higher in men than in women, but no increase in kidney stones has been demonstrated in men at the level of calcium intake recommended for optimal bone health. An observational study suggested that the risk of metastatic prostate cancer was higher in men who received high doses of supplemental calcium (1500&amp;ndash;2000 mg/d), but this has not been substantiated in clinical trials. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vitamin D at high doses may result in toxicity (hypercalcemia or hypercalciuria), but this is rarely seen unless 25(OH)D levels exceed 150 ng/ml (375 nmol/liter), and such levels are unlikely with the doses of vitamin D recommended in the guideline. In a recent report of high-dose vitamin D (500,000 IU [12.5 mg] orally once a year) given to women older than 70 yr, there was an increased risk of fracture and falling, especially in the first 3 months after administration, when 25(OH)D levels were on average 50 ng/ml (125 nmol/liter). This finding needs to be confirmed in women and has not been documented in men, but it raises caution about giving high doses of vitamin D intermittently. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Bisphosphonate therapy should not be used in men with impaired kidney function (estimated glomerular filtration rate &amp;le;30&amp;ndash;35 ml/min). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Teriparatide should not be used in men with prior irradiation. Full prescribing information should be consulted. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical Practice Guidelines are developed to be of assistance to endocrinologists and other health care professionals by providing guidance and recommendations for particular areas of practice. The Guidelines should not be considered inclusive of all proper approaches or methods, or exclusive of others. The Guidelines cannot guarantee any specific outcome, nor do they establish a standard of care. The Guidelines are not intended to dictate the treatment of a particular patient. Treatment decisions must be made based on the independent judgment of health care providers and each patient's individual circumstances. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The Endocrine Society makes no warranty, express or implied, regarding the Guidelines and specifically excludes any warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular use or purpose. The Society shall not be liable for direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages related to the use of the information contained herein.&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Watts NB, Adler RA, Bilezikian JP, Drake MT, Eastell R, Orwoll ES, Finkelstein JS. Osteoporosis in men: an Endocrine Society clinical practice guideline. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jun;97(6):1802-22. [203 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22675062&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2012 Jun" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="The Endocrine Society - Professional Association" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Endocrine Society&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force received no funding or remuneration from commercial or other entities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Osteoporosis in Men Task Force&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Task Force Members&lt;/em&gt;: Nelson B. Watts (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Robert A. Adler; John P. Bilezikian; Matthew T. Drake; Richard Eastell; Eric S. Orwoll; Joel S. Finkelstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Endocrine Society maintains a rigorous conflict of interest review process for the development of clinical practice guidelines. All Task Force members must declare any potential conflicts of interest, which are reviewed before they are approved to serve on the Task Force and periodically during the development of the guideline. The conflict of interest forms are vetted by the Clinical Guidelines Subcommittee (CGS) before the members are approved by the Society's Council to participate on the guideline Task Force. Participants in the guideline development must include a majority of individuals without conflict of interest in the matter under study. Participants with conflicts of interest may participate in the development of the guideline but they have disclosed all conflicts. The CGS and the Task Force have reviewed all disclosures for this guideline and resolved or managed all identified conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conflicts of interest are defined by remuneration in any amount from the commercial interest(s) in the form of grants; research support; consulting fees; salary; ownership interest (e.g., stocks, stock options, or ownership interest excluding diversified mutual funds); honoraria or other payments for participation in speakers' bureaus, advisory boards, or boards of directors; or other financial benefits. Completed forms are available through The Endocrine Society office.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Disclosure of Task Force&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nelson B. Watts, M.D. (Chair)&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/ Organizational Interests: American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists, International Society for Clinical Densitometry, OsteoDynamics; Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp;amp; Metabolism; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: Amgen, Baxter, Bristol Myers Squibb, Eli Lilly, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson, Imagepace, Medpace, Merck, Pfizer/Wyeth, Warner Chilcott&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert A. Adler, M.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: International Society of Clinical Densitometry; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: Amgen, Eli Lilly, Genentech, Merck, Novartis, Virginia Commonwealth University&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John P. Bilezikian, M.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: Endocrine Fellows Foundation, International Osteoporosis Foundation, GSK; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: Amgen, Novartis, Merck, Warner-Chilcott, Eli Lilly, NPS Pharmaceuticals&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew T. Drake, M.D., Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: KER unit (Mayo Clinic); Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: none declared&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Eastell, M.D., FRCP, FRCPath, FMedSci&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: European Calcified Tissue Society, European Society of Endocrinology, International Bone and Mineral Society, Amgen, AstraZeneca, GSK, Medtronics, Nastech, Nestle, Fonterra Brands, Novartis, Ono Pharma, Osteologix, Pfizer, Lilly, Sanofi-Aventis, Tethys, unilever, Unipath, Iverness Medical, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson, SPD, MSD, IDS, Roche; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: Amgen, Novo Nordisk, Pfizer, Sanofi-Aventis&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eric S. Orwoll, M.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: Merck, Lilly, Amgen, Wright; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: American Society for Bone and Mineral Research, International Osteoporosis Foundation&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joel S. Finkelstein, M.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;mdash;Financial or Business/Organizational Interests: Astra Zeneca, Solvay Pharmaceuticals, Abbott, Up-to-Date; Significant Financial Interest or Leadership Position: none declared&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="159" OrdBy="1255" ID="453" Name="Guideline Endorser(s)" Type="orglist"><FieldValue Value="American Society for Bone and Mineral Research - Professional Association" /><FieldValue Value="European Calcified Tissue Society - Professional Association" /><FieldValue Value="European Society of Endocrinology - Medical Specialty Society" /><FieldValue Value="International Society for Clinical Densitometry - Nonprofit Organization" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.endocrine.org/~/media/endosociety/Files/Publications/Clinical%20Practice%20Guidelines/FINAL-Osteoporosis-in-Men-Guideline.pdf&quot; title=&quot;The Endocrine Society Web site&quot;&gt;The Endocrine Society&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from The Endocrine Society, Phone: (301) 941.0210; Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Societyservices@endo-society.org&quot;&gt;Societyservices@endo-society.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Murad MH, Drake MT, Mullan, RJ, Mauck KF, Stuart LM, Lane, MA, Abo Alnour NO, Erwin PJ, Hazem A, Puhan MA, Li T, Montori VM. Comparative effectiveness of drug treatments to prevent fragility fractures: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jun;97(6):1871-80. Electronic copies: Available to subscribers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://jcem.endojournals.org/content/97/6/1871.full.pdf+html?sid=2f02313f-2675-4129-a917-444ddcd4445a&quot; title=&quot;The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism (JCEM) Web site&quot;&gt;The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp;amp; Metabolism (JCEM) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Drake MT, Murad MH, Mauck KF, Lane MA, Undavalli C, Elraiyah T, Stuart LM, Prasad C, Shahrour A, Mullan RJ, Hazem A, Erwin PJ, Montori VM .&amp;nbsp; Risk factors for low bone mass-related fractures in men: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jun;97(6):1861-70. Electronic copies: Available to subscribers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://jcem.endojournals.org/content/97/6/1861.full.pdf+html&quot; title=&quot;The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp;amp; Metabolism (JCEM) Web site&quot;&gt;The JCEM Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from The Endocrine Society, Phone: (301) 941.0210; Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Societyservices@endo-society.org&quot;&gt;Societyservices@endo-society.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on July 30, 2012. The information was verified by the guideline developer on August 30, 2012. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on April 3, 2015 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Testosterone Products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an author manuscript copyrighted by The Endocrine Society. This may not be duplicated or reproduced, other than for personal use or within the rule of &quot;Fair Use of Copyrighted Materials&quot; (section 107, Title 17, U.S. Code) without permission of the copyright owner, The Endocrine Society. From the time of acceptance following peer review, the full text of this manuscript is made freely available by The Endocrine Society at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.endo-society.org/guidelines/Current-Clinical-Practice-Guidelines.cfm&quot; title=&quot;The Endocrine Society Web site&quot;&gt;http://www.endo-society.org/guidelines/Current-Clinical-Practice-Guidelines.cfm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
