<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline update from the American College of Physicians, American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, and European Respiratory Society.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Qaseem A, Wilt TJ, Weinberger SE, Hanania NA, Criner G, van der Molen T, Marciniuk DD, Denberg T, Schunemann H, Wedzicha W, MacDonald R, Shekelle P, American College of Physicians, American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, European Respiratory Society. Diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline update from the American College of Physicians, American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, and European Respiratory Society. Ann Intern Med. 2011 Aug 2;155(3):179-191. [62 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21810710&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Qaseem A, Snow V, Shekelle P, Sherif K, Wilt TJ, Weinberger S, Owens DK, Clinical Efficacy Assessment Subcommittee of the American College of Physicians. Diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians. Ann Intern Med 2007 Nov 6;147(9):633-8.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All American College of Physicians (ACP) clinical practice guidelines are considered automatically withdrawn or invalid 5 years after publication, or once an update has been issued.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Chronic airway obstruction, not elsewhere classified  (496); General physical examination  (89.7)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Adrenal Cortex Hormones ; Adrenergic beta-Agonists ; Bronchodilator Agents ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Drug Therapy, Combination ; Medical History Taking ; Nebulizers and Vaporizers ; Oxygen Inhalation Therapy ; Physical Examination ; Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive ; Rehabilitation ; Respiratory Therapy ; Spirometry "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Adrenal Cortex Hormones ; Adrenergic beta-Agonists ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Chronic airway obstruction, NEC in ICD9CM_2014 ; Chronic Obstructive Airway Disease ; Combination Drug Therapy ; Nebulizers ; Oxygen Therapy Care ; physical examination ; Pulmonary rehabilitation (procedure) ; Rehabilitation therapy ; Respiratory Therapy ; Spirometer (device) "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Beta-adrenoceptor agonist  (349920008); Beta-adrenoceptor agonist  (373227004); Bronchodilator  (353866001); Bronchodilator  (372580007); Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease finding  (13645005); Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease finding  (413846005); Corticoid preparation  (21568003); Corticoid preparation  (79440004); Nebulizer  (334947002); Oxygen therapy  (57485005); Physical assessment  (302199004); Physical assessment  (5880005); Physical assessment  (81375008); Pulmonary rehabilitation  (15081005); Rehabilitation therapy  (52052004); Respiratory therapy  (53950000); Spirometer  (303501006); Spirometry  (127783003)"/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Nebulizers  (12-712); Spirometers  (13-674)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: For the purpose of this guideline, the terms &lt;em&gt;COPD&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;airflow obstruction&lt;/em&gt; are used, where COPD is defined by both physiologic and clinical criteria and airflow obstruction is defined by spirometric findings alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Screening" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Pulmonary Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To update the 2007 American College of Physicians clinical practice guideline on diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and present new evidence on the diagnosis and management of stable COPD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults with stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;History and physical examination &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Spirometry &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treatment strategies, including:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Inhaled bronchodilators &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Monotherapy with either long-acting inhaled anticholinergics or long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Combination inhaled therapies with long-acting inhaled anticholinergics, long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists, or inhaled corticosteroids &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Pulmonary rehabilitation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Continuous oxygen therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline does not address all components of management of a patient with COPD and is limited to pharmacologic management, pulmonary rehabilitation, and oxygen therapy. It does not cover smoking cessation, surgical options, palliative care, end-of-life care, or nocturnal ventilation.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exacerbations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hospitalizations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health-related quality-of-life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dyspnea &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minnesota Evidence-based Practice Center performed an updated literature search that included studies from MEDLINE published between March 2007 and December 2009 (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). Additional background material reviewed by the guideline panel included the 2007 systematic evidence review by Wilt and colleagues and the 2005 Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality&amp;ndash;sponsored Minnesota Evidence-based Practice Center evidence report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The literature search focused on evidence for the value of spirometry for screening or diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD); the efficacy and comparative effectiveness of management strategies, such as inhaled monotherapies (anticholinergics, long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists, or corticosteroids), combination therapies, and pulmonary rehabilitation programs, for patients with COPD. For diagnostic accuracy of the physical examination and spirometry, the authors used an updated systematic review from 2008, because the guideline panel agreed that there is no reason to suspect that diagnostic accuracy of the physical examination or spirometry would have changed since the American College of Physicians (ACP) guideline was published in 2007. In addition, they did not update the search for the utility of supplemental oxygen for patients with COPD who have awake, resting hypoxemia because widespread consensus remains on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guideline rates the evidence and recommendations by using the ACP guideline grading system, which is based on the system developed by the GRADE (Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation) workgroup (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guideline panel included representatives from each of the 4 collaborating organizations, and the resulting guideline represents an official and joint clinical practice guideline from those organizations. The guideline panel communicated via conference calls and e-mails. The members reached agreement and resolved any disagreements through facilitated discussion. The final recommendations were approved by unanimous vote.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The key questions and scope of the guideline were developed with input from the joint guideline panel. These questions were:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What is the value of the history and physical examination for predicting airflow obstruction? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What is the value of spirometry for screening and diagnosis of adults who are asymptomatic and have risk factors for developing airflow obstruction, or who are COPD treatment candidates? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What management strategies are effective for treating COPD?&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: lower-alpha;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Mono- and combination inhaled therapies (anticholinergics, long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists, or corticosteroids) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Pulmonary rehabilitation programs &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Supplemental long-term oxygen therapy (evidence not updated) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evidence reviews and tables were presented to the guideline panel for review and comments. The guideline panel evaluated the recommendations on the basis of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: American College of Physicians' Clinical Practice Guidelines Grading System&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;The American College of Physicians' Guideline Grading System*&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Quality of Evidence&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Strength of Recommendation&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Benefits Clearly Outweigh Risks and Burden or Risks and Burden Clearly Outweigh Benefits&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Benefits Finely Balanced With Risks and Burden&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;High&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Moderate&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Low&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Insufficient evidence to determine net benefits or risks&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Adopted from the classification developed by the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) workgroup.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guideline was approved by the American College of Physicians (ACP) Board of Regents on 31 July 2010; by the American College of Chest Physicians Board of Regents on 6 April 2011; by the American Thoracic Society Executive Committee on 11 April 2011; and by the European Respiratory Society Scientific Committee on 11 April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definitions for the strength of evidence (&lt;strong&gt;high, moderate, low, or insufficient evidence to determine net benefits or risks&lt;/strong&gt;) and strength of recommendations (&lt;strong&gt;strong, weak&lt;/strong&gt;) are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 1&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;The American College of Physicians (ACP), American College of Chest Physicians (ACCP), American Thoracic Society (ATS), and European Respiratory Society (ERS) recommend that spirometry should be obtained to diagnose airflow obstruction in patients with respiratory symptoms&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Spirometry should not be used to screen for airflow obstruction in individuals without respiratory symptoms&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Targeted use of spirometry for diagnosis of airflow obstruction is beneficial for patients with respiratory symptoms, particularly dyspnea. Existing evidence does not support the use of spirometry to screen for airflow obstruction in individuals without respiratory symptoms, including those with current or past exposure to risk factors for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Evidence is insufficient to support the use of inhaled therapies in asymptomatic individuals who have spirometric evidence of airflow obstruction, regardless of the presence or absence of risk factors for airflow obstruction. There is no difference in the annual rate of forced expiratory volume (FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;) decline or prevention of symptoms in these individuals with treatment. No evidence from randomized controlled trials (RCTs) supports treating asymptomatic individuals, with or without risk factors for airflow obstruction, who do not have spirometric evidence of airflow obstruction. In addition, evidence does not show any independent benefit of obtaining and providing spirometry results on success rates in smoking cessation. No study evaluated the use of periodic spirometry after initiation of therapy to monitor ongoing disease status or modify therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 2&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;For stable COPD patients with respiratory symptoms and FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; between 60% and 80% predicted, ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS suggest that treatment with inhaled bronchodilators may be used&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: weak recommendation, low-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is limited and conflicting evidence of health benefits resulting from initiation of inhaled bronchodilators (anticholinergics or long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists) in symptomatic patients with FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; between 60% and 80% predicted as documented by spirometry. Individual patients may benefit from the therapy and may show improvement in their respiratory symptoms. However, the duration of maintenance therapy and the frequency of reevaluation once a patient is receiving therapy are unknown because evidence is limited. Further research is needed to evaluate the health benefits of inhaled therapies (anticholinergics or long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists) in symptomatic patients with FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; between 60% and 80% predicted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This recommendation does not address the occasional use of short-acting inhaled bronchodilators for acute symptom relief.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 3&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;For stable COPD patients with respiratory symptoms and FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 60% predicted, ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS recommend treatment with inhaled bronchodilators&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Patients who benefit the most from inhaled bronchodilators (anticholinergics or long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists) seem to be those who have respiratory symptoms and airflow obstruction with an FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; less than 60% predicted. The mean FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; was less than 60% predicted in the majority of the trials that evaluated the management of COPD.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This recommendation does not address the occasional use of short-acting inhaled bronchodilators for acute symptom relief.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 4&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS recommend that clinicians prescribe monotherapy using either long-acting inhaled anticholinergics or long-acting inhaled &amp;beta;-agonists for symptomatic patients with COPD and FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;60% predicted&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Clinicians should base the choice of specific monotherapy on patient preference, cost, and adverse effect profile&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Monotherapy with a long-acting inhaled &amp;beta;-agonist or a long-acting inhaled anticholinergic is beneficial in reducing exacerbations and improving health-related quality of life. Evidence was inconclusive regarding the effect of inhaled agents (anticholinergics and long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists) on mortality, hospitalizations, and dyspnea. Although data support that inhaled corticosteroids are superior to placebo in reducing exacerbations, concerns about their side effect profile (thrush, potential for bone loss, and moderate to severe easy bruisability) and less biologic rationale, in contrast to the rationale that supports the use of inhaled steroids as anti-inflammatory monotherapy in asthma, led to our recommendation that inhaled corticosteroids are not a preferred monotherapy for patients with stable COPD. Adverse effects related to inhaled long-acting anticholinergics or long-acting &amp;beta;-agonists range from mild (for example, dry mouth) to potentially serious (for example, cardiovascular events). Pooled analyses of results from trials of monotherapy show no statistically significant differences in outcomes among various monotherapies. However, some of the large recent trials have shown that different monotherapies may have a greater effect on certain outcomes. These observed effects need to be confirmed with further comparative effectiveness studies. Clinicians should base selection of treatment from among various monotherapies on individual patient preferences, cost, and adverse effect profile.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 5&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS suggest that clinicians may administer combination inhaled therapies (long-acting inhaled anticholinergics, long-acting inhaled &amp;beta;-agonists, or inhaled corticosteroids) for symptomatic patients with stable COPD and FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;60% predicted&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: weak recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many symptomatic patients with stable COPD and an FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; less than 60% predicted may benefit from combination therapy, but when to use combination therapy instead of monotherapy has not been clearly established. The long-term benefit of combination therapy compared to monotherapy in 2 recent large clinical trials (Towards a Revolution in COPD Health [TORCH] and Understanding the Potential Long-Term Impacts on Function with Tiotropium [UPLIFT]) was moderate for COPD exacerbations and of borderline statistical significance for mortality, but was not consistently seen in earlier trials. In some studies, combination therapy has been associated with a modest increase in the risk for adverse events, whereas other studies have not found this. Thus, the evidence is insufficient to support a strong recommendation for the broad use of combination therapy, and clinicians will need to weigh the potential benefits and harms of combination therapy on a case-by-case basis. The combination therapy that has been most studied to date is long-acting inhaled &amp;beta;-agonists plus inhaled corticosteroids.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 6&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS recommend that clinicians should prescribe pulmonary rehabilitation for symptomatic patients with an FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;50% predicted&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Clinicians may consider pulmonary rehabilitation for symptomatic or exercise-limited patients with an FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt;50% predicted&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: weak recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evidence supports the use of pulmonary rehabilitation for symptomatic patients who have severe COPD (FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;50% predicted). This is based on the fact that controlled trials of pulmonary rehabilitation have had a mean FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; of less than 50% predicted. The generalizability of the benefits of pulmonary rehabilitation in patients with less severe airflow obstruction is less clear. Physicians may consider prescribing pulmonary rehabilitation for patients with an FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; greater than 50% predicted if they remain symptomatic or have exercise limitation despite maximal medical therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 7&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;ACP, ACCP, ATS, and ERS recommend that clinicians should prescribe continuous oxygen therapy in patients with COPD who have severe resting hypoxemia (partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood [PaO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] &amp;le;55 mm Hg or saturation of peripheral oxygen [SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] &amp;le;88%)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(Grade: strong recommendation, moderate-quality evidence)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To accurately evaluate oxygen status, the assessment should ideally occur when patients are stable rather than during or immediately after an exacerbation. Use of supplemental oxygen for 15 or more hours daily can help improve survival in patients with COPD who have severe resting hypoxemia (PaO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;le;55 mm Hg or SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;le;88%).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because pulse oximetry has essentially supplanted arterial blood gases as a measure of oxygenation in nonhospitalized patients, it is reasonable to use oxygen saturation measured by pulse oximetry (SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) as a surrogate for PaO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. On the basis of the typical relationship between PaO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; as defined by the oxyhemoglobin dissociation curve, PaO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; of 55 mm Hg or less correlates approximately with SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; 88% or less.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See the figure in the original guideline document for a chart of the summary of the recommendations and clinical considerations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: American College of Physicians' Clinical Practice Guidelines Grading System&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;The American College of Physicians' Guideline Grading System*&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Quality of Evidence&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Strength of Recommendation&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Benefits Clearly Outweigh Risks and Burden or Risks and Burden Clearly Outweigh Benefits&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Benefits Finely Balanced With Risks and Burden&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;High&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Moderate&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Low&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Weak&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Insufficient evidence to determine net benefits or risks&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Adopted from the classification developed by the Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) workgroup.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adverse effects of therapy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical practice guidelines are &quot;guides&quot; only and may not apply to all patients and all clinical situations. Thus, they are not intended to over-ride clinicians' judgment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The authors of this article are responsible for its contents, including any clinical or treatment recommendations. No statement in this article should be construed as an official position of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality or the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Mobile Device Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Qaseem A, Wilt TJ, Weinberger SE, Hanania NA, Criner G, van der Molen T, Marciniuk DD, Denberg T, Schunemann H, Wedzicha W, MacDonald R, Shekelle P, American College of Physicians, American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, European Respiratory Society. Diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline update from the American College of Physicians, American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, and European Respiratory Society. Ann Intern Med. 2011 Aug 2;155(3):179-191. [62 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21810710&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2011 Aug 2" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="American College of Chest Physicians - Medical Specialty Society" /><FieldValue Value="American College of Physicians - Medical Specialty Society" /><FieldValue Value="American Thoracic Society - Medical Specialty Society" /><FieldValue Value="European Respiratory Society - Professional Association" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American College of Physicians&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical Guidelines Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;: Amir Qaseem, MD, PhD, MHA; Timothy J. Wilt, MD, MPH; Steven E. Weinberger, MD; Nicola A. Hanania, MD, MS; Gerard Criner, MD; Thys van der Molen, PhD; Darcy D. Marciniuk, MD; Tom Denberg, MD, PhD; Holger Sch&amp;uuml;nemann, MD, PhD, MSc; Wisia Wedzicha, PhD; Roderick MacDonald, MS; and Paul Shekelle, MD, PhD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any financial and nonfinancial conflicts of interest of the group members were declared, discussed, and resolved. Dr. Wilt: &lt;em&gt;Grant&lt;/em&gt;: American College of Physicians; &lt;em&gt;Payment for manuscript preparation&lt;/em&gt;: American College of Physicians. Dr. Hanania: &lt;em&gt;Consultancy&lt;/em&gt;: GlaxoSmithKline, Boehringer Ingelheim, Novartis, Pfizer, Sunovion, Pearl, Forest; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: GlaxoSmithKline, Boehringer Ingelheim, Novartis, Pfizer, Sunovion; &lt;em&gt;Payment for lectures including service on speakers bureaus&lt;/em&gt;: GlaxoSmithKline, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Merck. Dr. Criner: Consultancy: Uptake Medical, PortAero, Pulmonx; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution):&lt;/em&gt; Aeris Therapeutics, Emphysas Medica. Dr. van der Molen: &lt;em&gt;Consultancy&lt;/em&gt;: MSD, AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline, Nycomed; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline, Novartis; &lt;em&gt;Payment for lectures including service on speakers bureaus&lt;/em&gt;: AstraZeneca, Nycomed, GlaxoSmithKline, MSD. Dr. Marciniuk: &lt;em&gt;Board membership&lt;/em&gt;: American College of Chest Physicians, Chest Foundation, Lung Association of Saskatchewan, Canadian COPD Alliance, Canadian Thoracic Society; &lt;em&gt;Consultancy (no payment received)&lt;/em&gt;: Public Health Agency of Canada, Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technology in Health; Consultancy: Saskatchewan Medical Association; &lt;em&gt;Consultancy (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, GlaxoSmithKline, Saskatchewan Health Quality Council, Novartis, Nycomed, Pfizer; &lt;em&gt;Employment&lt;/em&gt;: University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon Health Region; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: Canadian Institute of Health Research, AstraZeneca, GlaxoSmithKline, Lung Association of Saskatchewan, Nycomed, Pfizer, Novartis, Saskatchewan Health Research Foundation, Schering-Plough, Saskatchewan Ministry of Health; &lt;em&gt;Payment for lectures including service on speakers bureaus&lt;/em&gt;: AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, GlaxoSmithKline, Pfizer, Lung Association of Saskatchewan, Canadian Thoracic Society, American Thoracic Society. Dr. Wedzicha: &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: Boehringer Ingelheim; &lt;em&gt;Board membership&lt;/em&gt;: GlaxoSmithKline, Novartis, Bayer, Pfizer, Medimmune/AstraZeneca, Danone/Nutricia, Nycomed; &lt;em&gt;Consultancy&lt;/em&gt;: Chiesi; &lt;em&gt;Consultancy (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: Novartis; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: GlaxoSmithKline, Novartis, Chiesi, AstraZeneca, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson; &lt;em&gt;Payment for lectures including service on speakers bureaus&lt;/em&gt;: Boehringer Ingelheim, GlaxoSmithKline, Pfizer, Bayer, Nycomed, Chiesi; &lt;em&gt;Travel/accommodations/meeting expenses unrelated to activities listed&lt;/em&gt;: Boehringer Ingelheim. Dr. Shekelle: &lt;em&gt;Employment&lt;/em&gt;: Veterans Affairs Medical Center; &lt;em&gt;Grants/grants pending (money to institution)&lt;/em&gt;: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ), National Institutes of Health, Veterans Administration; &lt;em&gt;Royalties&lt;/em&gt;: UpToDate; &lt;em&gt;Travel/accommodations/meetings expenses unrelated to activities listed&lt;/em&gt;: Travel to meetings sponsored by AHRQ, the Health Foundation, the University of Michigan, VA, Italian regional health authority, and RAND. Disclosures can also be viewed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acponline.org/authors/icmje/ConflictOfInterestForms.do?msNum=M11-0925&quot; title=&quot;ACP Web site&quot;&gt;https://www.acponline.org/authors/icmje/ConflictOfInterestForms.do?msNum=M11-0925&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Qaseem A, Snow V, Shekelle P, Sherif K, Wilt TJ, Weinberger S, Owens DK, Clinical Efficacy Assessment Subcommittee of the American College of Physicians. Diagnosis and management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians. Ann Intern Med 2007 Nov 6;147(9):633-8.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All American College of Physicians (ACP) clinical practice guidelines are considered automatically withdrawn or invalid 5 years after publication, or once an update has been issued.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annals.org/content/155/3/179&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;&gt;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Amir Qaseem, MD, PhD, MHA, Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106: email, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aqaseem@acponline.org&quot;&gt;aqaseem@acponline.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Qaseem A, Snow V, Owens DK, Shekelle P. The development of clinical practice guidelines and guidance statements of the American College of Physicians: summary of methods. Ann Intern Med. 2010 Aug 3;153(3):194-199. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annals.org/content/153/3/194.full&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;&gt;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106-1572.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following is also available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Video news release. Management of stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acponline.org/multimedia/?bclid=713149900001&amp;amp;bctid=1089881729001&quot; title=&quot;ACP Web site&quot;&gt;American College of Physicians (ACP) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A collection of Recommendation Summaries for all current ACP Clinical Guidelines is now available for mobile devices from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acponline.org/clinical_information/guidelines/mobile.htm&quot; title=&quot;ACP Web site&quot;&gt;ACP Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A continuing medical education (CME) is available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cme.annals.org/cgi/hierarchy/annintcme_course;M110925&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;&gt;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Summaries for patients. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a clinical practice guideline. Ann Intern Med 2011 Aug 2;155:179-191. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annals.org/content/155/3/I-35&quot; title=&quot;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&quot;&gt;Annals of Internal Medicine Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from the American College of Physicians (ACP), 190 N. Independence Mall West, Philadelphia PA 19106-1572.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on February 12, 2008. The information was verified by the guideline developer on February 29, 2008. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on September 30, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
