<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Practice parameter on gay, lesbian or bisexual sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender discordance in children and adolescents.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Adelson SL, American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Committee on Quality Issues (CQI). Practice parameter on gay, lesbian, or bisexual sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender discordance in children and adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012 Sep;51(9):957-74. [110 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22917211&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Gender identity disorder in adolescents or adults  (302.85); Gender identity disorder in children  (302.6); Major depressive affective disorder, recurrent episode, unspecified  (296.30); Major depressive affective disorder, single episode, unspecified  (296.20); Suicidal ideation  (V62.84); Unspecified drug dependence, unspecified  (304.90); Unspecified psychosexual disorder  (302.9)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Anxiety Disorders ; Community Health Services ; Confidentiality ; Depression ; Depressive Disorder ; Family Relations ; Gender Identity ; Goals ; Homosexuality ; Homosexuality, Female ; Homosexuality, Male ; Patient Care Planning ; Psychosexual Development ; Risk Assessment ; School Health Services ; Sexual and Gender Disorders ; Sexual Dysfunctions, Psychological ; Stress, Psychological ; Substance-Related Disorders ; Suicidal Ideation ; Suicide ; Transsexualism "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Anxiety Disorders ; confidentiality ; Depressive Disorder ; Drug abuse ; Family dynamics ; Family Relationship ; Feeling suicidal (finding) ; Female Homosexuality ; Homosexuality ; Lesbians ; Male Homosexuality ; Mental Depression ; objective (goal) ; Psychosexual Development ; Psychosexual Disorders ; Risk Assessment ; sexual orientation - bisexual ; Stress, Psychological ; Suicide ; treatment goals "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: anxiety disorder "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Anxiety disorder  (197480006); Bisexual  (42035005); Community health services  (413294000); Depressive disorder  (21061000119107); Depressive disorder  (35489007); Drug abuse  (26416006); Feeling suicidal  (225457007); Feeling suicidal  (6471006); Female homosexual  (89217008); Gender dysphoria  (93461009); Gender identity disorder of adolescence  (57715001); Gender identity disorder of childhood  (5095008); Goal  (410518001); Homosexual behavior  (225531006); Homosexual behavior  (38628009); Male homosexual  (76102007); Psychosexual assessment  (444778007); Psychosexual disorder  (56627002); Psychosexual identity disorder  (191787001); Psychosexual identity disorder  (87991007); Recurrent major depressive episodes  (268621008); Recurrent major depressive episodes  (66344007); Risk assessment  (225338004); Single major depressive episode  (268620009); Single major depressive episode  (36923009); Suicide  (44301001); Suicide risk assessment  (225337009)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Psychosocial distress that can develop in child and adolescent members of sexual minorities (homosexual, lesbian, bisexual, gender variant, or transgender) including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Depression &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anxiety disorders &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Substance abuse &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Suicidality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Counseling" /><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Endocrinology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Psychiatry" /><FieldValue Value="Psychology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /><FieldValue Value="Psychologists/Non-physician Behavioral Health Clinicians" /><FieldValue Value="Social Workers" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To foster clinical competence in those caring for children and adolescents who are growing up gay, lesbian, bisexual, gender variant, or transgender, reflecting what is currently known about best clinical practices for these youth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children and adolescents who are growing up gay, lesbian, bisexual, gender variant, or transgender&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Comprehensive diagnostic evaluation with an assessment of psychosexual development &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Confidentiality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exploration of family dynamics pertinent to sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender identity &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Awareness of psychiatric risk and a healthy psychosexual development should be fostered &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Utilization of current evidence in choosing treatment goals and modality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liaison with schools, community agencies, and other health care providers &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Community and professional resources &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Sexual therapy is not recommended since there is no evidence that sexual orientation can be altered through therapy, and that attempts to do so may be harmful.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Rate of persistence/desistence of gender nonconformity or discordance &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incidence of bullying of gay, lesbian, bisexual, or transgender (GLBT) youth &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incidence of suicide, drug abuse, and sexually transmitted diseases in GLBT youth &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Side effects of hormone or surgical treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The list of references for this Practice Parameter was developed by online searches of Medline and PsycINFO. A search of PsycINFO articles published since 1806 and Medline articles published from 1950 through April 27, 2010, of key-word terms &quot;sexual orientation,&quot; &quot;gay,&quot; &quot;homosexuality,&quot; &quot;male homosexuality,&quot; &quot;lesbianism,&quot; &quot;bisexuality,&quot; &quot;transgender,&quot; &quot;transsexualism,&quot; &quot;gender variant,&quot; &quot;gender atypical,&quot; &quot;gender identity disorder,&quot; and &quot;homosexuality, attitudes toward&quot; limited to English language, human subjects, and ages 0&amp;ndash;17 years (PsycINFO) or 0&amp;ndash;18 years (Medline) produced 7,825 unique and 967 duplicate references.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To take full advantage of the MeSH Subject Headings database, a subsequent search was conducted of articles in the Medline database through May 3, 2010 using MeSH Subject Headings terms &quot;homosexuality, &quot;male homosexuality,&quot; &quot;female homosexuality,&quot; &quot;bisexuality,&quot; &quot;transsexualism,&quot; and limiting articles to those written in English and related to human subjects, all child and adolescent ages (0&amp;ndash;18 years). This search produced 2,717 references.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Similarly, to take full advantage of the Thesaurus Terms (Descriptors) database, a subsequent search was conducted of articles in the PsycINFO articles through May 14, 2010 using Thesaurus Terms (Descriptors) &quot;sexual orientation,&quot; &quot;homosexuality,&quot; &quot;male homosexuality,&quot; &quot;female homosexuality,&quot; &quot;lesbianism,&quot; &quot;bisexuality,&quot; &quot;transgender,&quot; &quot;transsexualism,&quot; &quot;gender identity disorder,&quot; and &quot;homosexuality (attitudes toward)&quot; and limiting articles to those written in English and related to human subjects of childhood age (0&amp;ndash;12) and adolescent age (13&amp;ndash;17). This search produced 1,751 references.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The combined search in Medline MeSH Subject Headings and PsycINFO Thesaurus Terms (Descriptors) databases produced 4,106 unique references and 361 duplicate references. Of the 4,106 unique references, the following were winnowed out: 345 books or book sections; 94 dissertation abstracts; 18 editorials; 13 articles whose focus was primarily historical; 104 theoretical formulation or comment without peer review; 163 case reports or brief series; 32 related primarily to policy or law; 19 related to news; 74 related primarily to research methods; 736 primarily about human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)/acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) and an additional 404 about early HIV/AIDS or other sexually transmitted illness; one each related to an award, book review, or interview; 168 that dealt primarily with diseases, reproduction, paraphilia or intersex conditions beyond the scope of the Parameter; an additional 8 that fell outside the specified age range; an additional 26 duplicates that were found; and 10 dating from 1960 to 1975 related to aversive or &quot;reparative&quot; techniques intended to change sexual orientation that are inconsistent with current ethical position statements of the American Psychiatric Association. This winnowing process yielded 1,889 references.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To help ensure completeness of the search strategies, the search results using Medline MeSH terms and PsycINFO Thesaurus terms (Descriptors) were compared to key-word terms of the Medline and PsycINFO databases. This comparison demonstrated 1,113 overlapping references, with 6,712 unique to the key-word search and 2,993 unique to the combined Thesaurus Term (Descriptor) and MeSH searches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An updated Medline search of articles through March 3, 2011, of the MeSH database using the same Subject Headings and limits used in the previous search produced 138 references. An updated PsycINFO search of articles through March 3, 2011, of the Thesaurus database using the same Terms (Descriptors) and limits used in the previous search produced 107 references. Throughout the search, the bibliographies of source materials including books, book chapters, and review articles were consulted for additional references that were not produced by the online searches. Bibliographies of publications by selected experts were also examined to find additional pertinent articles not produced by online searches. Recent studies and discussions at scientific meetings in the past decade were considered for inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the list of references assembled in this way, references were selected whose primary focus was mental health related to sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender discordance in children and adolescents. References that were not a literature review, published in peer-reviewed literature, or based on methodologically sound strategies such as use of population-based, controlled, blinded, prospective, or multi-site evidence were eliminated. References were selected that illustrated key points related to clinical practice. When more than one reference illustrated a key point around which there is general consensus, preference was given to those that were more recent, relevant to the U.S. population, most illustrative of key clinical concepts, based upon larger samples, prospective study design, or meta-analysis. When discussing issues around which consensus is not yet established, citations illustrating a representative sample of multiple viewpoints were selected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Not stated" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Practice Parameters are developed by the AACAP Committee on Quality Issues (CQI) in accordance with American Medical Association policy. Parameter development is an iterative process between the primary author(s), the CQI, topic experts, and representatives from multiple constituent groups, including the AACAP membership, relevant AACAP Committees, the AACAP Assembly of Regional Organizations, and the AACAP Council. Details of the Parameter development process can be accessed on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aacap.org&quot; title=&quot;AACAP web site&quot;&gt;AACAP website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AACAP develops both patient-oriented and clinician-oriented Practice Parameters. Patient-oriented Parameters provide recommendations to guide clinicians toward best assessment and treatment practices. Recommendations are based on the critical appraisal of empirical evidence (when available) and clinical consensus (when not), and are graded according to the strength of the empirical and clinical support. Clinician-oriented Parameters provide clinicians with the information (stated as principles) needed to develop practice-based skills. Although empirical evidence may be available to support certain principles, principles are based primarily on clinical consensus. This Parameter is a clinician-oriented Parameter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Practice Parameter was reviewed at the Member Forum at the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Annual Meeting in October 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From September 2011 to February 2012, this Parameter was reviewed by a Consensus Group convened by the Committee on Quality Issues (CQI).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Practice Parameter was approved by the AACAP Council on May 31, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 1. A comprehensive diagnostic evaluation should include an age-appropriate assessment of psychosexual development for all youths.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The psychiatric evaluation of every patient should take into consideration psychosexual development in a way that is appropriate to developmental level and the clinical situation. Questions about sexual feelings, experiences, and identity or about gender role behavior and gender identity can help clarify any areas of concern related to sexuality. The history should be obtained in a nonjudgmental way, for example without assuming any particular sexual orientation or implying that one is expected. This can be conveyed, for example, by the use of gender-neutral language related to the aim of affection (e.g., asking &quot;is there someone special in your life?&quot; rather than &quot;do you have a boyfriend/girlfriend?&quot;) until the adolescent reveals a particular sexual orientation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sexual and gender minority adolescents very frequently face unique developmental challenges, as described above. If an initial screen indicates that issues of sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, or gender identity are of clinical significance, these challenges can be explored in greater depth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 2. The need for confidentiality in the clinical alliance is a special consideration in the assessment of sexual and gender minority youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Issues of confidentiality are important with all patients; they are particularly so with sexual and gender minority youth, who require a clinical environment in which they can explore their developing orientation and identity. Prior experiences of rejection and hostility may lead them to watch social cues vigilantly to determine whether they can safely reveal their sexual orientation to others without fear of bias or judgment. Any sign of these in a mental health professional may induce shame and undermine the clinical alliance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should bear in mind potential risks to patients of premature disclosure of sexual orientation, such as family rejection or alienation from support systems, which might precipitate a crisis. They should be familiar with standard confidentiality practices for minors, and should protect confidentiality when possible to preserve the clinical alliance. This is particularly true when using media such as electronic health records, in which sensitive information can be easily disseminated. It is often helpful to emphasize reasonable expectations of privacy in the clinical relationship with sexual and gender minority youth&amp;mdash;not to express shame, but to permit the exploration of sexual identity free from fear and with a sense of control over disclosure. As the development of sexual identity is variable, it is often desirable to allow youth to set the pace of self-discovery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 3. Family dynamics pertinent to sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender identity should be explored in the context of the cultural values of the youth, family, and community.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Families of sexual or gender minority youth may consult mental health professionals for a variety of reasons, for example, to ask whether a disclosure of being gay represents a temporary stage, to request support for an adolescent, or to address problems such as bullying, anxiety, or depression. Just as some adults try to alter their sexual orientation, some parents may similarly hope to prevent their children from being gay. Difficulty coping with prejudice and stigma are often the appropriate focus of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Families treat gay or gender-discordant children with considerable variation. Whereas some accept their children, others explicitly or implicitly disparage or reject them, evoking shame and guilt; some force them to leave home. Although some are surprised by a child's coming out, others are not, and some are supportive. Families may have to fundamentally alter their ideas about a child who comes out, confront misconceptions, and grieve over lost hopes and/or expectations. Most parents experience distress following a child's coming out, frequently experiencing cognitive dissonance or feelings of anxiety, anger, loss, shame, or guilt; despite this, over time the majority become affirming and are not distressed. Children frequently predict their parents' reactions poorly. Ideally, families will support their child as the same person they have known and loved, although doing so may require time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Youth who are rejected by their parents can experience profound isolation that adversely affects their identity formation, self-esteem, and capacity for intimacy; stigmatized teens are often vulnerable to dropping out of school, homelessness (which may lead to exploitation or heightened sexual risk), substance abuse, depression and suicide. Clinicians should aim to alleviate any irrational feelings of shame and guilt, and preserve empathic and supportive family relationships where possible. They should assess parents' ideas about what constitutes normal, acceptable behavior, their cultural background, and any misconceptions or distorted expectations about homosexuality. These may include fears that their child will have only casual relationships, is fated to contract human immunodeficiency virus/acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (HIV/AIDS), cannot become a parent if desired, or will be ostracized. Stereotyped views of gay males as engaging only in numerous, indiscriminate sexual encounters are not supported by empirical research except in rare cases. If such behavior is present and cannot be explained as part of normal adolescent sexual drive or identity formation, factors known to be associated with excessive sexuality in youth, such as a history of sexual abuse, family dysfunction, a pattern of conduct problems, or mood disorder such as bipolar disorder or depression, should be considered. Clinicians should screen for all forms of abuse or neglect (as in any evaluation), with careful attention to adverse family reactions to a youth's sexual or gender development. If these are suspected, they should involve child protective services as clinical appropriateness and ethical and legal mandates warrant. Support groups may be helpful for families in distress. In cases of protracted turmoil or family pathology, referrals to family therapy, individual or couples therapy may be appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sexual and gender minority youth may experience unique developmental challenges relating to the values and norms of their ethnic group. Various groups may place different emphasis on ideals of masculinity or femininity, on family loyalty, or on social conformity; some with authoritarian parenting ideals may sanction youth who reject traditional mores.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For gay and lesbian adolescents who are also members of ethnic minorities, the deleterious effect of anti-homosexual bias may be compounded by the effect of racial prejudice. In response to unique pressures to gain group acceptance, they may give particular weight to negative group stereotyping of gay people. Gay and lesbian youth who are also members of ethnic minorities may be less likely than nonminority youth to be involved in gay-related social activities, to be comfortable with others knowing they are gay, or to disclose a gay identity. In caring for youth who are members of both ethnic and sexual minorities, mental health professionals should take into account the unique complexities of identity formation for these groups.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Religion, often a valued aspect of identity, can vary widely regarding tolerance for sexual minorities. Membership in relatively more liberal or conservative religious groups is a significant influence on one's &quot;sexual script,&quot; or social pattern in the expression of sexuality. Some minority denominations hold strong religious injunctions against homosexuality and stricter views about gender roles. As a result, members of certain religious groups can experience special challenges in integrating their sexual identity with family and community values. However, many religious groups are reconciling their traditions with more inclusive values. This remains an area of active social and cultural debate and change. Clinicians should respect the religious values of their patients, and should be aware of ongoing developments in religious thinking that may provide opportunities to integrate the religious and sexual aspects of identity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 4. Clinicians should inquire about circumstances commonly encountered by youth with sexual and gender minority status that confer increased psychiatric risk.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bullying&lt;/em&gt;. Gay, lesbian, bisexual, and gender nonconforming youth are regularly exposed to hostile peers. Victims of peer harassment experience serious adverse mental health consequences including chronic depression, anxiety, and suicidal thoughts. Sexual and gender minority youth may benefit from support for coping with peer harassment. School programs including no-tolerance policies for bullying have proved effective. Family treatment may be useful when sexual and gender minority youth are harassed in their families. Psychotherapy may help to avert or alleviate self-loathing related to identification with the aggressor. Clinicians should consider environmental interventions such as consultation or advocacy with schools, police, or other agencies and institutions advocating enforcement of zero tolerance policies to protect youth who may be victims of harassment or bullying.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suicide&lt;/em&gt;. Rates of suicidal thoughts and suicide attempts among gay, lesbian, and gender-variant youth are elevated in comparison with the general population. The developmental interval following same-sex experience but before self-acceptance as gay may be one of especially elevated risk. Suicidal thoughts, depression, and anxiety are especially elevated among gay males who were gender-variant as children. Family connectedness, adult caring, and school safety are highly significant protective factors against suicidal ideation and attempts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High-Risk Behaviors&lt;/em&gt;. Unique factors promoting risk-taking among gay and lesbian youth include maladaptive coping with peer, social and family ostracism, emotional and physical abuse, and neglect. Fear of rejection may lead some youth to be truant, run away, become homeless, be sexually exploited, or become involved in prostitution. Positive coping skills and intact support systems can act as protective factors. Lesbian youth have higher rates of unintended pregnancy than heterosexual female youth, perhaps due to anxiety about their same-sex attractions and a desire to &quot;fit in,&quot; an assumption birth control is unnecessary, or high-risk behavior rooted in psychological conflict. Clinicians should monitor for these risks or provide anticipatory guidance for them when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Substance Abuse&lt;/em&gt;. Some adolescents explore a gay identity in venues such as dance clubs and bars where alcohol and drugs are used. These youth may be at heightened risk of substance abuse because of peer pressure and availability of drugs. Lesbian and bisexual girls and boys describing themselves as &quot;mostly heterosexual&quot; (as opposed to unambiguously hetero- or homosexual) are at increased risk for alcohol use. A subgroup of gay youth displays higher rates of use of alcohol and drugs including marijuana, cocaine, inhalants, designer, and injectable drugs. They may use drugs and alcohol to achieve a sense of belonging or to relieve painful affects such as shame, guilt, and a lack of confidence associated with their romantic and sexual feelings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HIV/AIDS and Other Sexually Transmitted Illnesses&lt;/em&gt;. Adolescents are at risk for acquiring sexually transmitted illnesses included HIV infection through sexual risk taking, especially those who feel invulnerable or fatalistic, or who lack mature judgment, self-confidence, or the mature interpersonal skills needed to negotiate safe sexual experiences. Programs aimed at reducing adolescent sexual risk taking that are successful not only increase information about how HIV and sexually transmitted diseases are acquired and prevented, but also provide emotionally relevant and practical help in having safe sexual experiences that are developmentally relevant to youth. Adolescent gay males may be at particular risk of acquiring HIV sexually because of its high prevalence among men who have sex with men. Factors such as substance abuse or internalized homophobia associated with shame, guilt, or low self-esteem may interfere with an individual's motivation to use knowledge effectively about how to protect oneself from acquiring HIV infection. If present, these issues should be addressed clinically. Special HIV-prevention programs have been developed for and tested in gay youth and have demonstrated promising results.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 5. Clinicians should aim to foster healthy psychosexual development in sexual and gender minority youth and to protect the individual's full capacity for integrated identity formation and adaptive functioning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Protecting the opportunity to achieve full developmental potential is an important clinical goal in working with sexual and gender minority youth. The psychological acceptability of homosexual feelings to an individual and his or her family, and the individual's capacity to incorporate them into healthy relationships, can change with therapeutic intervention, and are an appropriate focus of clinical attention. Clinicians should strive to support healthy development and honest self-discovery as youth navigate family, peer, and social environments that may be hostile. Family rejection and bullying are often the proper focus of psychiatric treatment rather than current or future sexual orientation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes questions about a youth's future sexual orientation come to psychiatric attention. When they do, it may be most useful to explore what this issue means to the adolescent and significant persons in his/her life. It may be preferable to indicate that it is too early to know an adolescent's sexual orientation rather than to refer to such feelings as a &quot;phase,&quot; which may have connotations of disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When working clinically with youth whose sexual orientation or gender identity is uncertain, protecting the opportunity for healthy development without prematurely foreclosing any developmental possibility is an important goal. Clinicians should evaluate and support each child's ability to integrate awareness of his or her sexual orientation into his or her sexual identity while developing age-appropriate capacities in the areas of emotional stability, behavior, relationships, academic functioning, and progress toward an adult capacity for work, play, and love.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The availability of role models for sexual and gender minority youth varies greatly. The increasing visibility of gay people in society may decrease the isolation and loneliness of some gay youth, but others may be confronted with information that forces self-labeling before they are able to cope with irrational bias and feeling different. Some have access to positive role models or opportunities to form an affirming sexual identity among family, friends, the media, or through school programs such as gay&amp;ndash;straight alliances. Urban environments or the Internet may give youth access to positive role models and experiences, but may also carry risks that require adult supervision.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 6. Clinicians should be aware that there is no evidence that sexual orientation can be altered through therapy, and that attempts to do so may be harmful.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is no established evidence that change in a predominant, enduring homosexual pattern of development is possible. Although sexual fantasies can, to some degree, be suppressed or repressed by those who are ashamed of or in conflict about them, sexual desire is not a choice. However, behavior, social role, and&amp;mdash;to a degree&amp;mdash; identity and self-acceptance are. Although operant conditioning modifies sexual fetishes, it does not alter homosexuality. Psychiatric efforts to alter sexual orientation through &quot;reparative therapy&quot; in adults have found little or no change in sexual orientation, while causing significant risk of harm to self-esteem. A study of efforts to do so in adults has been criticized for failure to adequately consider risks such as increased anguish, self-loathing, depression, anxiety, substance abuse and suicidality, and for failure to support appropriate coping with prejudice and stigma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is no empirical evidence that adult homosexuality can be prevented if gender nonconforming children are influenced to be more gender conforming. Indeed, there is no medically valid basis for attempting to prevent homosexuality, which is not an illness. On the contrary, such efforts may encourage family rejection and undermine self-esteem, connectedness, and caring, which are important protective factors against suicidal ideation and attempts. As bullies typically identify their targets on the basis of adult attitudes and cues, adult efforts to prevent homosexuality by discouraging gender variant traits in &quot;prehomosexual children&quot; may risk fomenting bullying. Given that there is no evidence that efforts to alter sexual orientation are effective, beneficial, or necessary, and the possibility that they carry the risk of significant harm, such interventions are contraindicated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 7. Clinicians should be aware of current evidence on the natural course of gender discordance and associated psychopathology in children and adolescents in choosing the treatment goals and modality.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A majority of children display gender role behavior that adult caregivers regard as departing from gender role norms in toy preferences at least some of the time (demonstrating a difference between that which is culturally expected and that which is actually statistically normal). However, a smaller group of children demonstrate a consistent difference in gender role behavior from social norms. In different children, this may be true to varying degrees. In some, it may involve only a few areas&amp;mdash;for example, an aversion to rough-and-tumble sports in boys, or tomboyishness in girls. In others, it may involve several areas, including dress, speech, and use of social styles and mannerisms. It is important to distinguish those who display only variation in gender role behavior (gender nonconformity, which is not a Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders [DSM] diagnosis) from those who also display a gender identity discordant from their socially assigned birth gender and biological sex (gender discordance, reflected in the DSM-IV diagnosis Gender Identity Disorder when accompanied by marked gender nonconformity).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A clinical interview using DSM criteria is the gold standard for making a DSM diagnosis. In some cases of gender role variance, there may be clinical difficulty distinguishing between gender nonconformity and gender discordance&amp;mdash;for example, there may be clearly marked gender nonconforming behavior, but ambiguous cross-sex wishes. To assist clinicians in determining whether gender discordance is present, in addition to using clinical interviews, they can consider using structured instruments such as the Gender Identity Interview for Children, the Gender Identity Questionnaire for Children, and the Gender Identity/Gender Dysphoria Questionnaire for Adolescents and Adults. In using such instruments, clinicians should bear in mind that the American Psychiatric Association's Gender Identity Disorder subworkgroup for DSM-5 is currently debating areas of controversy in the diagnostic criteria for gender identity disorder (GID), including whether and how the explicit verbalization of gender discordant wishes should be included as a criterion, given the difficulty children may have expressing such wishes in nonaccepting environments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Disorders of sex development are an important differential diagnosis in gender discordant children and adolescents, for which endocrinological treatment may be indicated. When the clinical history suggests that a somatic intersex condition may be present, clinicians should consider consultation with a pediatric endocrinologist or other specialist familiar with these conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Children&lt;/em&gt;. Different clinical approaches have been advocated for childhood gender discordance. Proposed goals of treatment include reducing the desire to be the other sex, decreasing social ostracism, and reducing psychiatric comorbidity. There have been no randomized controlled trials of any treatment. Early treatments for gender discordance developed in the 1970s included behavioral paradigms; their long-term risks and benefits have not been followed up in controlled trials, and have been rejected on ethical grounds as having an inappropriately punitive and coercive basis. Psychodynamically based psychotherapy for gender discordance in boys has been proposed based on a psychodynamic hypothesis that gender discordance is a defense in fantasy against profound, early separation anxiety; like other treatment strategies, this has not been empirically tested in controlled trials.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recent treatment strategies based upon uncontrolled case series have been described that focus on parent guidance and peer group interaction. One seeks to hasten desistence of gender discordance in boys through eclectic interventions such as behavioral and milieu techniques, parent guidance and school consultation aimed at encouraging positive relationships with father and male peers, gender-typical skills, and increased maternal support for male role-taking and independence. Another approach encourages tolerance of gender discordance, while setting limits on expression of gender-discordant behavior that may place the child at risk for peer or community harassment. Desistence of gender discordance has been described in both treatment approaches, as it is in untreated children.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As an ethical guide to treatment, &quot;the clinician has an obligation to inform parents about the state of the empiric database,&quot; including information about both effectiveness and potential risks. As children may experience imperatives to shape their communications about gender discordant wishes in response to social norms, a true change in gender discordance must be distinguished from simply teaching children to hide or suppress their feelings. Similarly, the possible risk that children may be traumatized by disapproval of their gender discordance must be considered. Just as family rejection is associated with problems such as depression, suicidality, and substance abuse in gay youth, the proposed benefits of treatment to eliminate gender discordance in youth must be carefully weighed against such possible deleterious effects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Given the lack of empirical evidence from randomized, controlled trials of the efficacy of treatment aimed at eliminating gender discordance, the potential risks of treatment, and longitudinal evidence that gender discordance persists in only a small minority of untreated cases arising in childhood, further research is needed on predictors of persistence and desistence of childhood gender discordance as well as the long-term risks and benefits of intervention before any treatment to eliminate gender discordance can be endorsed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is similarly no data at present from controlled studies to guide clinical decisions regarding the risks and benefits of sending gender-discordant children to school in their desired gender. Such decisions must be made based on clinical judgment, bearing in mind the potential risks and benefits of doing so. Social gender assignment appears to exert partial influence on the gender identity of infants with disorders of sex development. At the same time, countervailing biological factors may override social gender assignment and contribute significantly to gender discordance in many cases. Therefore, the possibility that sending a child to school in his/her desired gender may consolidate gender discordance or expose the child to bullying should be weighed against risks of not doing so, such as distress, social isolation, depression, or suicide due to lack of social support. Further research is needed to guide clinical decision making in this area.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adolescents&lt;/em&gt;. For some individuals, discordance between gender and phenotypic sex presents in adolescence or adulthood. Sometimes it emerges in parallel with puberty and secondary sex characteristics, causing distress leading to a developmental crisis. Transgender adolescents and adults often wish to bring their biological sex into conformity with their gender identity through strategies that include hormones, gender correction surgery, or both, and may use illicitly obtained sex hormones or other medications with hormonal activity to this end. They may be at risk from side effects of unsupervised medication or sex hormone use.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One goal of treatment for adolescents in whom a desire to be the other sex is persistent is to help them make developmentally appropriate decisions about sex reassignment, with the aim of reducing risks of reassignment and managing associated comorbidity. In general, it is desirable to help adolescents who may be experiencing gender distress and dysphoria to defer sex reassignment until adulthood, or at least until the wish to change sex is unequivocal, consistent, and made with appropriate consent. Transgender youth may face special risks associated with hormone misuse, such as short- and long-term side effects, improper dosing, impure or counterfeit medications, and infection from shared syringes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For situations in which deferral of sex-reassignment decisions until adulthood is not clinically feasible, one approach that has been described in case series is sex hormone suppression under endocrinological management with psychiatric consultation using gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogues that reversibly delay the development of secondary sexual characteristics. The goals of such treatment are to avoid distress caused by unwanted secondary sexual characteristics, to minimize the later need for surgery to reverse them, and to delay the need for treatment decisions until maturity allows the adolescent to participate in providing informed consent regarding transition to living as the other sex. Prospective, case-controlled study of such treatment to delay puberty has shown some beneficial effects on behavioral and emotional problems, depressive symptoms, and general functioning (although not on anxiety or anger), and appears to be well tolerated acutely. In addition, gender discordance is associated with lower rates of mental health problems when it is treated in adolescence than when it is treated in adulthood. Therefore, such treatment may be in the best interest of the adolescent when all factors, including reducing psychiatric comorbidity and the risk of harm from illicit hormone abuse, are considered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment approaches for GID using guidelines based on the developmental trajectories of gender-discordant adolescents have been described. In one approach, puberty suppression is considered beginning at age 12, cross-sex hormone treatment is considered beginning at age 16, and gender reassignment surgery at age 18. Gender reassignment services are available in conjunction with mental health services focusing on exploration of gender identity, cross-sex treatment wishes, counseling during such treatment if any, and treatment of associated mental health problems. In another approach based on stage of physical development rather than age, pubertal suppression has been described at Tanner stage 2 in adolescents with persistent GID; risks requiring management include effects on growth, future fertility, uterine bleeding, and options for subsequent genital surgery and cross-sex hormone use. For families of transgender adolescents, a therapeutic group approach has been described that encourages parental acceptance. This approach may help to mitigate psychopathology and other deleterious effects of environmental nonacceptance. Further research is needed to definitively establish the effectiveness and acceptability of these treatment approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 8. Clinicians should be prepared to consult and act as a liaison with schools, community agencies, and other health care providers, advocating for the unique needs of sexual and gender minority youth and their families.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evaluating youths' school, community, and culture&amp;mdash;essential in any psychiatric evaluation&amp;mdash;is particularly important for sexual and gender minority youth. Clinicians should seek information about the sexual beliefs, attitudes, and experiences of these social systems, and whether they are supportive or hostile in the patient's perception and in reality. Clinicians should not assume that all parties involved in a youth's social system know about his or her sexual identity. They should review with the youth what information can be shared with whom, and elicit concerns regarding specific caregivers. If appropriate, the clinician can consider interventions to enhance support, with the youth&amp;rsquo;s knowledge and assent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As consultants, mental health professionals can help to raise awareness of issues affecting sexual and gender minority youth in schools and communities, and advise programs that support them. Clinicians can consider advocating for policies and legislation supporting nondiscrimination against and equality for sexual and gender minority youth and families, and the inclusion of related information in school curricula and in libraries.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle 9. Mental health professionals should be aware of community and professional resources relevant to sexual and gender minority youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many community-based organizations and programs provide sexual and gender minority students with supportive, empowering experiences safe from stigma and discrimination (e.g., the Harvey Milk School at the Hetrick Martin Institute, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hmi.org&quot; title=&quot;Harvey Milk Institute web site&quot;&gt;www.hmi.org&lt;/a&gt;; Gay-Straight Alliances, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsanetwork.org&quot; title=&quot;Gay-Straight Alliance Network web site&quot;&gt;www.gsanetwork.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many books and Internet resources for youth and families on issues such as discovering whether one is gay or lesbian. Clinicians should consider exploring what youth and families read, and help them to identify useful resources. Organizations such as Parents, Friends, and Families of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pflag.org&quot; title=&quot;PFLAG web site&quot;&gt;www.pflag.org&lt;/a&gt;) and the Gay, Lesbian and Straight Education Network (GLSEN) provide support and resources for families, youth, and educators. These organizations have programs in a number of communities. Clinicians can obtain information through professional channels such as the American Academy of Child &amp;amp; Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Issues Committee (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aacap.org&quot; title=&quot;AACAP web site&quot;&gt;www.aacap.org&lt;/a&gt;), the American Psychiatric Association (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.psych.org&quot; title=&quot;American Psychiatric Assn Web site&quot;&gt;www.psych.org&lt;/a&gt;), the Lesbian and Gay Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Association (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lagcapa.org&quot; title=&quot;Lesbian and Gay Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Association Web site&quot;&gt;www.lagcapa.org&lt;/a&gt;), and the Association for Gay and Lesbian Psychiatrists (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aglp.org&quot; title=&quot;Association for Gay and Lesbian Psychiatrists web site&quot;&gt;www.aglp.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Model Standards Project, published by the Child Welfare League of America, is a practice tool related to the needs of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) youth in foster care or juvenile justice systems available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cwla.org&quot; title=&quot;Child Welfare League of America web site&quot;&gt;www.cwla.org&lt;/a&gt;. The Standards of Care for Gender Identity Disorders, including psychiatric and medical care, are published by the World Professional Association for Transgender Health (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wpath.org&quot; title=&quot;World Professional Association for Transgender Health web site&quot;&gt;www.wpath.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although empirical evidence may be available to support certain principles, principles are based primarily on clinical consensus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate management of children and adolescents who are growing up to be gay, lesbian, bisexual, gender variant, or transgender&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Urban environments or the Internet may give youth access to positive role models and experiences, but may also carry risks that require adult supervision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that there is no evidence that efforts to alter sexual orientation are effective, beneficial, or necessary, and the possibility that they carry the risk of significant harm, such interventions are contraindicated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Practice Parameters are developed to assist clinicians in psychiatric decision making. These Parameters are not intended to define the sole standard of care. As such, the Parameters should not be deemed inclusive of all proper methods of care or exclusive of other methods of care directed at obtaining the desired results. The ultimate judgment regarding the care of a particular patient must be made by the clinician in light of all of the circumstances presented by the patient and that patient's family, the diagnostic and treatment options available, and other available resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Adelson SL, American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Committee on Quality Issues (CQI). Practice parameter on gay, lesbian, or bisexual sexual orientation, gender nonconformity, and gender discordance in children and adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012 Sep;51(9):957-74. [110 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22917211&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2012 Sep" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Committee on Quality Issues (CQI)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Stewart L. Adelson, M.D. and the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) Committee on Quality Issues (CQI): Heather J. Walter, M.D., M.P.H., and Oscar G. Bukstein, M.D., M.P.H., Co-Chairs, and Christopher Bellonci, M.D., R. Scott Benson, M.D., Allan Chrisman, M.D., Tiffany R. Farchione, M.D., John Hamilton, M.D., Helene Keable, M.D., Joan Kinlan, M.D., Nicole Quiterio, M.D., Ulrich Schoettle, M.D., Matthew Siegel, M.D., and Saundra Stock, M.D.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;AACAP Liaison&lt;/em&gt;: Jennifer Medicus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oscar Bukstein, M.D., M.P.H., co-chair, has received support from the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD), and Shire. He has received royalties from Routledge Press. Stewart L. Adelson, M.D., and Heather J. Walter, M.D., M.P.H., co-chair, report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest. Disclosures of potential conflicts of interest for all other individuals are provided on the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) website on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aacap.org/cs/root/member_information/practice_information/practice_parameters/conflicts_of_interest_for_practice_parameters_not_listed_in_parameter&quot; title=&quot;AACAP Web site&quot;&gt;Practice Parameters page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aacap.org/galleries/PracticeParameters/GLBT_Practice_Parameter_Sept2012.pdf&quot; title=&quot;American Academy of Adolescent and Child Psychiatry (AACAP) Web site&quot;&gt;American Academy of Adolescent and Child Psychiatry (AACAP) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Gay, Lesbian and Bisexual Adolescents. Facts for families. Washington (DC): American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry; 2006 Dec. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aacap.org/cs/root/facts_for_families/gay_lesbian_and_bisexual_adolescents&quot; title=&quot;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry Web site&quot;&gt;American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on October 22, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions. Any reproduction, retransmission, or republication of all or part of the original guideline is expressly prohibited, unless AACAP has expressly granted its prior written consent to so reproduce, retransmit, or republish the material. All other rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
