<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Follow-up care for early-stage breast cancer.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team. Follow-up care for early-stage breast cancer. Edmonton (Alberta): CancerControl Alberta; 2013 May. 26 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical practice guideline; no. BR-013).&amp;nbsp; [120 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Edema  (782.3); Heart disease, unspecified  (429.9); Malignant neoplasm of breast (female), unspecified  (174.9); Osteoporosis, unspecified  (733.00)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Breast Neoplasms ; Breast Self-Examination ; Counseling ; Diagnostic Imaging ; Edema ; Fatigue ; Heart Diseases ; Life Style ; Lymphedema ; Mammography ; Motor Activity ; Neoplasm Staging ; Osteoporosis ; Patient Care Planning ; Sex Education ; Smoking Cessation "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Acute leukemia ; Breast Self-Examination ; Cessation of smoking ; Counseling ; Diagnostic Imaging ; Diagnostic Neoplasm Staging ; edema ; Emotional support ; Family planning counseling ; Fatigue ; follow-up ; Follow-up status ; Heart Diseases ; Life Style ; Malignant neoplasm of female breast ; Mammary Neoplasms ; Mammography ; Myelodysplasia ; Osteoporosis ; Peripheral edema ; Physical activity ; Weight maintenance regimen "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: acute leukemia ; diagnostic imaging ; fatigue ; lymphedema ; mammography ; osteoporosis "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Acute leukemia  (24072005); Acute leukemia  (91855006); Breast self-examination  (409979009); Cancer care plan discussed with patient  (395673000); Cancer emotional and psychosocial support and education  (413736002); Counseling  (129441002); Counseling  (409063005); Diet good  (226234005); Diet good  (310500000); Edema  (20741006); Edema  (267038008); Edema  (423666004); Edema  (79654002); Education about alcohol consumption  (281078001); Emotional support  (133921002); Examination of breast  (46662001); Family planning education  (397619005); Fatigue  (248274002); Fatigue  (84229001); Follow-up status  (308273005); Heart disease  (56265001); Imaging  (363679005); Implementation of measures to provide psychological support  (372067001); Life style  (134436002); Life style  (60134006); Lymphedema  (234097001); Lymphedema  (30213001); Malignant neoplasm of female breast  (372064008); Mammography  (71651007); Neoplasm of breast  (126926005); Osteoporosis  (64859006); Peripheral edema  (271809000); Peripheral edema  (82014009); Physical activity  (48761009); Physical activity  (68130003); Psychological assessment  (405783006); Psychological assessment  (45392008); Sexuality education  (386468009); Weight maintenance regimen  (388962008)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="394" OrdBy="200" Name="Regulatory Alert"><Field FieldID="154" OrdBy="205" ID="395" Name="FDA Warning/Regulatory Alert" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline references a drug(s) for which important revised regulatory and/or warning information has been released.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/SafetyAlertsforHumanMedicalProducts/ucm454141.htm&quot; title=&quot;FDA Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;July 9, 2015 - Non-aspirin Nonsteroidal Anti-inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDS)&lt;/a&gt;: The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) is strengthening an existing label warning that non-aspirin nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) increase the chance of a heart attack or stroke. Based on FDA&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive review of new safety information, FDA is requiring updates to the drug labels of all prescription NSAIDs. As is the case with current prescription NSAID labels, the Drug Facts labels of over-the-counter (OTC) non-aspirin NSAIDs already contain information on heart attack and stroke risk. FDA will also request updates to the OTC non-aspirin NSAID Drug Facts labels. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early-stage breast cancer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Prevention" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Obstetrics and Gynecology" /><FieldValue Value="Oncology" /><FieldValue Value="Preventive Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Psychology" /><FieldValue Value="Radiation Oncology" /><FieldValue Value="Radiology" /><FieldValue Value="Surgery" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /><FieldValue Value="Psychologists/Non-physician Behavioral Health Clinicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide evidence-based strategies for the care of patients who have been discharged to their referring physician&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients who have completed active medical or radiation oncology treatment for early-stage breast cancer and have been discharged by the cancer care centre for care by the referring physician&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Responsibilities of the physician and cancer care centre regarding follow-up care &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Investigations and surveillance for patient follow-up: self-examination of breasts, clinical examination of breasts, imaging tests (mammography, other investigations) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Signs and symptoms to look for regarding breast cancer recurrence &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Counseling patients on potential complications of treatment, including use of endocrine therapy and avoiding exogenous estrogens &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Preventing and treating osteoporosis, fatigue, peripheral edema, lymphedema, cardiac dysfunction, acute leukemia/myelodysplasia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Assessment of patients for emotional/psychological health issues and offering resources and support &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Encouraging health lifestyle for cancer prevention (diet, physical activity, healthy weight, bone health, limiting alcohol consumption, smoking cessation) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Counseling patients on sexual health and family planning issues &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Survival rate (disease-free, overall) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Recurrence rate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Complication rate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treatment-related adverse effects &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patient satisfaction &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Specific research questions to be addressed by the guideline document were formulated by the guideline lead(s) and Knowledge Management (KM) Specialist using the PICO question format (patient or population, intervention, comparisons, outcomes).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guideline Questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What investigations (i.e., tests and exams) constitute follow-up care for patients who have completed active medical or radiation oncology treatment for early-stage breast cancer? How often should these investigations be performed? &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What are the responsibilities of the physician and cancer care centre, regarding follow-up care for patients with early-stage breast cancer? &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Are there any complications, from treatment with surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, endocrine therapy, and/or biologic therapy, of which the physician should be aware? What are the symptoms of these complications and how are they managed? &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What are the signs and symptoms to look for regarding a breast cancer recurrence? &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What are the more common survivorship concerns and challenges of patients who have been treated for early-stage breast cancer? How can survivorship be improved for these patients? What commendable supports are available in the community or on the internet? &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A systematic search for relevant literature related to breast cancer follow-up was conducted of MEDLINE and EMBASE. The search included the terms &quot;follow-up&quot; or &quot;surveillance&quot; or &quot;discharge&quot; or &quot;investigation&quot; or &quot;clinical examination&quot; AND &quot;breast neoplasm&quot;. The MEDLINE and EMBASE search was limited to clinical trials and meta-analyses published in the English language during the previous ten years only (e.g., 2001 to September 2011); a total of 3,812 citations were returned, of which 29 were deemed relevant (i.e., presented data on delivery of follow-up or investigations for follow-up).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A second search was conducted of specific concerns related to follow-up. The MEDLINE and EMBASE databases were searched using the following terms: &quot;lymphedema&quot; or &quot;weight management&quot; or &quot;bone pain&quot; or &quot;sexual functioning&quot; or &quot;psychosocial health&quot; or &quot;fatigue&quot; AND &quot;breast cancer follow-up&quot; and limited to clinical trials and meta-analyses published in the English language during the previous ten years only (e.g., 2001 to September 2011).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The search strategies were repeated just prior to publication of the guideline and covered the period of time from September 2011 through April 2013. An additional 778 studies were identified; of these, 12 were deemed relevant and included in the full literature review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Cochrane Library, Search Standards and Guidelines Evidence (SAGE) database available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.Cancerview.ca&quot; title=&quot;Cancerview.ca Web site&quot;&gt;www.Cancerview.ca&lt;/a&gt;, and the National Guideline Clearinghouse were searched for guidelines and systematic reviews related to breast cancer follow-up. A total of six clinical practice guidelines and two systematic reviews were deemed relevant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Refer to the &quot;Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Not stated" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evidence was selected and reviewed by a working group comprised of members from the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team and a Knowledge Management (KM) Specialist from the Guideline Utilization Resource Unit (GURU). A detailed description of the methodology followed during the guideline development process can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/hp/if-hp-cancer-guide-utilization-handbook.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;Guideline Utilization Resource Unit Handbook&lt;/a&gt; (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Tables&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evidence tables containing the first author, year of publication, patient group/stage of disease, methodology, and main outcomes of interest are assembled using the studies identified in the literature search. Existing guidelines on the topic are assessed by the KM Specialist using portions of the Appraisal of Guidelines Research and Evaluation (AGREE) II instrument (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agreetrust.org&quot; title=&quot;AGREE Web site&quot;&gt;http://www.agreetrust.org&lt;/a&gt;) and those meeting the minimum requirements are included in the evidence document. Due to limited resources, GURU does not regularly employ the use of multiple reviewers to rank the level of evidence; rather, the methodology portion of the evidence table contains the pertinent information required for the reader to judge for himself the quality of the studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the clinical practice guidelines is included in the Appendix in the original guideline document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guideline development panel, including medical oncologists, radiation oncologists, and breast surgeons, originally developed a patient discharge letter to be sent to patients' referring physicians regarding aspects of follow-up care. Recommendations contained in the physician letter were based largely on the 2005 Canadian Medical Association guidelines on follow-up after treatment for breast cancer, as well as other available guidelines. Subsequently, the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team agreed to develop a formal consensus guideline, with updated recommendations based on more recent evidence from the literature. After a review of existing guidelines, consensus recommendations were agreed upon.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formulating Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The working group members formulated the guideline recommendations based on the evidence synthesized by the Knowledge Management (KM) Specialist during the planning process, blended with expert clinical interpretation of the evidence. As detailed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/hp/if-hp-cancer-guide-utilization-handbook.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;Guideline Utilization Resource Unit Handbook&lt;/a&gt; (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field), the working group members may decide to adopt the recommendations of another institution without any revisions, adapt the recommendations of another institution or institutions to better reflect local practices, or develop their own set of recommendations by adapting some, but not all, recommendations from different guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The degree to which a recommendation is based on expert opinion of the working group and/or the Provincial Tumour Team members is explicitly stated in the guideline recommendations. Similar to the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) methodology for formulating guideline recommendations, the Guideline Utilization Resource Unit (GURU) does not use formal rating schemes for describing the strength of the recommendations, but rather describes, in conventional and explicit language, the type and quality of the research and existing guidelines that were taken into consideration when formulating the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;As compared to physician-led follow-up, nurse-led follow-up has demonstrated high patient satisfaction, no differences in terms of time to recurrence or death, and greater cost-effectiveness. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A cost analysis that included 472 breast cancer patients without distant metastasis after primary treatment and compared four strategies (e.g., three versus six months and routine versus clinical examinations) showed, after a mean follow-up of 4.2 years, that there was no difference in disease-free or overall survival, regardless of strategy. Cost, however, was more than two times greater for more frequent routine follow-up. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guideline was reviewed and endorsed by the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the draft guideline document has been completed, revised, and reviewed by the Knowledge Management Specialist and the working group members, it is sent to all members of the Provincial Tumour Team for review and comment. This step ensures that those intended to use the guideline have the opportunity to review the document and identify potential difficulties for implementation before the guideline is finalized. Depending on the size of the document, and the number of people it is sent to for review, a deadline of one to two weeks will usually be given to submit any feedback. Ideally, this review will occur prior to the annual Provincial Tumour Team meeting, and a discussion of the proposed edits will take place at the meeting. The working group members will then make final revisions to the document based on the received feedback, as appropriate. Once the guideline is finalized, it will be officially endorsed by the Provincial Tumour Team Lead and the Executive Director of Provincial Tumour Programs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsibilities of the physician and cancer care centre regarding follow-up care&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Cancer surveillance is a shared responsibility. Following completion of active medical or radiation oncology treatment, patients may be discharged from the tertiary cancer center back to their primary healthcare provider for ongoing breast cancer surveillance. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Guidance on follow-up care and mechanisms for referral back to tertiary cancer care center should be made available, if required. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;A written care plan recorded by a named health professional with copies sent to the healthcare provider and the patient should be encouraged. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Ideally a health practitioner (i.e., family physician, nurse practitioner, specialist from a breast or genetic clinic, etc.) with experience in clinical breast exam should provide follow-up care to patients who have been treated for early-stage breast cancer. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investigations and surveillance for the follow-up of all patients who have completed active medical or radiation oncology treatment for early-stage breast cancer&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Self-examination:&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Patients may perform self-examination of their breasts and armpits every month. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Clinical examination:&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Components: at minimum, history and physical examination of the breast(s), chest wall, and supraclavicular and axillary nodes, auscultation of the chest, and palpation of the liver. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Frequency: every 6 months for 2 years, then annually. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Imaging tests (for patients with intact breasts) (Note: reconstructed breasts [autologous tissue or implants] do not require any form of imaging surveillance):&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic mammography: annually, performed at an accredited mammography facility. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Other routine investigations (e.g., bone scan, ultrasound of the abdomen, chest x-ray, breast magnetic resonance imaging [MRI], tumour markers, and laboratory tests, etc.) are generally not recommended for asymptomatic patients. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signs and symptoms to look for regarding a breast cancer recurrence&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patients should be counseled on symptoms of potential recurrence (i.e., new lumps, bone pain, chest pain, persistent headaches, dyspnea, or abdominal pain). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patients should be informed on the use/limitations of monthly breast self-exam. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;The table below describes signs and symptoms that may suggest recurrence. Patients presenting with any of these symptoms should undergo the appropriate investigations, as described, with a copy of the results to be forwarded to the cancer centre.&#xA;        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table. Symptoms and Appropriate Investigations for a Local Recurrence or Metastatic Disease&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;        &lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Symptoms and Appropriate Investigations for a Local Recurrence or Metastatic Disease&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Symptom&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Action/Investigation&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New mass in breast&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Mammography +/- ultrasound (+/- biopsy)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New suspicious rash or nodule on chest wall&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Refer to surgeon or interventional radiology for biopsy&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New palpable lymphadenopathy&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Refer to surgeon or interventional radiology for biopsy&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New persistent bone pain&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Plain x-ray of affected site(s) and bone scan&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New persistent cough or dyspnea&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Chest x-ray and/or computed tomography (CT) chest&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New hepatomegaly or right upper quadrant (RUQ) abdominal pain&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Ultrasound and/or CT scan of abdomen and liver enzymes&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New onset seizures&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Seizure management (as required) and CT/magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Back pain with limb weakness, change in sensation, change in reflexes, or loss of bowel/bladder control&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;MRI spine&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;New persistent headache or new concerning neurologic deficits&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;CT/MRI brain&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Altered level of consciousness, nausea, vomiting, and/or pain with symptomatic hypercalcemia&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Intravenous (IV) hydration and bisphosphonate therapy&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/table&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;If at any time the physician has concerns regarding possible local or metastatic recurrence and requires an &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;urgent referral&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;appointment booking office&lt;/strong&gt; should be contacted to arrange to see the patient. Should the physician have any specific questions, one of the oncologists in radiation oncology or medical oncology will be available to discuss the patient. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential complications from treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;General Considerations for All Patients&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;For any patient with a history of previous breast cancer, the use of exogenous estrogens (such as oral contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy) is generally contraindicated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Raloxifene is not recommended for treatment of osteoporosis in patients with a previous breast cancer diagnosis while on adjuvant endocrine therapy (e.g., tamoxifen or aromatase inhibitors). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Endocrine Therapy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Adherence to adjuvant endocrine therapy should be assessed and encouraged. &lt;em&gt;The referring physician may write the prescription for the patient, to be dispensed by the cancer centre pharmacy or fax the prescription the cancer center for it to be mailed to the patient.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patients receiving tamoxifen are at a slightly increased risk of deep vein thrombosis, strokes, and cataracts; investigations should be performed, as per signs and symptoms (e.g., sudden swelling or pain in an arm or leg, shortness of breath, visual changes, etc.).&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;More common side effects of tamoxifen include hot flashes and vaginal discharge. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;In patients with an intact uterus, monitoring for endometrial cancer should include a gynecologic assessment, in addition to clinical examination. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Patients experiencing abnormal vaginal bleeding should be referred to a gynecologist. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patients receiving aromatase inhibitors (i.e., anastrozole, exemestane, letrozole) may be at increased risk of joint pain and joint stiffness (especially among those with history of taxane use), bone pain, hot flashes, feeling tired, muscle pain, and insomnia.&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Patients at risk for developing osteopenia and/or osteoporosis should have a baseline and annual bone density assessment (dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry [DEXA] scan) performed. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Osteoporosis should be treated according to the 2010 Canadian Osteoporosis Guidelines (Papaioannou et al., 2010). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Patients at risk of fracture are recommended to:&#xA;            &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Perform regular weight-bearing, balance and strengthening exercises &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Practice smoking cessation &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Optimize total calcium (dietary and supplements): 1000&amp;ndash;1200 mg per day if postmenopausal (preferably from dietary/food sources) &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Optimize total vitamin D (supplements): vitamin D: 1000&amp;ndash;2000 international units (IU) per day (Papaioannou et al., 2010) &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Raloxifene (Evista&amp;reg;) should not be prescribed for osteoporosis treatment in patients with a previous breast cancer diagnosis. In cases where osteopenia/osteoporosis treatment is indicated, consideration for an alternate bone targeted agent (e.g., bisphosphonate or RANK-ligand inhibitor) should be used instead. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fatigue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Long-term follow-up care is important for patients after cancer therapy. Fatigue may be caused by anemia, depression, anxiety, pain, dehydration, nutritional deficiencies, sedating medications, and therapies that may have poorly tolerated side effects (National Cancer Institute, 2011). A history of symptoms should be taken to rule out physical causes. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Psychostimulant drugs, treatment for anemia, exercise, cognitive behavior therapy, activity and rest, or patient education may help patients alleviate the symptoms of fatigue. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peripheral Neuropathy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Chemotherapy may cause damage to nerves, resulting in neuropathy. Symptoms vary depending on the type of chemotherapy and whether sensory or motor nerves are involved, but can include paresthesias, numbness, imbalance, pain, and weakness of muscles in the hands and feet (Emery et al., 2001; Reyes-Gibby et al., 2009). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Work-up should include history and physical exam, as well as neurological exam (e.g., reflexes, muscle strength and tone, sensations, posture, and coordination). Electromyography, nerve biopsy, and computed tomography (CT) or MRI imaging may be indicated (Mayo Clinic, &quot;Diseases,&quot; 2011). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Treatments may include pain relievers (i.e., acetaminophen, ibuprofen, opiates), anti-seizure drugs (i.e., gabapentin, topiramate, pregabalin, carbamazepine, phenytoin), lidocaine (patch), antidepressants (i.e., amitriptyline, nortriptyline) or transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (Mayo Clinic, &quot;Diseases,&quot; 2011). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Alternative techniques, such as acupuncture, capsaicin cream, alpha-lipoic acid, and biofeedback have been used to manage the symptoms of peripheral neuropathy; however, these methods have not been tested rigorously. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lymphedema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Lymphedema or swelling of the arm is a possible complication of breast cancer treatment. It occurs more frequently with mastectomy, axillary lymph node dissection, and radiation therapy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Treatments may include the following:&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Manual lymphatic drainage therapy: a technique that uses massage to move lymph fluid out of the affected limb to functioning lymph nodes for drainage; this technique may be contraindicated in individuals with a skin infection, active cancer, blood clots, and congestive heart failure, as well as on areas of the body that have received radiotherapy (Mayo Clinic, &quot;Lymphedema,&quot; 2011). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Physical therapy or exercise: a technique that uses light muscle contractions of the affected limb to facilitate the drainage of lymph fluid; strenuous exercises should be avoided. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Compression therapy: a technique that uses garments, bandages, or gradient pumps to compress the affected limb and move lymph fluid towards the torso (Mayo Clinic, &quot;Lymphedema,&quot; 2011). Compression therapy may be combined with manual lymphatic drainage and/or physical therapy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Surgery: several procedures, such as lymphatic venous anastomosis, vascularized lymph node transfer, and lymphatic liposuction can be performed to reconstruct the lymphatic vessels or remove lymphedematous tissue. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Low level laser therapy (LLLT): infra-red light is used to displace nitric oxide from the cells and restore the production of cellular energy (adenosine triphosphate [ATP]), allowing tissue to repair; LLLT has been approved by Health Canada, but is still considered experimental. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Programs and services are available in Calgary and Edmonton:&#xA;        &lt;ul&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Calgary: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1026510&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1026510&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Edmonton: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lymphovenous-canada.ca/lymphedemaclinics.htm&quot; title=&quot;Lymphovenous Canada  Web site&quot;&gt;www.lymphovenous-canada.ca/lymphedemaclinics.htm&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cardiac Dysfunction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Cardiac dysfunction can occur in some patients undergoing treatment with anthracycline-based chemotherapy or trastuzumab. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;If patient is symptomatic or has clinical signs, evaluate further with electrocardiogram (ECG) and multigated acquisition scan (MUGA) or echocardiogram and refer to cardiology if significant abnormalities are noted. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acute Leukemia/Myelodysplasia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;In some patients undergoing treatment with chemotherapy, perform a complete blood count (CBC) + differential (peripheral blood smear); refer to hematology if significant persistent cytopenias or blast cells are noted. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Support Resources &amp;amp; Recommendations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patients may experience fear of recurrence, stress over financial, family, or work issues, depression and anxiety, anger over their experience with cancer, or loneliness after support from caregivers is no longer needed. Patients should be assessed for emotional health issues (Waldemar, 2007). Patients often struggle with emotional and psychological concerns post-treatment. Post-treatment adjustment should therefore be assessed, and if problems are identified, treatment and/or referral to an appropriately trained professional should be ensured. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;General support resources:&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;CancerBridges &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cancerbridges.ca&quot; title=&quot;Cancer Bridges Canada Web site&quot;&gt;www.cancerbridges.ca&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Canadian Cancer Society &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cancer.ca&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Cancer Soceity Web site&quot;&gt;http://www.cancer.ca&lt;/a&gt; or 1-888-939-3333. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Wellspring &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wellspring.ca&quot; title=&quot;Wellspring Canada Web site&quot;&gt;www.wellspring.ca&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Alberta Health Services &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;            &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Click: &lt;em&gt;Health Information &amp;gt; Diseases &amp;amp; Conditions &amp;gt; Cancer &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;American Society for Clinical Oncology (patient site): &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cancer.net&quot; title=&quot;ASCO Web site&quot;&gt;http://www.cancer.net&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Counseling and support:&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Psychosocial support should be encouraged and facilitated, as needed. Some patients may benefit by participating in educational, support, or counseling programs, available through the cancer centres and in the community:&#xA;            &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Calgary: call 403-355-3207; or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1047804&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1047804&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Edmonton: call 780-643-4303; 780-643-4304 or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1053260&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1053260&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1003332&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;www.albertahealthservices.ca/services.asp?pid=service&amp;amp;rid=1003332&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Peer Support via Telephone: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cancer.ca/en/support-and-services/support-services/talk-to-someone-who-has-been-there/?region=ab&quot; title=&quot;Cancer Canada Web site&quot;&gt;www.cancer.ca/Alberta-NWT/Support%20Services/AB-Peer%20support%20programs/AB-CancerConnection.aspx&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Healthy Lifestyle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;According to the American Institute for Cancer Research, once treatment for cancer has been completed, and unless otherwise advised, the patient should aim to follow cancer prevention recommendations for diet, physical activity, and healthy weight maintenance (American Institute for Cancer Research, 2011). &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Healthy Lifestyle Table&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Lifestyle Factor&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;                &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendations&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;        &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Body weight (Han et al., 1995; Lean, Han, &amp;amp; Morrison, 1995)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Body mass index (BMI): 18.5&amp;ndash;25 kg/mg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#xA;                &lt;br /&gt;&#xA;                Waist circumference: less than 80 cm for women and less than 94 cm for men.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Physical activity (Canadian Cancer Society, 2011; Beasley et al., 2012; Rock et al., 2012; Kushi et al., 2012)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Be active 2.5 hours/week, focusing on moderate-vigorous activity spread throughout week.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Diet (World Cancer Research Fund/American Institute for Cancer Research, 2007)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Follow cancer prevention recommendations from the American Institute for Cancer Research:&#xA;                &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;li&gt;Avoid sugary drinks. Limit consumption of energy-dense foods. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;li&gt;Eat more of a variety of vegetables, fruits, whole grains and legumes such as beans. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;li&gt;Limit consumption of red meats (beef, pork and lamb) and avoid processed meats. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                    &lt;li&gt;Limit consumption of salty foods and foods processed with salt. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;                &lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Dietary Supplements/Bone Health (Hanley et al., 2010; Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement, 2011; National Guideline Clearinghouse, 2012)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Vitamin D: 1000&amp;ndash;2000 IU per day.&lt;br /&gt;&#xA;                &lt;br /&gt;&#xA;                Calcium: 1000&amp;ndash;1200 mg per day if post-menopausal (preferably from dietary/food sources).&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Alcohol (Bagnardi et al., 2013; Seitz et al., 2012)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Ideally none or limit consumption (&amp;lt;3 drinks/week).&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;            &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Smoking&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;                &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Practice smoking cessation. For help contact Alberta Quits 1-877-710-QUIT (7848) or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertaquits.ca&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Quits Web site&quot;&gt;www.albertaquits.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;            &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/table&gt;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sexual Functioning/Relationships&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Sexual Health&lt;/span&gt;: Common issues for patients include intimacy concerns, painful intercourse or loss of sensation, symptoms of menopause and loss of desire to have sex (Kedde et al., 2013; Panjari, Bell, &amp;amp; Davis, 2011). Sexual functioning should be discussed with the patient at follow-up visits.&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Menopause symptoms: Endocrine therapies commonly cause menopausal symptoms and chemotherapy may lead to early menopause. Hot flashes which interfere with sleep and daily function can be managed with non-hormone therapies (e.g., venlafaxine or gabapentin). Vaginal dryness can be managed with a dual purpose vaginal moisturizer and lubricant (e.g., Replens&amp;reg;). If non-hormonal therapies do not help, vaginal estrogen (Estring&amp;reg;, Vagifem&amp;reg;) can be considered. Exogenous hormonal therapy is generally contraindicated. For refractory vaginal symptoms, referral to gynecology should be considered. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Self-image: For some women, breasts are an important part of their self-image. If they are concerned about how a lumpectomy or mastectomy has changed their body, they may be interested in more information regarding a breast prosthesis or breast reconstruction. Psychological counseling can also be helpful for improving body image satisfaction, addressing relationship concerns and reducing sexual dysfunction. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Family Planning&lt;/span&gt;: Pregnancy while on endocrine therapy is contraindicated. The absence of regular menses does not equate to menopause in all cases. Non-hormonal contraception is generally recommended. There is an increased risk of sub-fertility/infertility and premature menopause in women who have had previous chemotherapy. There is no evidence that future pregnancy adversely affects recurrence or survival; there is no medical reason to terminate a pregnancy in absence of evidence of relapse. &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="98" OrdBy="605" ID="425" Name="References Supporting the Recommendations" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;American Institute for Cancer Research. Second Expert Report, food, nutrition, physical activity, and the prevention of cancer: a global perspective. [internet]. [accessed 2011 Sep 07]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Bagnardi V, Rota M, Botteri E, Tramacere I, Islami F, Fedirko V, Scotti L, Jenab M, Turati F, Pasquali E, Pelucchi C, Bellocco R, Negri E, Corrao G, Rehm J, Boffetta P, La Vecchia C. Light alcohol drinking and cancer: a meta-analysis. Ann Oncol. 2013 Feb;24(2):301-8. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22910838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Beasley JM, Kwan ML, Chen WY, Weltzien EK, Kroenke CH, Lu W, Nechuta SJ, CadmusBertram L, Patterson RE, Sternfeld B, Shu XO, Pierce JP, Caan BJ. Meeting the physical activity guidelines and survival after breast cancer: findings from the after breast cancer pooling project. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2012 Jan;131(2):637-43. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21935600&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Canadian Cancer Society. Eat well, be active. [internet]. 2004 (updated 2011)&amp;nbsp;[accessed 2012 Oct 25]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Emery C, Gallagher R, Hugi M, Levine M, Steering Committee on Clinical Practice Guidelines for the Care and Treatment of Breast Cancer. Clinical practice guidelines for the care and treatment of breast cancer: the management of chronic pain in patients with breast cancer (summary of the 2001 update). CMAJ. 2001 Oct 30;165(9):1218-9. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=11706911&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Han TS, van Leer EM, Seidell JC, Lean ME. Waist circumference action levels in the identification of cardiovascular risk factors: prevalence study in a random sample. BMJ. 1995 Nov 25;311(7017):1401-5. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8520275&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hanley DA, Cranney A, Jones G, Whiting SJ, Leslie WD, Cole DE, Atkinson SA, Josse RG, Feldman S, Kline GA, Rosen C, Guidelines Committee of the Scientific Advisory Council of Osteoporosis Canada. Vitamin D in adult health and disease: a review and guideline statement from Osteoporosis Canada. CMAJ. 2010 Sep 7;182(12):E610-8. [85 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=20624868&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement (ICSI). Diagnosis and treatment of osteoporosis. [internet]. Bloomington (MN): Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement (ICSI); 2011&amp;nbsp;[accessed 2012 Oct 23]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kedde H, van de Wiel HB, Weijmar Schultz WC, Wijsen C. Sexual dysfunction in young women with breast cancer. Support Care Cancer. 2013 Jan;21(1):271-80. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22714701&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kushi LH, Doyle C, McCullough M, Rock CL, Demark-Wahnefried W, Bandera EV, Gapstur S, Patel AV, Andrews K, Gansler T, American Cancer Society 2010 Nutrition and Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory. American Cancer Society guidelines on nutrition and physical activity for cancer  prevention: reducing the risk of cancer with healthy food choices and physical activity. CA Cancer J Clin. 2012 Jan-Feb;62(1):30-67. [376 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22237782&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Lean ME, Han TS, Morrison CE. Waist circumference as a measure for indicating need for weight management. BMJ. 1995 Jul 15;311(6998):158-61. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=7613427&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mayo Clinic health information: lymphedema. [internet]. [accessed 2011 Sep 07]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mayo Clinic. Diseases and conditions: peripheral neuropathy. [internet]. [accessed 2011 Sep 08]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Cancer Institute. Cancer topics: fatigue. [internet]. [accessed 2011 Sep 07]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC). Osteoporosis: diagnosis, treatment, and fracture prevention. In: National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC). [Web site]. Rockville (MD): Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ); [accessed 2012 Oct 24]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Panjari M, Bell RJ, Davis SR. Sexual function after breast cancer. J Sex Med. 2011 Jan;8(1):294-302. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21199377&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Papaioannou A, Morin S, Cheung AM, Atkinson S, Brown JP, Feldman S, Hanley DA, Hodsman A, Jamal SA, Kaiser SM, Kvern B, Siminoski K, Leslie WD, Scientific Advisory Council of Osteoporosis Canada. 2010 clinical practice guidelines for the diagnosis and management of osteoporosis in Canada: summary. CMAJ. 2010 Nov 23;182(17):1864-73. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=20940232&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Reyes-Gibby CC, Morrow PK, Buzdar A, Shete S. Chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy as a predictor of neuropathic pain in breast cancer patients previously treated with paclitaxel. J Pain. 2009 Nov;10(11):1146-50. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=19595634&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Rock CL, Doyle C, Demark-Wahnefried W, Meyerhardt J, Courneya KS, Schwartz AL, Bandera EV, Hamilton KK, Grant B, McCullough M, Byers T, Gansler T. Nutrition and physical activity guidelines for cancer survivors. CA Cancer J Clin. 2012 Jul-Aug;62(4):243-74. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22539238&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Seitz HK, Pelucchi C, Bagnardi V, La Vecchia C. Epidemiology and pathophysiology of alcohol and breast cancer: Update 2012. Alcohol Alcohol. 2012 May-Jun;47(3):204-12. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22459019&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Waldemar G, Dubois B, Emre M, Georges J, McKeith IG, Rossor M, Scheltens P, Tariska P, Winblad B, EFNS. Recommendations for the diagnosis and management of Alzheimer's disease and other disorders associated with dementia: EFNS guideline. Eur J Neurol. 2007 Jan;14(1):e1-26. [253 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=17222085&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;World Cancer Research Fund, American Institute for Cancer Research. Food, nutrition, physical activity, and the prevention of cancer: a global perspective. [internet]. 2007&amp;nbsp;[accessed 2012 Oct 25]. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate follow-up care for patients with early-stage breast cancer to detect recurrent or new breast cancer, to provide patient support (i.e., patient education, reassurance, and psychosocial support), and to monitor the efficacy and side effects of any adjuvant therapy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients receiving tamoxifen are at a slightly increased risk of deep vein thrombosis, strokes, and cataracts; investigations should be performed, as per signs and symptoms (e.g., sudden swelling or pain in an arm or leg, shortness of breath, visual changes, etc.). More common side effects of tamoxifen include hot flashes and vaginal discharge. Monitoring for endometrial cancer should include a gynecologic assessment, in addition to clinical examination. Patients experiencing abnormal vaginal bleeding should be referred to a gynecologist. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients receiving aromatase inhibitors (i.e., anastrozole, exemestane, letrozole) may be at increased risk of joint pain and joint stiffness (especially among those with history of taxane use), bone pain, hot flashes, feeling tired, muscle pain, and insomnia. These patients are also at risk for osteoporosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Chemotherapy may cause damage to nerves, resulting in neuropathy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Lymphedema or swelling of the arm is a possible complication of breast cancer treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cardiac dysfunction can occur in some patients undergoing treatment with anthracycline-based chemotherapy or trastuzumab. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients often struggle with emotional and psychological concerns post-treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;There is an increased risk of sub-fertility/infertility and premature menopause in women who have had previous chemotherapy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;For any patient with a history of previous breast cancer, the use of exogenous estrogens (such as oral contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy) is generally contraindicated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manual lymphatic drainage therapy (a technique that uses massage to move lymph fluid out of the affected limb to functioning lymph nodes for drainage) may be contraindicated in individuals with a skin infection, active cancer, blood clots, and congestive heart failure, as well as on areas of the body that have received radiotherapy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exogenous hormonal therapy is generally contraindicated for menopause symptoms. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Pregnancy while on endocrine therapy is contraindicated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Raloxifene (Evista&amp;reg;) should not be prescribed for osteoporosis treatment in patients with a previous breast cancer diagnosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations contained in this guideline are a consensus of the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team and are a synthesis of currently accepted approaches to management, derived from a review of relevant scientific literature. Clinicians applying these guidelines should, in consultation with the patient, use independent medical judgment in the context of individual clinical circumstances to direct care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Present the guideline at the local and provincial tumour team meetings and weekly rounds. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Post the guideline on the Alberta Health Services Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Send an electronic notification of the new guideline to all members of CancerControl Alberta. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team. Follow-up care for early-stage breast cancer. Edmonton (Alberta): CancerControl Alberta; 2013 May. 26 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical practice guideline; no. BR-013).&amp;nbsp; [120 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2013 May" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="CancerControl Alberta - State/Local Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;CancerControl Alberta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team include medical oncologists, radiation oncologists, surgeons, nurses, pathologists, and pharmacists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participation of members of the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team in the development of this guideline has been voluntary and the authors have not been remunerated for their contributions. There was no direct industry involvement in the development or dissemination of this guideline. CancerControl Alberta recognizes that although industry support of research, education and other areas is necessary in order to advance patient care, such support may lead to potential conflicts of interest. Some members of the Alberta Provincial Breast Tumour Team are involved in research funded by industry or have other such potential conflicts of interest. However the developers of this guideline are satisfied it was developed in an unbiased manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/hp/if-hp-cancer-guide-br013-early-stage-follow-up.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;Alberta Health Services Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Guideline utilization resource unit handbook. Edmonton (Alberta): CancerControl Alberta; 2013 Jan. 5 p. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albertahealthservices.ca/hp/if-hp-cancer-guide-utilization-handbook.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Alberta Health Services Web site&quot;&gt;Alberta Health Services Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on August 12, 2014. The information was verified by the guideline developer on September 22, 2014. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on September 21, 2015 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on non-aspirin nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
