<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 40 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 197).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Atrial fibrillation  (427.31)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Amiodarone ; Atrial Fibrillation "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Atrial Fibrillation "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Amiodarone  (372821002); Amiodarone  (69236009); Atrial fibrillation  (49436004); Dronedarone  (443195003); Dronedarone  (443310000)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-permanent atrial fibrillation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Cardiology" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with non-permanent atrial fibrillation whose atrial fibrillation is not controlled by first-line therapy (usually including beta-blockers), who do not have unstable New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV heart failure, and who have at least one of the following cardiovascular risk factors:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hypertension requiring drugs of at least two different classes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Diabetes mellitus &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Previous transient ischaemic attack, stroke, or systemic embolism &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Left atrial diameter of 50 mm or greater &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40% &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Age 70 years or older &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dronedarone as second-line treatment in selected patients&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical effectiveness&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;All-cause mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Atrial fibrillation recurrence &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Stroke &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Cardiac events &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Treatment withdrawals &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Adverse events of treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Health-related quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by Centre for Reviews and Dissemination (CRD), Centre for Health Economics (CHE) (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description of Manufacturer's Search Strategy and Comment on Whether the Search Strategy Was Appropriate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer's submission described the search strategies used to identify relevant studies of dronedarone for atrial fibrillation/atrial flutter (AF/AFL), and full details of the search strategies used in each section were reported in the appendices or in supplementary material provided. Overall, the search strategies employed for each of the sections of the submission were appropriate. A detailed commentary of the search strategies employed is given in Appendix 1 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statement of the Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria Used in the Study Selection and Comment on Whether They Were Appropriate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Within the submission, the trials of dronedarone are presented separately from the review of dronedarone and comparators. The detailed presentation of the dronedarone trials focuses on 4 phase III randomised controlled trials (RCTs) of dronedarone (EURIDIS/ADONIS, ATHENA and DIONYSOS). These four trials are in the licensed indication and provide data on the efficacy and safety of dronedarone. Additionally, one phase II dose ranging study (DAFNE) and one phase III trial of dronedarone in patients with permanent AF (ERATO), which are not discussed in detail in the submission, provide data on treatment discontinuations and safety of dronedarone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The comparative review of dronedarone and other&amp;nbsp;anti-arrhythmic drugs (AADs) presented in the submission is based on a broader systematic review and meta-analysis commissioned by the manufacturer. This broader review encompassed class 1a, class 1c, class III, class II, class IV drugs and digoxin, and ablation. Within this broader review, dronedarone, amiodarone, sotalol, flecainide and propafenone were identified as 'priority drugs' and the review was based on 72 RCTs that involved at least one priority drug treatment arm. Although this is not clearly stated in the submission, only comparisons of these priority drugs with a non-active control or another priority drug were included in the meta-analysis presented in the submission (a total of 39 trials). Thus, only trials of dronedarone, amiodarone, sotalol, flecainide and propafenone versus placebo, no treatment, or each other are included.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer's submission states that the systematic review of clinical effectiveness included RCTs and controlled trials, although the systematic review submitted as supplementary material to the ERG itself states that only RCTs were included.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Outcomes of interest included mortality, stroke, AF recurrence, treatment withdrawals (due to any cause and due to adverse effects) and serious adverse effects (SAEs).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The intervention criteria were appropriate given current NICE guidelines for the treatment of AF. The use of data from RCTs only was appropriate as this is likely to provide the most reliable estimates of efficacy and safety. However, the inclusion of participants with any type of AF was inappropriate given that the anticipated licensed indication for dronedarone was for non-permanent AF, i.e., paroxysmal and persistent AF, rather than permanent AF. The omission of health-related quality of life as an outcome deviates from the inclusion criteria stipulated in systematic review protocol, and the appraisal scope.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The search strategy was described in the manufacturer's submission to identify published cost-effectiveness studies for dronedarone and for the comparators (amiodarone, sotalol and class 1c). The manufacturer searched a variety of electronic databases including Medline, Medline (R) In Process, Embase, Health Economic Evaluation Database and the National Health Service Economic Evaluation Database (NHS EED).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A total of 15 studies were considered to be eligible for the systematic review. However, all 15 studies evaluated the cost-effectiveness of the comparator treatment and no cost-effectiveness studies of dronedarone were identified. The manufacturer did not consider these studies to be directly relevant to the decision problem, and no further details of these were reported in the main submission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A total of 39 publications that reported data from 6 randomised controlled trials (RCTs) were used in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;No cost-effectiveness studies of dronedarone were identified. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The manufacturer submitted an economic model. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by the Centre for Reviews and Dissemination (CRD), Centre for Health Economics (CHE) (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description and Critique of Manufacturer's Approach to Validity Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The systematic review protocol stated that the quality of the randomised controlled trials (RCTs) was to be assessed according to adequacy of randomisation, allocation concealment, blinding procedures, follow-up, and the use of intention to treat analysis. However, neither the manufacturer's submission nor the supporting systematic review provides any details of the validity assessment of the included RCTs, or utilises study validity in their analyses. Whilst data from RCTs can represent the best available evidence, the absence of a validity assessment means that it is not possible to determine the reliability of the data used in the analyses. In particular, in this submission, the lack of information on the comparator trials makes a lack of a quality assessment particularly important. This is because the quality of the trials should be considered when deciding whether they can be combined in a meta-analysis or mixed treatment comparison (MTC).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Describe and Critique the Statistical Approach Used&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;RCTs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The methods of analysis for the dronedarone trials are generally good. In most cases appropriate intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis was used. A number of post-hoc analyses of additional outcomes and subgroups from the ATHENA trial were reported.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The methods of analysis used in the comparator trials cannot be commented upon, as no details were supplied in the submission or the supporting systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Direct and Indirect Comparisons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The methods of the direct and indirect statistical (meta) analysis are not reported in the manufacturer's submission but are detailed in the supporting systematic review. However, it should be noted that the methods were not previously specified in the systematic review protocol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MTC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No details of the methods used to perform the MTC analysis were included in the submission. The full report supplied on request by the manufacturer contained only limited details of the methods. Some further limited information was supplied by the company upon further request regarding issues of model convergence and a new methods section, which better explained the difference between the methods used and Bayesian methods utilising WinBUGs methods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When interpreting the results from any MTC, it is crucial to understand the network of trials that were included. Although the data included in the final MTC analyses were supplied to the ERG, and the ERG were able to construct network diagrams for each outcome, not all trials comprising the data set for each outcome were included in the MTC.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critique of Submitted Evidence Syntheses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Results are presented for atrial fibrillation (AF) recurrence, all-cause mortality, treatment discontinuation (any cause), treatment discontinuation (adverse effects [AEs]), and stroke. Results are presented for all three types of analyses (where available): direct, indirect, and MTC.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ERG have identified which trials are included in each comparison synthesis and have attempted, from the limited information available in the submission and the supporting systematic review, to identify some of the potential problems and limitations of these analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 4 of the ERG report for additional information and critique of the manufacturer's methodology.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview of Manufacturer's Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer evaluated the cost-effectiveness of dronedarone in two separate positions:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: lower-roman;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;For patients with multiple cardiovascular (CV) risk factors (corresponding to a clinical prediction rule for estimating risk of stroke in patients with AF [CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] &amp;ge;4) on top of standard baseline therapy (including anti-coagulation and beta blockers in line with current UK clinical guidelines and referred to within these guidelines as 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; line treatment) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;For patients when it is considered appropriate to introduce an anti-arrhythmic drug (AAD), as a first line alternative to current AADs. The manufacturer notes that this position is referred to within current UK guidelines as 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; line treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To establish the cost-effectiveness in these two separate clinical positions, dronedarone was compared with a range of alternative therapeutic options (including standard care, class 1c, sotalol and amiodarone). The choice of comparator was dependent upon both the clinical position, the clinical AF type, and baseline risk factors in line with clinical guidelines and are outlined schematically in the manufacturer's submission.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A model-based cost utility analysis was carried out using discrete event simulation (DES). The model includes four main health states (normal sinus rhythm, permanent atrial fibrillation with uncontrolled symptoms, permanent atrial fibrillation with controlled symptoms, and death). Movements between these main health states were driven by events. A total of seven events were included (AF recurrence, acute coronary syndrome [ACS], stroke, congestive heart failure [CHF], treatment discontinuation for any cause, AF symptoms change for permanent patient and death) to capture the range of possible clinical pathways for the patient population.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Patients were stratified in the model according to their clinical AF type and the baseline risk factors in line with UK guidelines. Five main patient groups were considered:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Paroxysmal AF patients with no structural heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Paroxysmal AF patients with coronary heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Paroxysmal AF patients with left ventricular (LV) dysfunction &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Persistent AF patients with no structural heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Persistent AF patients with structural heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition to these main groups of patients, a range of additional subgroup analyses were also performed in the economic evaluation including: age, CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; score, and gender. The choice of subgroups was considered by the manufacturer to be the most clinically relevant groups to be analysed in accordance with the approach employed in current UK clinical guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sensitivity Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Both univariate and probabilistic sensitivity analyses (PSA) were undertaken by the manufacturer. A full list of parameters (and their associated distributions) included in the PSA are reported in the manufacturer's submission. The main sources of parameter uncertainty considered in the PSA were: (1) the time to event equations, (2) treatment effect estimates, (3) the increased risk of all-cause mortality due to CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, (4) post-stoke mortality, (5) utilities assigned to the main events and (6) costs (AF hospitalisation, ablation and initiation costs).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A detailed series of univariate sensitivity analyses were also undertaken to explore a range of alternative scenarios. These are summarised in Table 18 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 5 of the ERG report for additional information on the economic analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technology appraisal recommendations are based on a review of clinical and economic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology Appraisal Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) invites 'consultee' and 'commentator' organisations to take part in the appraisal process. Consultee organisations include national groups representing patients and carers, the bodies representing health professionals, and the manufacturers of the technology under review. Consultees are invited to submit evidence during the appraisal and to comment on the appraisal documents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Commentator organisations include manufacturers of the products with which the technology is being compared, the National Health Service (NHS) Quality Improvement Scotland and research groups working in the area. They can comment on the evidence and other documents but are not asked to submit evidence themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE then commissions an independent academic centre to review published evidence on the technology and prepare an 'assessment report'. Consultees and commentators are invited to comment on the report. The assessment report and the comments on it are then drawn together in a document called the evaluation report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An independent Appraisal Committee then considers the evaluation report. It holds a meeting where it hears direct, spoken evidence from nominated clinical experts, patients and carers. The Committee uses all the evidence to make its first recommendations, in a document called the 'appraisal consultation document' (ACD). NICE sends all the consultees and commentators a copy of this document and posts it on the NICE website. Further comments are invited from everyone taking part.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the Committee meets again it considers any comments submitted on the ACD; then it prepares its final recommendations in a document called the 'final appraisal determination' (FAD). This is submitted to NICE for approval.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consultees have a chance to appeal against the final recommendations in the FAD. If there are no appeals, the final recommendations become the basis of the guidance that NICE issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Is on the Appraisal Committee?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE technology appraisal recommendations are prepared by an independent committee. This includes health professionals working in the NHS and people who are familiar with the issues affecting patients and carers. Although the Appraisal Committee seeks the views of organisations representing health professionals, patients, carers, manufacturers and government, its advice is independent of any vested interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model used in the manufacturer's cost-effectiveness analysis was a discrete event simulation that predicts a person's course if they are treated with dronedarone compared with the predicted course with alternative treatment pathways. The manufacturer stratified people depending on their type of atrial fibrillation and baseline risk factors into five groups in accordance with the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) guidance on atrial fibrillation (NICE clinical guideline 36): paroxysmal atrial fibrillation without structural heart disease, paroxysmal atrial fibrillation with coronary heart disease, paroxysmal atrial fibrillation with left ventricular dysfunction, persistent atrial fibrillation without structural heart disease, and persistent atrial fibrillation with structural heart disease. For each of these subgroups, the manufacturer evaluated the cost-effectiveness of dronedarone at two positions in the care pathway for atrial fibrillation. When dronedarone was evaluated as part of a first-line treatment for people with a&amp;nbsp;clinical prediction rule for estimating risk of stroke in patients with AF (CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) score of 4 or more (in addition to standard baseline therapy), the comparator was standard baseline therapy alone (including beta-blockers [excluding sotalol] and anticoagulation). When dronedarone was evaluated as a second-line treatment option, the comparators were the antiarrhythmic drugs amiodarone, sotalol and class 1c drugs, depending on the type of atrial fibrillation and baseline risk factors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Committee discussed the cost-effectiveness of dronedarone as a first-line treatment for atrial fibrillation (in addition to standard baseline therapy usually including beta-blockers). It noted that cost-effectiveness evidence for dronedarone as a first-line therapy had only been provided for the subgroup of people with a CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; score of 4 or more. In addition to concerns about the validity of the CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; score in this context, the Committee considered that the beneficial effect of dronedarone on all-cause mortality assumed in the manufacturer's submission was not proven. It noted that when this effect was removed from the economic analysis, the cost per quality-adjusted life-year (QALY) gained was above &amp;pound;50,000. The Committee concluded that the use of dronedarone in people with a CHADS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; score of 4 or more (in addition to standard baseline therapy) for the first-line treatment of atrial fibrillation could not be considered a cost-effective use of National Health Service (NHS) resources.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Committee discussed the cost-effectiveness of dronedarone as a second-line treatment for people whose atrial fibrillation is not controlled by standard baseline therapy (that is, as an alternative to the antiarrhythmic drugs: amiodarone, sotalol and class 1c agents). It considered that a beneficial effect of dronedarone on all-cause mortality was not proven; however, it accepted that the risk of mortality with the other antiarrhythmic drugs was likely to be higher than with dronedarone. The Committee concluded that using dronedarone as a second-line alternative to amiodarone, class 1c drugs, or sotalol for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation could be considered a cost-effective use of the NHS resources in people who have the same characteristics as the population in the ATHENA trial; that is, they have at least one of the following additional cardiovascular risk factors: hypertension requiring drugs of at least two different classes, diabetes, previous transient ischaemic attack, stroke or systemic embolism, left atrial diameter at least 50 mm, left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40%, or age 70 years or older.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Sections 3 and 4 of the original guideline document for a detailed discussion of the cost-effectiveness analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultee organisations from the following groups were invited to comment on the draft scope, Assessment Report and the Appraisal Consultation Document (ACD) and were provided with the opportunity to appeal against the Final Appraisal Determination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manufacturer/sponsors &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Professional/specialist and patient/carer groups &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Commentator organisations (without the right of appeal) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, individuals selected from clinical expert and patient advocate nominations from the professional/specialist and patient/carer groups were also invited to comment on the ACD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by Centre for Reviews and Dissemination (CRD), Centre for Health Economics (CHE) (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dronedarone is recommended as an option for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; in people:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Whose atrial fibrillation is not controlled by first-line therapy (usually including beta-blockers), that is, as a second-line treatment option, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Who have at least one of the following cardiovascular risk factors:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Hypertension requiring drugs of at least two different classes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Diabetes mellitus &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Previous transient ischaemic attack, stroke or systemic embolism &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Left atrial diameter of 50 mm or greater &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40% (noting that the summary of product characteristics [SPC] does not recommend dronedarone for people with left ventricular ejection fraction less than 35% because of limited experience of using it in this group) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Age 70 years or older, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Who do not have unstable New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV heart failure. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People who do not meet the criteria in the section above who are currently receiving dronedarone should have the option to continue treatment until they and their clinicians consider it appropriate to stop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Appraisal Committee considered clinical and cost-effectiveness evidence submitted by the manufacturer of dronedarone and reviews of these submissions by the Evidence Review Group. For clinical effectiveness, the Committee mainly considered evidence from randomised controlled trials. For cost-effectiveness, the Committee considered an economic analysis submitted by the manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;According to the summary of product characteristics (SPC), the most frequently observed adverse events in people receiving dronedarone are elevated blood creatinine levels and prolongation of the QT interval. Other common adverse events include bradycardia, gastrointestinal events such as diarrhoea and vomiting, rashes, pruritus, fatigue and asthenia. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;There is also a recommendation in the SPC (under 'special warnings and precautions for use') which states that because of limited experience in stable patients with recent (1 to 3 months) New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III heart failure or with left ventricular ejection fraction less than 35%, the use of dronedarone is not recommended in these patients. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects and contraindications, see the SPC.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The summary of product characteristics (SPC) states that because of the unexplained results of the ANDROMEDA study, the use of dronedarone in unstable patients with New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III and IV heart failure is contraindicated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects and contraindications, see the SPC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. The guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way which would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State and the Welsh Assembly Minister for Health and Social Services have issued directions to the National Health Service (NHS) on implementing National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) technology appraisal guidance. When a NICE technology appraisal recommends use of a drug or treatment, or other technology, the NHS must usually provide funding and resources for it within 3 months of the guidance being published. If the Department of Health issues a variation to the 3-month funding direction, details will be available on the NICE website. When there is no NICE technology appraisal guidance on a drug, treatment or other technology, decisions on funding should be made locally.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE has developed tools to help organisations put this guidance into practice (listed below). These are available on the NICE website (&lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Costing report and costing template to estimate the savings and costs associated with implementation. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Audit support for monitoring local practice. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 40 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 197).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2010 Aug" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appraisal Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Dr Darren Ashcroft, Senior Clinical Lecturer, School of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Manchester; Dr Brian Buckley, Lay member; Mark Campbell, Director of Standards, Bury Primary Care Trust; Professor Usha Chakravarthy, Professor of Ophthalmology and Vision Sciences, The Queen's University of Belfast; Professor Peter Clark (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Consultant Medical Oncologist, Clatterbridge Centre for Oncology; Dr Ian Davidson, Lecturer in Rehabilitation, University of Manchester; Professor Simon Dixon, Professor of Health Economics, University of Sheffield; Dr Martin Duerden, Medical Director, Conwy Local Health Board; Dr Alexander Dyker, Consultant Physician, Wolfson Unit of Clinical Pharmacology; Dr Jon Fear, Consultant in Public Health Medicine, Head of Healthcare Effectiveness, NHS Leeds; Paula Ghaneh, Senior Lecturer and Honorary Consultant, University of Liverpool; Susan Griffin, Research Fellow, Centre for Health Economics, University of York; Professor Carol Haigh, Professor in Nursing, Manchester Metropolitan University; Dr Kevin Hardy, Consultant Physician, St Helens &amp;amp; Knowsley Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust; Alison Hawdale, Lay member; Professor John Hutton, Professor of Health Economics, University of York; Professor Peter Jones, Pro Vice Chancellor for Research &amp;amp; Enterprise and Professor of Statistics, Keele University; Dr Vincent Kirkbride, Consultant Neonatologist, Regional Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Sheffield; Rachel Lewis, Practice Development Manager, Manchester Primary Care Trust; Professor Jonathan Michaels (&lt;em&gt;Vice-Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Professor of Vascular Surgery, University of Sheffield; Dr Neil Milner, General Medical Practitioner, Tramways Medical Centre; Professor Oluwafemi Oyebode, Professor of Psychiatry &amp;amp; Consultant Psychiatrist, The National Centre for Mental Health; Mr Mike Pinkerton, Chief of Business Development, The Rotherham NHS Foundation Trust; Dr John Radford, Director of Public Health, Rotherham Primary Care Trust; Dr Phillip Rutledge, Consultant Public Health and Health Policy, NHS Lothian; Dr Stephen Saltissi, Consultant Cardiologist, Royal Liverpool University Hospital; Dr Brian Shine, Consultant Chemical Pathologist, John Radcliffe Hospital; Paddy Storrie, Lay member; Dr Cathryn Patricia Thomas, GP and Associate Professor, University of Birmingham; Mr Mike Wallace, Health Economics &amp;amp; Reimbursement Director, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson Medical Ltd; Dr Lok Yap, Consultant in Acute Medicine &amp;amp; Clinical Pharmacology, Whittington Hospitals NHS Trust&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Committee members are asked to declare any interests in the technology to be appraised. If it is considered there is a conflict of interest, the member is excluded from participating further in that appraisal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation. Quick reference guide. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 2 p. (Technology appraisal 197). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197/QuickRefGuide/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dronedarone for the treatment of non-permanent atrial fibrillation. Audit support. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010. 6 p. (Technology appraisal 197). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197/AuditSupport/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Atrial fibrillation - dronedarone. Costing template. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Oct. (Technology appraisal 197). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197/CostingTemplate/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dronedarone for atrial fibrillation and atrial flutter. Evidence review group report. Centre for Reviews and Dissemination and Centre for Health Economics; 2009 Dec. 136 p. Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=46777&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dronedarone for non-permanent atrial fibrillation. Understanding NICE guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 4 p. (Technology appraisal 197). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=50472&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in Welsh from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA197/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on March 9, 2011. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on December 21, 2011 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory on Multaq (dronedarone).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their Technology Appraisal guidance with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects the original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE technology appraisal guidance is prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
