<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Clinical Guideline Centre. Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Feb. 38 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical guideline; no. 114).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline has been updated. The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) is working to update this summary. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Anemia, unspecified  (285.9); Chronic kidney disease, unspecified  (585.9); End stage renal disease  (585.6); Hemodialysis  (39.95); Hyperparathyroidism, unspecified  (252.00)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Androgens ; Anemia ; Ascorbic Acid ; Blood Chemical Analysis ; Blood Transfusion ; Carnitine ; Chronic Disease ; Culture ; Drug Resistance ; Folic Acid ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Hematinics ; Hyperparathyroidism ; Kidney Diseases ; Kidney Failure, Chronic ; Medication Therapy Management ; Patient Education as Topic ; Patient Satisfaction ; Patient-Centered Care ; Renal Insufficiency, Chronic ; Renal Replacement Therapy "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Androgens ; Anemia ; Anemia of chronic disease ; Anthropological Culture ; Ascorbic Acid ; Blood Chemical Analysis ; Blood Transfusion ; Carnitine ; Chronic disease ; Chronic Kidney Diseases ; Chronic Kidney Insufficiency ; Client satisfaction ; Drug resistance ; Erythropoietin measurement ; Folic Acid ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Hematinics ; Hemodialysis ; Hemoglobin measurement ; Iron Compounds, Inorganic ; Kidney Diseases ; Kidney Failure, Chronic ; Patient education (procedure) ; Serum ferritin measurement "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: anemia ; ascorbic acid ; folic acid "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Androgen  (66349002); Androgen  (84629008); Anemia  (271737000); Anemia of chronic disease  (234347009); Ascorbic acid  (43706004); Ascorbic acid  (46123006); Blood chemistry  (166312007); Carnitine  (59888006); Chronic disease  (27624003); Chronic renal impairment  (236425005); Client satisfaction  (406193000); Drug resistance  (31438003); End stage renal disease  (46177005); End stage renal disease  (90688005); Erythropoietin measurement  (43979001); Folic acid  (6247001); Folic acid  (63718003); Glomerular filtration rate  (80274001); Hematinic  (24036003); Hematinic  (259699009); Hemodialysis  (302497006); Hyperparathyroidism  (66999008); Kidney disease  (90708001); Patient education  (311401005); Serum ferritin measurement  (269821003); Transfusion of blood product  (116859006)"/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Hemodialysis Units, Renal  (24-896); Hemodialysis Units, Renal, Continuous Replacement Therapy  (23-426)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anaemia of chronic kidney disease&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Geriatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Hematology" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Nephrology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Pharmacology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Allied Health Personnel" /><FieldValue Value="Health Care Providers" /><FieldValue Value="Health Plans" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Patients" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /><FieldValue Value="Public Health Departments" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2006 Guideline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To provide a user-friendly, clinical, evidence-based guideline for the National Health Service (NHS) that:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Offers best clinical advice for anaemia management in chronic kidney disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Is based on best published evidence and expert consensus &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Takes into account patient choice and informed decision-making &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Defines the major components of NHS care provision for anaemia of chronic kidney disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Indicates areas suitable for clinical audit &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Details areas of uncertainty or controversy requiring further research &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Provides a choice of guideline versions for differing audiences &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2011 Guideline Update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To update recommendations on anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults and children with a clinical diagnosis of anaemia associated with chronic kidney disease (CKD), including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Those with pre-dialysis CKD &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Those with established renal failure receiving renal replacement therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Those with established renal failure receiving conservative management &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;After renal transplant surgery &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Groups that are not covered include those for whom CKD is not the principal cause of the anaemia, for example anemia caused by:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul class=&quot;contentListFont&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Haematological disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Acute and chronic inflammatory disease states &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Malignancy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Acute kidney injury &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnosis/Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Investigation of haemoglobin (Hb) levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Investigation of estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Tests to determine iron status (serum ferritin levels) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management/Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESAs), including consideration of:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patient preference &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Route of administration &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Dose and frequency &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Adjusting ESA therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Optimal Hb levels (determining individual aspirational Hb ranges) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Iron supplements (oral and intravenous) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treatment of clinically relevant hyperparathyroidism &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Blood transfusion &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Maintenance of stable Hb levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Monitoring of iron status and Hb levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Detecting ESA resistance &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Managing ESA resistance &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Use of patient-centred care, including&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Provision of information to patient and general practitioner (GP) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Protocols defining roles and responsibilities of healthcare professionals in primary and secondary care &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Consideration of patient preferences about supervised- or self-administration, dose frequency, pain on injection, method of supplying ESA, and storage &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Provision of culturally and age-appropriate patient education programmes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The following were considered but not recommended include measurement of erythropoietin levels; supplements of vitamin C, folic acid or carnitine; and androgens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;All-cause mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cardiovascular mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Stroke &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Myocardial infarction &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Left ventricular hypertrophy/left ventricular mass index &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Quality of life indices &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Progression of chronic kidney disease in non-dialysis patients &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Access thrombosis (haemodialysis patients) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hypertension/blood pressure control &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reduction in transfusion requirements &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Haemoglobin variability &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increased hospitalisation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Quality adjusted life years &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre on behalf of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Searching for Evidence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Systematic literature searches were undertaken to identify evidence from 2005 onwards within the published literature in order to answer the review questions as per the Guidelines Manual 2009. Clinical databases were searched using relevant medical subject headings, free-text terms and study type filters where appropriate. Studies published in languages other than English were not reviewed. Where possible, searches were restricted to articles published in the English language. Searches were conducted in core databases, MEDLINE, EMBASE, CINAHL, and the Cochrane Library. All searches were updated on 8th July 2010. No papers after this date were considered. Search strategies were checked against search strategies in the original guideline, reference lists of relevant key papers, search strategies in other systematic reviews and asking the guideline development group (GDG) for known studies. Searching for grey literature or unpublished literature was not undertaken. The questions, the study types applied, the databases searched and the years covered can be found in Appendix A in the full version of the original guideline document. See the review protocols in Appendix G of the full version of the original guideline document for inclusion/exclusion criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See section 2.12 of the full version of the original guideline document for information on requests for additional data.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence of Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Research Fellow identified potentially relevant studies for each review question from the search results by reviewing titles and abstracts &amp;ndash; full papers were then obtained. Full papers were reviewed against pre-specified inclusion and exclusion criteria to identify studies that addressed the review question in the appropriate population and reported on outcomes of interest (review protocols are included in Appendix G of the full version of the original guideline document).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Economic Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Systematic literature searches were also undertaken to identify health economic evidence within the published literature relevant to the review questions published since the original guideline. The evidence was identified by conducting a broad search relating to anaemia management in chronic kidney disease in the National Health Service (NHS) Economic Evaluation Database (NHS EED), the Health Economic Evaluations Database (HEED) and Health Technology Assessment (HTA) databases from 2005 onwards (the cut-off date for the original guideline was 28th September 2005). Additionally, the search was run in Medline and EMBASE, with a specific economic filter, from January 2009, to ensure recent publications that had not yet been indexed by the economic databases were identified. Studies published in languages other than English were not reviewed. Where possible, searches were restricted to articles published in English language. All searches were updated on 8th July 2010. No papers published after this date were considered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The health economist:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Identified potentially relevant studies for each review question for the update from the economic search results by reviewing titles and abstracts &amp;ndash; full papers were then obtained &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reviewed full papers against pre-specified inclusion/exclusion criteria to identify relevant studies (see below for details) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Critically appraised relevant studies using the economic evaluations checklist as specified in the Guidelines Manual &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inclusion/Exclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Full economic evaluations (cost-effectiveness, cost-utility, cost-benefit, and cost-consequence analyses) and comparative costing studies that addressed the review question in the relevant population were considered potentially applicable as economic evidence. The same population and intervention criteria were applied as in the clinical review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Studies that only reported cost per hospital (not per patient), or only reported average cost effectiveness without disaggregated costs and effects, were excluded. Abstracts, posters, reviews, letters/editorials, foreign language publications, and unpublished studies were excluded. Studies judged to have an applicability rating of 'not applicable' were excluded (this included studies that took the perspective of a non-Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development [OECD] country).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Remaining studies were prioritised for inclusion based on their relative applicability to the current UK NHS situation and development of this guideline, and the study limitations. For example, if a high quality, directly applicable UK analysis is available other less relevant studies may not be included. Where exclusions occurred on this basis, this is noted in the relevant evidence section.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more details about the assessment of applicability and methodological quality see the economic evaluation checklist (The Guidelines Manual, Appendix H of the full version of the original guideline document) and the health economics research protocol in Appendix G of the full version of the original guideline document.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additional data for the analysis was identified as required through additional literature searches undertaken by the health economist, and discussion with the GDG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Quality of Outcome Evidence in Grades of Recommendation Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High&lt;/strong&gt;: Further research is very unlikely to change confidence in the estimate of the effect &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderate&lt;/strong&gt;: Further research is likely to have an important impact on confidence in the estimate of the effect and may change the estimate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low&lt;/strong&gt;: Further research is very likely to have an important impact on confidence in the estimate of the effect and is likely to change the estimate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Very low&lt;/strong&gt;: Any estimate of effect is very uncertain &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre on behalf of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Evidence of Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Relevant studies were critically appraised using the appropriate checklist as specified in the Guidelines Manual 2009 (see &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Key information about the study's methods and results was extracted into evidence tables (evidence tables are included in Appendix H of the full version of the original guideline document).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Summaries of the evidence by outcome were generated (and included in the relevant chapter write-ups in the full version of the original guideline document).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where appropriate randomised studies were meta-analysed, and reported in Grades of Recommendation Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) profiles (for clinical studies).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods of Combining Clinical Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Synthesis for Intervention Reviews&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where possible, meta-analyses were conducted to combine the results of studies for each review question using Cochrane Review Manager (RevMan5) software. Fixed-effects (Mantel-Haenszel) techniques were used to calculate risk ratios (relative risk) for the binary outcomes. The continuous outcomes were analysed using an inverse variance method for pooling weighted mean differences and where the studies had different scales, standardised mean differences were used. Where reported, time-to-event data was presented as a hazard ratio using the generic invariance method on the Cochrane Review Manger (RevMan5) software. In order to enable pooling with studies that did not report the outcome as a time-to-event, an estimate of the hazard ratio was calculated from the risk ratios using a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet. Statistical heterogeneity was assessed by considering the chi-squared test for significance at p&amp;lt;0.1 or an I-squared inconsistency statistic of &amp;gt;50% to indicate significant heterogeneity. Where significant heterogeneity was present, predefined subgroup analyses for comorbidities (diabetes, heart failure) was carried out. Sensitivity analysis based on the quality of studies was also carried out if there were differences, with particular attention paid to allocation concealment, blinding and loss to follow-up (missing data). In cases where there was inadequate allocation concealment, unclear blinding, more than 50% missing data (if the reason for loss to follow-up was not due to renal replacement therapy) or differential missing data, this was examined in a sensitivity analysis. For the latter, the duration of follow up was also taken into consideration prior to including in a sensitivity analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assessments of potential differences in effect between subgroups were based on the chi-squared tests for heterogeneity statistics between subgroups. If no sensitivity analysis was found to completely resolve statistical heterogeneity then a random effects (DerSimonian and Laird) model was employed to provide a more conservative estimate of the effect.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The means and standard deviations of continuous outcomes were required for meta-analyses. However, in cases where standard deviations were not reported, the standard error was calculated if the p-values or 95% confidence intervals were reported and meta-analysis was undertaken with the mean and standard error using the generic inverse variance method in Cochrane Review Manager (RevMan5) software. Where p values were reported as &quot;less than&quot;, a conservative approach was undertaken. For example, if the p value was reported as &quot;p &amp;le;0.001&quot;, the calculations for standard deviations were based on a p value of 0.001. If these statistical measures were not available then the methods described in section 16.1.3 of the Cochrane Handbook (September 2009) 'Missing standard deviations' were applied as the last resort.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For binary outcomes, absolute event rates were also calculated using the GRADEpro software using event rate in the control arm of the pooled results.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Synthesis for Prognostic Factor Reviews&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Odds ratio, relative risks or hazard ratios, with their 95% confidence intervals, from multivariate analyses were extracted from the papers, and standard errors were calculated from the 95% confidence intervals. The log of the effect size with its standard error was entered into the generic inverse variance technique in the Cochrane Review Manager (RevMan5) software. Studies were not combined in a meta-analysis for cohort studies. Heterogeneity between trials was assessed by visual inspection of forest plots. Where appropriate, sensitivity analyses were carried out on the basis of study quality and results were reported as ranges.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appraising the Quality of Evidence by Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The evidence for outcomes from the included studies were evaluated and presented using an adaptation of the GRADE toolbox developed by the international GRADE working group. The summary of findings was presented as two separate tables in this guideline. The &quot;Clinical/Economic evidence - quality assessment&quot; table includes details of the quality assessment while the &quot;Clinical /Economic - results&quot; table includes pooled outcome data, where appropriate, an absolute measure of intervention effect and the summary of quality of evidence for that outcome. The GRADE toolbox is currently designed only for randomised trials and observational studies and hence does not apply to prognostic or diagnostic studies. See Section 2.14 in the full version of the original guideline document for additional detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After results were pooled, the overall quality of evidence for each outcome was considered. See Section 2.14.1 in the full version of the original guideline document for additional detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evidence was also appraised for study limitations, inconsistency, indirectness, and imprecision. See sections 2.14.2-2.14.5 in the full version of the original guideline document for detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Evidence of Cost Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The health economist:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Critically appraised relevant studies using the economic evaluations checklist as specified in the Guidelines Manual &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Extracted key information about the study's methods and results into evidence tables (evidence tables are included in Appendix H of the full version of the original guideline document) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Generated summaries of the evidence &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Undertaking New Health Economic Analysis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As well as reviewing the published economic literature for each review question in the clinical evidence review, a new economic analysis was undertaken by the health economist in priority areas. Priority areas for new health economic analysis were agreed by the GDG after formation of the review questions and consideration of the available health economic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Model structure, inputs, and assumptions were explained to and agreed by the GDG members during meetings, and they commented on subsequent revisions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See the Health Economic Appendix C in the full version of the original guideline document for details of the health economic analysis undertaken for the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /><FieldValue Value="Informal Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre on behalf of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guidance was developed in accordance with the methods outlined in the NICE Guidelines Manual 2009 (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The guideline has been produced using standard NICE methodology, and is therefore explicitly evidence-linked. Following a comprehensive literature search and evaluation of research papers, a GDG comprising clinical experts and patient and carer representatives assessed the evidence and used it to produce a detailed set of recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing the Review Questions and Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Review questions were developed in a patient, intervention, comparison and outcome (PICO) framework. This was to guide the literature searching process and to facilitate the development of recommendations by the GDG. The PICO questions were drafted by the National Clinical Guideline Centre (NCGC) technical team, refined and validated by the GDG, and based on the key clinical areas identified in the scope. See Table 2.1U in in section 2.11 in the full version of the original guideline document for the PICO framework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the 2006 guideline a cost-effectiveness model looking at the optimal haemoglobin (Hb) target was undertaken. However, the approach taken was judged by the Guideline Development Group (GDG) to no longer be appropriate in light of new clinical data available in the 2011 update. On this basis this analysis was removed from the guideline in the 2011 update.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A new cost-effectiveness analysis based on the randomised controlled trial (RCT) data identified in the clinical review was developed. This compared treating to a target Hb of &amp;lt;12 g/dl and &amp;gt;12 g/dl. Costs and quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) were considered from a National Health Service (NHS) and personal social services perspective. In the base case analysis a 3-year treatment period was considered with the impact of this extrapolated to a lifetime perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The model incorporated differences between the Hb targets in terms of mortality, quality of life, and erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESA) dose based on the RCTs identified in the clinical review of the literature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Results found that treating to a higher target of &amp;gt;12 g/dL was not cost effective when compared to treating to a target &amp;lt;12 g/dL. The lower target 'dominated' the higher target with lower costs and improved health outcomes (higher QALYs). This conclusion was robust to various sensitivity analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See Appendix C of the full version of the original guideline document for a discussion of limitations and interpretation of cost-effectiveness evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generalisability to Other Populations/Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whilst it is difficult to extrapolate from a non-dialysis population to a dialysis population, the available dialysis evidence did not suggest an overall improvement in quality of life over a dialysis population, suggests a similar difference in mortality to non-dialysis patients, and suggests a larger difference in ESA dose than in non-dialysis patients. It was therefore considered unlikely that conclusions would vary in dialysis patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guideline was validated through two consultations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The first draft of the guideline (the full guideline, National Institute for Clinical Excellence [NICE] guideline and Quick Reference Guide) were consulted with stakeholders and comments were considered by the Guideline Development Group (GDG) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The final consultation draft of the full guideline, the NICE guideline and the Information for the Public were submitted to stakeholders for final comments. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The final draft was submitted to the Guideline Review Panel for review prior to publication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline has been updated. The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) is working to update this summary. The recommendations that follow are based on the previous version of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre on behalf of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;New recommendations have been added for the diagnostic evaluation and assessment of anaemia and the assessment and optimisation of erythropoiesis. Recommendations are marked as &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;[2006, amended 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; indicates that the evidence has not been updated and reviewed since 2006. &lt;strong&gt;[2006, amended 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; indicates recommendations where the evidence has not been reviewed since the original guideline but they have been amended because of Guideline Development Group (GDG) consensus that they no longer reflect clinical practice or to add clarity; or recommendations that need amending to be consistent with new recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Diagnostic Evaluation and Assessment of Anaemia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnostic Role of Haemoglobin (Hb) Levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider investigating and managing anaemia in people with chronic kidney disease (CKD) if:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Their Hb level falls to 11 g/dl or less (or 10.5 g/dl or less if younger than 2 years) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;They develop symptoms attributable to anaemia (such as tiredness, shortness of breath, lethargy, and palpitations) &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnostic Role of Glomerular Filtration Rate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of less than 60 ml/min/1.73m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; should trigger investigation into whether anaemia is due to CKD. When the eGFR is greater than or equal to 60 ml/min/1.73m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; the anaemia is more likely to be related to other causes. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnostic Tests to Determine Iron Status&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Serum ferritin levels may be used to assess iron deficiency in people with CKD. Because serum ferritin is an acute-phase reactant and frequently raised in CKD, the diagnostic cut-off value should be interpreted differently to non-CKD patients. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Iron-deficiency anaemia should be:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Diagnosed in people with stage 5 CKD with a ferritin level of less than 100 micrograms/l &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Considered in people with stage 3 and 4 CKD if the ferritin level is less than 100 micrograms/l &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stages of Chronic Kidney Disease&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Stages of Chronic Kidney Disease&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Stage&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;GFR&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            (ml/min/1.73m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;90&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Normal or increased GFR, with other evidence of kidney damage&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;60&amp;ndash;89&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Slight decrease in GFR, with other evidence of kidney damage&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;3a&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;45&amp;ndash;59&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Moderate decrease in GFR, with or without other evidence of kidney damage&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;3b&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;30&amp;ndash;44&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;15&amp;ndash;29&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Severe decrease in GFR, with or without other evidence of kidney damage&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Established renal failure&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Diagnosis should be on the basis of evidence of CKD for &amp;ge;3 months.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;GFR=glomerular filtration rate&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with CKD who have serum ferritin levels greater than 100 micrograms/l, functional iron deficiency (and hence, those patients who are most likely to benefit from intravenous iron therapy) should be defined by:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Percentage of hypochromic red cells greater than 6%, where the test is available &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Transferrin saturation less than 20%, when the measurement of the percentage of hypochromic red cells is unavailable &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurement of Erythropoietin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Measurement of erythropoietin levels for the diagnosis or management of anaemia should not be routinely considered for people with anaemia of CKD. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Management of Anaemia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initiation of Erythropoiesis-Stimulating Agents (ESA) Therapy in Iron-Deficient Patients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ESA therapy should not be initiated in the presence of absolute iron deficiency without also managing the iron deficiency. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with functional iron deficiency, iron supplements should be given concurrently when initiating ESA therapy. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximum Iron Levels in People with Anaemia of CKD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people treated with iron, serum ferritin levels should not rise above 800 micrograms/l. In order to prevent this, the dose of iron should be reviewed when serum ferritin levels reach 500 micrograms/l. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Utility of ESA Therapy in Iron-Replete Patients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pros and cons of a trial of anaemia management should be discussed between the clinician, the person with anaemia of CKD, and their families and carers if applicable. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ESAs need not be administered where the presence of comorbidities, or the prognosis, is likely to negate the benefits of correcting the anaemia. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A trial of anaemia correction should be initiated when there is uncertainty over whether the presence of comorbidities, or the prognosis, would negate benefit from correcting the anaemia with ESAs. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where a trial of ESA therapy has been performed, the effectiveness of the trial should be assessed after an agreed interval. Where appropriate, a mutual decision should be agreed between the clinician, the person with anaemia of CKD and their families and carers on whether or not to continue ESA therapy. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All people started on ESA therapy should be reviewed after an agreed interval in order to decide whether or not to continue using ESAs. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nutritional Supplements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Supplements of vitamin C, folic acid, or carnitine should not be prescribed as adjuvants specifically for the treatment of anaemia of CKD. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Androgens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD, androgens should not be used to treat the anaemia. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hyperparathyroidism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD, clinically relevant hyperparathyroidism should be treated to improve the management of the anaemia. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patient-Centred Care: ESAs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People offered ESA therapy and their general practitioners (GPs) should be given information about why ESA therapy is required, how it works, and what benefits and side effects may be experienced. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When managing the treatment of people with anaemia of CKD, there should be agreed protocols defining roles and responsibilities of healthcare professionals in primary and secondary care. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People receiving ESA therapy should be informed about the importance of concordance with therapy and the consequences of poor concordance. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When prescribing ESA therapy, healthcare professionals should take into account patient preferences about supervised- or self-administration, dose frequency, pain on injection, method of supplying ESA, and storage. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order for people to self-administer their ESA in a way that is clinically effective and safe, arrangements should be made to provide ready, reasonable and uninterrupted access to supplies. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patient Education Programmes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Culturally and age-appropriate patient education programmes should be offered to all people diagnosed with anaemia of CKD (and their families and carers). These should be repeated as requested, and according to the changing circumstances of the patient. They should include the following key areas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Practical information about how anaemia of CKD is managed &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Knowledge (for example, about symptoms, iron management, causes of anaemia, associated medications, and phases of treatment) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Professional support (for example, contact information, community services, continuity of care, monitoring, and feedback on progress of results) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Lifestyle (for example, diet, physical exercise, maintaining normality, and&amp;nbsp;meeting other patients) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adaptation to chronic disease (for example, previous information and expectations, and resolution of symptoms) &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Assessment and Optimisation of Erythropoiesis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits of Treatment with ESAs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment with ESAs should be offered to people with anaemia of CKD who are likely to benefit in terms of quality of life and physical function. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blood Transfusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD in whom kidney transplant is a treatment option, blood transfusions should be avoided where possible. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD, there may be situations where a transfusion is indicated clinically. In these cases, the relevant haematology guidelines should be followed. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; (See section 1.3.2.2 in the original guideline document for information on the haematology guideline.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparison of ESAs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The choice of ESA should be discussed with the person with anaemia of CKD when initiating treatment and at subsequent review, taking into consideration the patient's dialysis status, the route of administration and the local availability of ESAs. There is no evidence to distinguish between ESAs in terms of efficacy. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coordinating Care&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People with anaemia of CKD should have access to a designated contact person or persons who have principal responsibility for their anaemia management and who have skills in the following activities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Monitoring and managing a caseload of patients in line with locally agreed protocols &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Providing information, education and support to empower patients and their families and carers to participate in their care &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Coordinating an anaemia service for people with CKD, working between secondary and primary care and providing a single point of contact, to ensure patients receive a seamless service of the highest standard &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Prescribing medicines related to anaemia management and monitoring their effectiveness &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Providing ESAs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ESA therapy should be clinically effective, consistent and safe in people with anaemia of CKD. To achieve this, the prescriber and patient should agree a plan that is patient-centred and includes:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Continuity of drug supply &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Flexibility of where the drug is delivered and administered &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The lifestyle and preferences of the patient &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost of drug supply &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Desire for self-care where appropriate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Regular review of the plan in light of changing needs &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ESAs: Optimal Route of Administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The person with anaemia of CKD and the prescriber should agree (and revise as appropriate) the route of administration of ESAs, taking into account the following factors:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patient population (for example, haemodialysis patients) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Pain of injection &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Frequency of administration &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The lifestyle and preferences of the patient &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Efficacy (for example, subcutaneous versus intravenous administration, or long-acting versus short-acting preparations) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost of drug supply &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The prescriber should take into account that when using short-acting ESAs, subcutaneous injection allows the use of lower doses of drugs than intravenous administration. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ESAs: Dose and Frequency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When correcting anaemia of CKD, the dose and frequency of ESA should be:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Determined by the duration of action and route of administration of the ESA &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adjusted to keep the rate of Hb increase between 1 and 2 g/dl/month &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimal Hb Levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When determining individual aspirational Hb ranges for people with anaemia of CKD, take into account:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patient preferences &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Symptoms and comorbidities &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The required treatment &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The correction to normal levels of Hb with ESAs is not usually recommended in people with anaemia of CKD.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Typically maintain the aspirational Hb range between 10 and 12 g/dl for adults, young people and children aged 2 years and older, and between 9.5 and 11.5 g/dl for children younger than 2 years of age, reflecting the lower normal range in that age group. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To keep the Hb level within the aspirational range, do not wait until Hb levels are outside the aspirational range before adjusting treatment (for example, take action when Hb levels are within 0.5 g/dl of the range's limits). &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider accepting Hb levels below the agreed aspirational range if:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;High doses* of ESAs are required to achieve the aspirational range &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The aspirational range is not achieved despite escalating ESA doses &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*&amp;gt;175 IU/kg/week for haemodialysis population; &amp;gt;125 IU/kg/week for peritoneal dialysis population; &amp;gt;100 IU/kg/week for non-dialysis population (data provided by the National Renal Registry and Guideline Development Group expert opinion).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider accepting Hb levels above the agreed aspirational range when:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;These develop with iron therapy alone &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;These develop with low doses of ESAs &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;It is thought that the person might benefit (for example, if they have a physically demanding job) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The absolute risk of cerebrovascular disease is thought to be low &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Age alone should not be a determinant for treatment of anaemia of CKD. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjusting ESA Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Iron status should be optimised before or coincident with the initiation of ESA administration and during maintenance treatment with ESAs*. &lt;strong&gt;[2006, amended 2011]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Amended to clarify that iron status should be monitored during ESA maintenance treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Use of angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors or angiotensin type II receptor antagonists is not precluded, but if they are used, an increase in ESA therapy should be considered. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hb measurements should be taken into account when determining the dose and frequency of ESA administration.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The cause of an unexpected change in Hb level should be investigated (that is, intercurrent illness, bleeding) to enable intervention and iron status should be optimised*. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;ESA dose and/or frequency should be increased or decreased when Hb measurements fall outside action thresholds (usually below 10.5 g/dl or above 11.5 g/dl), or for example when the rate of change of Hb suggests an established trend (for example, greater than 1 g/dl/month). &lt;strong&gt;[2006, amended 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Amended to show iron status should be optimised following an unexpected change in Hb level.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treating Iron Deficiency: Correction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People with anaemia of CKD who are receiving ESAs should be given iron therapy to maintain:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Serum ferritin level greater than 200 micrograms/l &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Transferrin saturation greater than 20% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Percentage hypochromic red blood cells less than 6% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most patients will require 600&amp;ndash;1000 mg of iron for adults or equivalent doses for children, in a single or divided dose depending on the preparation. Patients with functional iron deficiency should be treated with intravenous iron. Peritoneal dialysis and non-dialysis patients who do not respond to oral iron will require intravenous iron. In appropriate circumstances, iron treatment can also be administered in the community. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In non-dialysis patients with anaemia of CKD in whom there is evidence of absolute or functional iron deficiency, this should be corrected before deciding whether ESA therapy is necessary. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treating Iron Deficiency: Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once ferritin levels are greater than 200 micrograms/l, and the percentage hypochromic red cells is less than 6% or transferrin saturation is greater than 20%, people with anaemia of CKD who are receiving ESAs should be given maintenance iron. The dosing regimen will depend on modality, for example haemodialysis patients will require the equivalent of 50&amp;ndash;60 mg intravenous iron per week (or an equivalent dose in children of 1 mg/kg/week). Peritoneal dialysis and non-dialysis patients who do not respond to oral iron will require intravenous iron. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ESAs: Monitoring Iron Status During Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People receiving ESA maintenance therapy should be given iron supplements to keep their:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Serum ferritin levels between 200 and 500 micrograms/l in both haemodialysis and non-haemodialysis patients, &lt;strong&gt;and either&lt;/strong&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Transferrin saturation level above 20% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Percentage hypochromic red cells (%HRC) less than 6% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In practice it is likely this will require intravenous iron. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Monitoring Treatment of Anaemia of CKD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Iron Status&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People with anaemia of CKD should not have iron levels checked earlier than 1 week after receiving intravenous iron. The length of time to monitoring of iron status is dependent on the product used and the amount of iron given. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Routine monitoring of iron stores should be at intervals of 4 weeks to 3 months. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Hb Levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD, Hb should be monitored:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Every 2&amp;ndash;4 weeks in the induction phase of ESA therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Every 1&amp;ndash;3 months in the maintenance phase of ESA therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;More actively after an ESA dose adjustment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;In a clinical setting chosen in discussion with the patient, taking into consideration their convenience and local healthcare systems &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detecting ESA Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After other causes of anaemia, such as intercurrent illness or chronic blood loss, have been excluded, people with anaemia of CKD should be considered resistant to ESAs when:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;An aspirational Hb range is not achieved despite treatment with 300 IU/kg/week or more of subcutaneous epoetin or&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;450 IU/kg/week or more of intravenous epoetin or&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;1.5 micrograms/kg/week of darbepoetin, &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;There is a continued need for the administration of high doses of ESAs to maintain the aspirational Hb range. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with CKD, pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) is indicated by a low reticulocyte count, together with anaemia and the presence of neutralising antibodies. The Guideline Development Group considered that PRCA should be confirmed by the presence of anti-erythropoietin antibodies together with a lack of pro-erythroid progenitor cells in the bone marrow. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In people with anaemia of CKD, aluminium toxicity should be considered as a potential cause of a reduced response to ESAs after other causes, such as intercurrent illness and chronic blood loss, have been excluded. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing ESA resistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In haemodialysis patients with anaemia of CKD in whom aluminium toxicity is suspected, a desferrioxamine test should be performed and the patient's management reviewed accordingly. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider specialist referral for ESA-induced PRCA. &lt;strong&gt;[2006, amended 2011]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A clinical algorithm is provided in the original guideline document for diagnosis, treatment, and maintenance of people with anemia with chronic kidney disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate management of anaemia in patients with chronic kidney disease, which may improve quality of life and prevent associated complications&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Higher doses of erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESAs) have been associated with adverse patient outcomes. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Common adverse effects from oral iron preparations include constipation, diarrhoea, nausea, vomiting, and dyspepsia. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Potential adverse effects of intravenous iron include nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, flushing, anaphylactoid reactions, dyspnoea, numbness, fever, urticaria, rash, arthralgia, myalgia, blurred vision, injection-site reactions including phlebitis, rarely diarrhoea, arrhythmias, hypotension, chest pain, seizures, tremor, dizziness, fatigue and sweating. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. However, the guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer, and informed by the summary of product characteristics of any drugs they are considering. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way that would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Healthcare providers need to use clinical judgement, knowledge and expertise when deciding whether it is appropriate to apply guidelines. The recommendations cited here are a guide and may not be appropriate for use in all situations. The decision to adopt any of the recommendations cited here must be made by the practitioner in light of individual patient circumstances, the wishes of the patient, clinical expertise and resources. The NCC-CC disclaims any responsibility for damages arising out of the use or non-use of these guidelines and the literature used in support of these guidelines. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has developed tools to help organisations implement this guidance. These are available on the NICE Web site (&lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114&lt;/a&gt;; see also the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Key Priorities for Implementation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following recommendations have been identified as priorities for implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When to Begin Treating the Anaemia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consider investigating and managing anaemia in people with chronic kidney disease (CKD) if:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Their haemoglobin (Hb) level falls to 11 g/dl or less (or 10.5 g/dl or less if younger than 2 years) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;They develop symptoms attributable to anaemia (such as tiredness, shortness of breath, lethargy, and palpitations) &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Should Receive Erythropoiesis-Stimulating Agents (ESAs)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treatment with ESAs should be offered to people with anaemia of CKD who are likely to benefit in terms of quality of life and physical function. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agreeing a Plan for ESA Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;ESA treatment should be clinically effective, consistent and safe in people with anaemia of CKD. To achieve this, the prescriber and patient should agree a plan that is patient-centred and includes:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Continuity of drug supply &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Flexibility of where the drug is delivered and administered &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;The lifestyle and preferences of the patient &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Cost of drug supply &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Desire for self-care where appropriate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Regular review of the plan in light of changing needs. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aspirational Range and Action Thresholds for Hb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;When determining individual aspirational Hb ranges for people with anaemia of CKD, take into account:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Patient preferences &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Symptoms and comorbidities &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;The required treatment &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The correction to normal levels of Hb with ESAs is not usually recommended in people with anaemia of CKD.&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Typically maintain the aspirational Hb range between 10 and 12 g/dl for adults, young people and children aged 2 years and older, and between 9.5 and 11.5 g/dl for children younger than 2 years of age, reflecting the lower normal range in that age group. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;To keep the Hb level within the aspirational range, do not wait until Hb levels are outside the aspirational range before adjusting treatment (for example, take action when Hb levels are within 0.5 g/dl of the range's limits). &lt;strong&gt;[new 2011]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Age&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Age alone should not be a determinant for treatment of anaemia of CKD. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iron Supplementation: Aspirational Ranges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;People receiving ESA maintenance therapy should be given iron supplements to keep their:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Serum ferritin levels between 200 and 500 micrograms/l in both haemodialysis and non-haemodialysis patients, &lt;strong&gt;and either&lt;/strong&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Transferrin saturation level above 20% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;li&gt;Percentage hypochromic red cells (%HRC) less than 6% (unless ferritin is greater than 800 micrograms/l) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;p&gt;In practice it is likely this will require intravenous iron. &lt;strong&gt;[2006]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Clinical Algorithm" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Slide Presentation" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Clinical Guideline Centre. Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Feb. 38 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical guideline; no. 114).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2006 (revised 2011 Feb)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Clinical Guideline Centre for Acute and Chronic Conditions - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guideline Development Group&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guideline Development Group (GDG) Members&lt;/em&gt;: Dr Penny Ackland, General Practitioner, London; Dr Samir Agrawal, Senior Lecturer, Queen Mary, University of London; Honorary Consultant in Haematology, Barts and The London NHS Trust; Ms Carol Anderson, Anaemia Nurse Specialist, East Kent Hospitals University NHS Foundation Trust; Dr Miranda Dodwell, Patient and Carer Member, London; Mr Robert Dunn, Patient and Carer Member, Devon; Dr Jonathan Evans, Consultant Paediatrician, Nottingham City Hospital NHS Trust; Dr David Halpin (&lt;em&gt;GDG Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Ms Karen Jenkins, Anaemia Nurse Specialist, East Kent Hospitals University NHS Foundation Trust; Dr Mick Kumwenda, Consultant Renal Physician, Conwy and Denbighshire NHS Trust; Professor Alison MacLeod, Consultant Nephrologist, Aberdeen Royal Infirmary; Professor of Medicine, University of Aberdeen; Dr Shelagh O'Riordan, Consultant Physician in Healthcare of Older People, East Kent Hospitals University NHS Foundation Trust; Dr Paul Roderick, Professor of Public Health, University of Southampton and Southampton University Hospitals NHS Trust; Dr Paul Stevens, GDG Clinical Advisor, Consultant Renal Physician, East Kent Hospitals University NHS Foundation Trust; Dr Stephen Thomas, Consultant in Diabetes Medicine, Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust; Dr Eric Will, Consultant Renal Physician, Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All members of the guideline development group and all members of the National Clinical Guideline Centre staff were required to make formal declarations of interest at the outset, and these were updated at every subsequent meeting throughout the development process. No interests were declared that required actions. See Appendix F of the full version of the guideline document for interests declared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline has been updated. The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) is working to update this summary. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies of the updated guideline: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng8&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Full guideline. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. 544 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/Guidance/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Quick reference guide. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. 12 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/QuickRefGuide/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Costing report. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. 33 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/CostingReport/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Costing template. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/CostingTemplate/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Implementation advice. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Sep. 23 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/ImplementationAdvice/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Slide set. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011. 23 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/SlideSet/ppt/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in people with chronic kidney disease. Baseline assessment tool. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/BaselineAssessment/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Anaemia management in CKD (update). Podcast. Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/newsroom/podcasts/index.jsp?pid=13&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guidelines manual 2009. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2009 Jan. Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/aboutnice/howwework/developingniceclinicalguidelines/clinicalguidelinedevelopmentmethods/GuidelinesManual2009.jsp&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, audit criteria can be found in section 3.4 of the full version of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/Guidance/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;original guideline document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treating anaemia in people with chronic kidney disease. Understanding NICE guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Feb. 12 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 114). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/PublicInfo/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in Welsh from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG114/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summary was completed by ECRI on February 15, 2007. The information was verified by the guideline developer on March 9, 2007. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on March 21, 2008 following the FDA advisory on Erythropoiesis Stimulating Agents. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on August 15, 2008 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Erythropoiesis Stimulating Agents (ESAs). This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on April 1, 2010 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Erythropoiesis-Stimulating Agents (ESAs). This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on July 15, 2011 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESAs) in chronic kidney disease. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 22, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their clinical guidelines with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not yet verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects that original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE clinical guidelines are prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
