<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 31 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 186).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Rheumatoid arthritis  (714.0)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Arthritis, Rheumatoid ; Immunoglobulin Fab Fragments ; Polyethylene Glycols "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: certolizumab pegol ; Fab Immunoglobulins ; Polyethylene Glycols ; Rheumatoid Arthritis "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: polyethylene glycol "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Certolizumab pegol  (430306004); Certolizumab pegol  (430307008); Immunoglobulin, F(ab) fragment  (112136000); Polyethylene glycol  (356076006); Polyethylene glycol  (8030004); Rheumatoid arthritis  (69896004)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Rheumatology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Certolizumab pegol&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical effectiveness&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Disease activity &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Physical function &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Joint damage &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Pain &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Fatigue &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Radiological progression &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Adverse effects of treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Health related quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;American College of Rheumatology criteria 20 (ACR20), ACR50, and ACR70 &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;The Health Assessment Questionnaire Disability Index (HAQ-DI) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;The Disease Activity Score (DAS28) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Modified Total Sharp Score (mTSS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Safety and tolerability &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness expressed in terms of incremental cost per quality-adjusted life year &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Patient Registry Data" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Unpublished Data" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by the West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description and Critique of Clinical Effectiveness Search Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer conducted an initial search to July 2007; this was subsequently broadened and updated to April 2009 (see Appendix 2 of the ERG report).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The stated aim of the search was to identify studies allowing systematic review of the efficacy of biological disease modifying antirheumatic drug (bDMARD) treatments for rheumatoid arthritis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The identification of relevant studies was performed in a two-step process. An initial systematic review of the efficacy of biological DMARD treatments for rheumatoid arthritis was conducted with databases searched up to July 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Comment:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above is a broader aim than implied in manufacturer's definition of the decision problem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In effect the manufacturer's search strategy and selection of studies served three distinct purposes:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The identification of appropriate studies to allow assessment of the clinical effectiveness of certolizumab pegol (CZP) + methotrexate (MTX) versus MTX + placebo and of CZP versus placebo in patients intolerant of MTX or for who MTX was contraindicated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The identification of appropriate studies to allow assessment of the effectiveness of CZP combination therapy (CZP + MTX), and of CZP mono- therapy relative to combination therapy and mono-therapy with other bDMARDs using indirect comparison methodology &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The identification of appropriate studies to inform the decision problem addressed in the economic analysis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The search strategy specifically named the bDMARDs that the manufacturer identified as comparators for the decision problem (i.e., etanercept, adalimumab, infliximab, rituximab and tocilizumab); it also included terms for anti-tumor necrosis factor (anti-TNF) agents and for monoclonal antibodies. Studies of some bDMARDs such as fusion protein anti-cytokine agents (e.g., abatacept and anakinra) may not be efficiently retrieved with this search strategy and therefore this search may not fulfil the broad aim stated in the manufacturer's submission (MS).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to determine if the studies were retrieved because the literature search tree presented in the submission is confusing and an appropriate list of excluded studies was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In summary the database strategies appear comprehensive and it is unlikely that studies of CZP and the specified comparators will have been missed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Omission of Foreign Language Papers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although it was stated that searches were limited to articles published in English this does not appear to have been implemented in the search strategies. However the submission does state that non-English language papers were excluded. This procedure may exclude relevant studies. The ERG re-ran the MEDLINE and EMBASE strategies to test how many papers in the time period 2007-2009 would have been disregarded as a result of this exclusion criterion (see Appendix 3 of the ERG report). The manufacturer's response to ERG's request for clarification on this issue is shown in Appendix 4 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;144 foreign language papers (45 MEDLINE, 108 EMBASE, 9 duplicates) were identified. The ERG did not assess whether any of these would have met all of the manufacturer's other inclusion criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer's strategy did not include any details of any searches for ongoing trials; thus, there is a possibility that studies which are ongoing or which are completed but not yet published may have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ERG conducted searches of the following publicly available trials registers: ClinicalTrials.gov, Current Controlled Trials meta Register and the United Kingdom Clinical Research Network (UKCRN) Portfolio database, using terms cimzia or certolizumab combined with rheumatoid. Table 1 of the ERG report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field) lists the ongoing studies of CZP identified. Of the ongoing studies, only one trial (C87051) was mentioned in MS ongoing studies section.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unpublished Completed Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Searches for CZP trials using ClinicalTrials.gov resulted in identification of a completed study (C87014) comparing CZP+MTX with Placebo+MTX. No published report appears to exist for this study and as a consequence it was not included in the manufacturer's effectiveness review as this only included published studies. The ERG conducted further searches for details of this trial (see Appendix 8 of the ERG report). A summary of information on study C87014 obtained from these searches is presented in Table 2 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Study C87014 is mentioned in the submission, where it is stated to be a previous study upon which the power calculation for RAPID1 and RAPID2 trials was based.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the CZP USA Prescribing Information this trial is listed as one of the four CZP RCTs conducted in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) patients. As such it was presumably submitted to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) during the USA marketing approval process (see Table 3 of the ERG report). As the European Medicines Agency (EMEA) scientific discussion on CZP for RA is not yet public it is unclear if the trial informed these discussions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This study was also mentioned in the adverse events section of the submission.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, with 247 randomised patients, C87014 is equivalent to about 15% of patients in RAPID 1 &amp;amp; 2 (also on CZP+MTX vs MTX+placebo).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statement of the Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria Used in the Study Selection and Comment on Whether They Were Appropriate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The inclusion and exclusion criteria specified in the submission are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inclusion criteria were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Studies must be published randomised controlled trials. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Studies must be conducted in human adult patients (&amp;ge;18 years) with active RA who have had an inadequate response to prior DMARD therapy, including MTX. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Studies must contain one of the following interventions administered with or without MTX: adalimumab, CZP, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, tocilizumab. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The treatment comparison must be to another biological DMARD, a conventional DMARD or placebo. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The study must report results for an outcome of interest, namely: patient's global assessment of disease activity; Disease Activity Score (DAS)28 scores; American College of Rheumatology (ACR) responses; European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) responses; Health Assessment Questionnaire Disability Index (HAQ-DI); swollen joint count; tender joint count; patient's global assessment of pain; patient's assessment of fatigue; Modified Total Sharp Score (mTSS) (van der Heijde); EQ-5D scores; mortality; hospitalisation; joint replacement surgery; rheumatoid nodules; vasculitis; neuropathy; any adverse event; any serious adverse event; infusion reactions/acute hypersensitivity reactions; injection site reactions; tuberculosis; serious infections; malignancies/lymphoma; withdrawals due to adverse events. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The interventions of interest must be studied at a licensed dose (EMEA or FDA). If a study included more than one treatment arm of the intervention of interest, one of them must be a licensed dose. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following studies were excluded:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Observational studies, reviews and open label extensions of RCTs &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Non-English language papers &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dose ranging studies and studies where the comparator was an untreated control group &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description of Manufacturer's Search Strategy and Comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Databases searched were:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MEDLINE (Ovid) and MEDLINE In Process (Ovid) 1950 to date &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;EMBASE (Ovid) 1980 to date &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cochrane Library (Wiley) (National Health Service Economic Evaluation Database [NHS EED]) 1982 to date &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Office of Health Economics (OHE) Health Economic Evaluation Database to date &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches were conducted on 18 May 2009.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches were limited to English language papers only.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches were based on those in an NHS Research and Development (R&amp;amp;D) Health Technology Assessment (HTA) study by Chen et al which included a systematic review of economic evaluations of anti-tumour necrosis factors (TNFs) (adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab) in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis in adults. The Chen review was updated from 2005 onwards, the newer biological DMARDs/TNF inhibitors not covered in the original review were searched for without date limit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Comments&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A combination of index terms and textwords are used to create a comprehensive strategy which is unlikely to have missed many relevant references. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;No searches relating to quality of life appear to have been conducted. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The strategy has been translated successfully between the databases; however, the results of the Cochrane Library search across NHS EED will have been restricted unnecessarily by the incorrect use of the Boolean &quot;AND&quot; operator where &quot;OR&quot; has been used in the MEDLINE and EMBASE searches. Therefore, the ERG re-ran the search using both the &quot;AND&quot; and &quot;OR&quot; operators in the final line &amp;ndash; the &quot;AND&quot; retrieved 3 economic evaluations but the broader search using&amp;nbsp;the &quot;OR&quot; operator and which correctly replicated the strategy which the manufacturer ran on MEDLINE and EMBASE retrieved 50 studies. The ERG specifically examined five of these studies which were deemed to be relevant because they involved the comparators (adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, or abatacept). One study did consider both the quality of life and economic impact of infliximab by comparison to adalimumab and could have been quoted. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Three randomised controlled trials (RCTs) met the criteria for inclusion. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A total of 18 RCTs contributed data for the indirect comparisons (13 for combination therapy and 5 for mono-therapy). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer submitted two economic models (original and revised).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by the West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description and Critique of Manufacturer's Approach to Validity Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Only randomised controlled trials (RCTs) were included in the manufacturer's review. The manufacturer applied clear and appropriate criteria to assess the validity of the three included studies on certolizumab pegol (CZP). These criteria were:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Method of concealing treatment allocation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Randomisation technique &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Sample size justified? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Observers blinded? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study design &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Location &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Comparability of patients with UK rheumatoid arthritis (RA) population &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;CZP dosage regimen &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dosage regimen within summary of product characteristics (SPC) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study groups comparable? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Statistical analyses appropriate? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intention to treat (ITT) analyses performed? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Confounding factors affecting interpretation present? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The results of the quality assessment were tabulated and not used in any analyses. The ERG considers the quality assessment to be fair and reasonable. However, the ERG does have some concern about a feature of the study design rules for early withdrawal of patients.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quality assessment was not undertaken for trials on comparator drugs included in the indirect comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Describe and Critique the Statistical Approach Used&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the direct and indirect comparisons (ICs) the approach appears appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However the approach for obtaining effectiveness inputs for the economic modelling for CZP compared to other biological disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (bDMARDs) had some shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Indirect Comparison Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A total of 18 RCTs contributed data for the ICs (13 for combination therapy and 5 for mono-therapy). Three outcomes were analysed (American College of Rheumatology criteria 20 [ACR20], ACR50 and ACR70) at each of 3 months and 6 months. A random effects meta-analysis was used that generated odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals for pair-wise comparisons between bDMARDs (between CZP, adalimumab, infliximab, etanercept, rituximab and tocilizumab for combination therapy and between CZP, adalimumab and etanercept for monotherapy).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The results are presented in Appendix 7 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critique of Submitted Evidence Syntheses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indirect Comparisons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The submission used the indirect comparison method of Bucher et al. rather than a mixed treatment comparison (MTC) to compare efficacy of CZP versus other bDMARDs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Comment&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A potential disadvantage of this approach is that only multiple two way comparisons between bDMARDs are possible. The alternative MTC approach has the potential advantage of allowing direct probability statements about which treatment is the most effective, even when standard methods might determine no significant difference between treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 4 of the ERG report for more information on methods used to analyze the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The submitted economic evaluation is a cost-utility analysis using a lifetime Markov model built in Microsoft Excel&amp;reg; and comparing the cost-effectiveness of CZP to the other bDMARDs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The model schema from the submission is shown in the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer submitted two different economic models during the appraisal process. The first model (&quot;original&quot; model) was included as part of the initial submission. The second model (&quot;revised&quot; model) was received during the clarification stage of the appraisal process. The manufacturer made changes to the model during this time that went beyond those prompted by requests for clarification by the ERG. As such, the ERG considers these as two separate models. The original model included:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Costs of drugs and monitoring medications and routine follow-up and assumed that there is no wastage of drugs &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Differential adverse event effects on quality-adjusted life year (QALY) between treatment comparators, but no associated costs of adverse event. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A Patient Access Scheme (PAS) that gives away the initial 10 syringes free of charge to all new patients treated with CZP. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Two model scenarios: scenario A with the PAS, and scenario B without PAS. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health outcomes (quality-adjusted life-years) and incremental cost-effectiveness. Utilities for patients are based on ACR response and other factors and are quantified via regression analysis on EQ-5D values or Health Assessment Questionnaire Disability Index (HAQ-DI) linked to utility weights via a simple linear relation. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A probabilistic sensitivity analysis (PSA) to assess the overall effect of the uncertainty in the model. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This revised model incorporates three key changes to the original model.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utility assumptions&lt;/strong&gt;. The utility assumptions have been revised. The originally submitted model assumed that utility as measured by EQ-5D decreased by 0.037 per year if response had been assessed at 6 months (or 0.014 per year at 3 months). The new model adopts an assumption of a utility decrease of 0.0025 per year if response had been assessed at both 6 months and 3 months. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adverse events&lt;/strong&gt;. The assumption of differential adverse event effects between comparator therapies is considered inappropriate and inconsistent with the accounting of costs, and the revised model does not directly include any adverse events. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discontinuation probabilities&lt;/strong&gt;. Treatment discontinuation probabilities are revised with exact values rather than approximate values using an exponential survival distribution. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The differences between the models are summarised by the ERG in Table 4 of the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 5 of the ERG report for additional information on economic evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technology appraisal recommendations are based on a review of clinical and economic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology Appraisal Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) invites 'consultee' and 'commentator' organisations to take part in the appraisal process. Consultee organisations include national groups representing patients and carers, the bodies representing health professionals, and the manufacturers of the technology under review. Consultees are invited to submit evidence during the appraisal and to comment on the appraisal documents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Commentator organisations include manufacturers of the products with which the technology is being compared, the National Health Service (NHS) Quality Improvement Scotland and research groups working in the area. They can comment on the evidence and other documents but are not asked to submit evidence themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE then commissions an independent academic centre to review published evidence on the technology and prepare an 'assessment report.' Consultees and commentators are invited to comment on the report. The assessment report and the comments on it are then drawn together in a document called the evaluation report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An independent Appraisal Committee then considers the evaluation report. It holds a meeting where it hears direct, spoken evidence from nominated clinical experts, patients and carers. The Committee uses all the evidence to make its first recommendations, in a document called the 'appraisal consultation document' (ACD). NICE sends all the consultees and commentators a copy of this document and posts it on the NICE website. Further comments are invited from everyone taking part.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the Committee meets again it considers any comments submitted on the ACD; then it prepares its final recommendations in a document called the 'final appraisal determination' (FAD). This is submitted to NICE for approval.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consultees have a chance to appeal against the final recommendations in the FAD. If there are no appeals, the final recommendations become the basis of the guidance that NICE issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Is on the Appraisal Committee?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE technology appraisal recommendations are prepared by an independent committee. This includes health professionals working in the NHS and people who are familiar with the issues affecting patients and carers. Although the Appraisal Committee seeks the views of organisations representing health professionals, patients, carers, manufacturers and government, its advice is independent of any vested interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer submitted two versions of its economic model (the original model and a revised model that was produced in response to requests for clarification from National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence [NICE]). The revised model differed from the original model in three key ways: assumptions used for utilities, adverse events, and discontinuation probabilities. Both models included scenarios with and without the patient access scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The models were Markov-based models that used a hypothetical cohort of people with moderate to severe active rheumatoid arthritis, whose disease had responded inadequately to conventional disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs), including methotrexate. The models were designed to compare certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate with etanercept plus methotrexate, adalimumab plus methotrexate, rituximab plus methotrexate, and infliximab plus methotrexate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The original model base case (not including the patient access scheme) reported that when etanercept plus methotrexate was compared with certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate, the quality-adjusted life year (QALY) gain was -0.005 and incremental costs were &amp;pound;2675. This meant that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was less effective and more costly than etanercept plus methotrexate. When certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was compared with adalimumab plus methotrexate, the QALY gain was 0.102 and incremental costs were &amp;pound;3563, giving an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;34,930 per QALY gained. Certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate compared with infliximab plus methotrexate showed a QALY gain of 0.211 and incremental costs of -&amp;pound;4468, meaning that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate dominated infliximab plus methotrexate (that is, certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was more effective and less costly than infliximab plus methotrexate). Certolizumab pegol monotherapy compared with adalimumab monotherapy resulted in a QALY gain of 0.127 and incremental costs of &amp;pound;5347. This gave an ICER for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;42,197 per QALY gained. When etanercept monotherapy was compared with certolizumab pegol monotherapy, the QALY gain was -0.047 and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;297, resulting in an ICER of &amp;pound;6341 per QALY gained for etanercept compared with certolizumab pegol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The original model base case (including the patient access scheme) reported that when etanercept plus methotrexate was compared with certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate, the QALY gain was -0.005 and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;900. This meant that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was less effective and less costly than etanercept plus methotrexate. The model showed that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate dominated adalimumab plus methotrexate and infliximab plus methotrexate. The incremental QALY gains were 0.102 and 0.211, and the incremental costs were -&amp;pound;12 and -&amp;pound;8043 respectively. Certolizumab pegol monotherapy compared with adalimumab monotherapy showed a QALY gain of 0.127 and incremental costs of &amp;pound;1772, resulting in an ICER for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;13,982 per QALY gained. When etanercept monotherapy was compared with certolizumab pegol monotherapy, the QALY gain was -0.047 and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;3872, resulting in an ICER of &amp;pound;82,695 per QALY gained for etanercept compared with certolizumab pegol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The revised model base case (not including the patient access scheme) reported that when etanercept plus methotrexate was compared with certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate, the QALY gain was 0.065 and incremental costs were &amp;pound;2993, resulting in an ICER for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;46,192 per QALY gained. When certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was compared with adalimumab plus methotrexate, the QALY gain was 0.242 and incremental costs were &amp;pound;3124, resulting in an ICER for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;12,937 per QALY gained. Certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate compared with infliximab plus methotrexate showed a QALY gain of 0.458 and incremental costs of -&amp;pound;6441, meaning that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate dominated infliximab plus methotrexate. Certolizumab pegol monotherapy compared with adalimumab monotherapy gave a QALY gain of 0.215 and incremental costs of &amp;pound;1223, resulting in an ICER for certolizumab pegol of &amp;pound;5687 per QALY gained. When etanercept monotherapy was compared with certolizumab pegol monotherapy, the QALY gain was -0.130 and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;517, meaning that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate was less effective and less costly than etanercept plus methotrexate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The revised economic model (including the patient access scheme) reported that certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate dominated etanercept plus methotrexate, adalimumab plus methotrexate and infliximab plus methotrexate. The incremental QALY gains were 0.065, 0.242 and 0.458 respectively and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;582, -&amp;pound;451 and -&amp;pound;10,016 respectively. Certolizumab pegol monotherapy also dominated adalimumab monotherapy with a QALY gain of 0.215 and incremental costs of -&amp;pound;2352. When etanercept monotherapy was compared with certolizumab pegol monotherapy, the QALY gain was -0.130 and incremental costs were -&amp;pound;4092, resulting in an ICER of &amp;pound;31,582 per QALY gained for etanercept compared with certolizumab pegol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer submitted probabilistic and incremental cost-effectiveness estimates at the request of the Committee based on the revised model but including the effectiveness estimates resulting from the mixed-treatment comparison analysis. This analysis also included the patient access scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the incremental analysis including C87014 and two direct comparisons, as well as the patient access scheme, certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate dominated all comparator tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitors, except etanercept plus methotrexate. For the latter the incremental QALY gain was 0.101 and incremental costs were &amp;pound;1481, resulting in an ICER of &amp;pound;14,722 per QALY gained for etanercept (that is, certolizumab pegol was less costly and less effective than etanercept). In the probabilistic sensitivity analysis, the probability of certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate being cost effective at a willingness-to-pay threshold of &amp;pound;20,000 per QALY gained was 48.7%. Certolizumab pegol monotherapy was less costly and less effective than etanercept monotherapy, and dominated adalimumab monotherapy. The probability of certolizumab monotherapy being cost effective at &amp;pound;20,000 per QALY gained was 46.2%.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Appraisal Committee was unable to make recommendations about the use of certolizumab pegol following failure of other TNF inhibitors. However, it considered that the recommendation for sequential TNF inhibitor use in the event of stopping treatment because of an adverse event in the first 6 months (as in NICE technology appraisal guidance 130) should also apply to certolizumab pegol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Sections 3 and 4 of the original guideline document for details of the economic analyses provided by the manufacturer, the Evidence Review Group (ERG) comments, and the Appraisal Committee considerations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultee organisations from the following groups were invited to comment on the draft scope, Assessment Report and the Appraisal Consultation Document (ACD) and were provided with the opportunity to appeal against the Final Appraisal Determination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manufacturer/sponsors &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Professional/specialist and patient/carer groups &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Commentator organisations (without the right of appeal) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, individuals selected from clinical expert and patient advocate nominations from the professional/specialist and patient/carer groups were also invited to comment on the ACD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Certolizumab pegol is recommended as an option for the treatment of people with rheumatoid arthritis only if:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol is used as described for other tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor treatments in the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) guidance, &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA130&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept and infliximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/a&gt; (NICE technology appraisal 130) &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The manufacturer provides the first 12 weeks of certolizumab pegol (10 pre-loaded 200-mg syringes) free of charge to all patients starting treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When using the Disease Activity Score (DAS)28 (as set out in NICE technology appraisal guidance 130), healthcare professionals should take into account any physical, sensory or learning disabilities, or communication difficulties that could affect a person's responses to the DAS28 and make any adjustments they consider appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Appraisal Committee considered clinical and cost-effectiveness evidence submitted by the manufacturer of certolizumab pegol (CZP) and a review of this submission by the Evidence Review Group.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer's submitted clinical evidence consisted of:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A meta-analysis of outcomes from two triple-arm randomised controlled trials (RCTs) comparing CZP plus methotrexate (MTX) at two different CZP dose regimens versus MTX + placebo &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Results from a 24-week RCT comparing a single dose regimen of CZP versus placebo &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;An indirect comparison meta-analysis (ICM) that included thirteen studies of combined therapy of a biological disease-modifying anti-rheumatic agent (DMARD) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;An ICM that included five studies of three biological DMARDs (adalimumab, etanercept and CZP) in monotherapy versus placebo &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;An analysis of the safety of CZP using data from various RCTs and their extension studies &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cost-effectiveness was based on economic models submitted by the manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects and contraindications, see the summary of product characteristics (SPC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the summary of product characteristics (SPC), contraindications for the use of certolizumab pegol are: hypersensitivity to the active substance; active, severe infections (including tuberculosis, sepsis and opportunistic infections); and severe heart failure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects and contraindications, see the SPC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. However, the guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way which would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The Secretary of State and the Welsh Assembly Minister for Health and Social Services have issued directions to the National Health Service (NHS) on implementing National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) technology appraisal guidance. When a NICE technology appraisal recommends use of a drug or treatment, or other technology, the NHS must provide funding and resources for it within 3 months of the guidance being published. If the Department of Health issues a variation to the 3-month funding direction, details will be available on the NICE website. The NHS is not required to fund treatments that are not recommended by NICE. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;NICE has developed tools to help organisations put this guidance into practice (listed below). These are available on the NICE website (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/TA186&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk/TA186&lt;/a&gt;).&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;A costing statement explaining the resource impact of this guidance. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Audit support for monitoring local practice. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 31 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 186).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2010 Feb" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appraisal Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Dr Jane Adam (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Department of Diagnostic Radiology, St George's Hospital; Professor Philip Home (&lt;em&gt;Vice Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Professor of Diabetes Medicine, Newcastle University; Professor A E Ades, MRC Senior Scientist, MRC Health Services Research Collaboration, Department of Social Medicine, University of Bristol; Mrs Elizabeth Brain, Lay Member; Professor Karl Claxton, Professor of Health Economics, University of York; Dr Fiona Duncan, Clinical Nurse Specialist, Anaesthetic Department, Blackpool Victoria Hospital, Blackpool; Mr Christopher Earl, Surgical Care Practitioner, Renal Transplant Unit, Manchester Royal Infirmary; Dr Paul Ewings, Statistician, Taunton &amp;amp; Somerset NHS Trust, Taunton; Professor John Geddes, Professor of Epidemiological Psychiatry, University of Oxford; Mr John Goulston, Chief Executive, Barking, Havering and Redbridge Hospitals NHS Trust; Mr Adrian Griffin, VP Strategic Affairs, LifeScan, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson; Professor Jonathan Grigg, Professor of Paediatric Respiratory and Environmental Medicine, Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University London; Dr Vincent Kirkbride, Consultant Neonatologist, Regional Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Sheffield; Dr Ian Lewin, Consultant Endocrinologist, North Devon District Hospital; Dr Alec Miners, Lecturer in Health Economics, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine; Dr James Moon, Consultant Cardiologist and Senior Lecturer, University College London Hospital (UCLH) and UCL; Dr Nick Murray, Senior Lecturer and Consultant in Medical Oncology, University of Southampton; Dr Ann Richardson, Lay Member; Mrs Angela Schofield, Chairman, Bournemouth and Poole Teaching PCT; Mr Mike Spencer, General Manager, Cardiff and Vale NHS Trust &amp;ndash; Facilities and Clinical Support Services; Professor Iain Squire, Consultant Physician, University Hospitals of Leicester; Professor Andrew Stevens, Professor of Public Health, Department of Public Health and Epidemiology, University of Birmingham; Mr David Thomson, Lay Member; Mr William Turner, Consultant Urologist, Addenbrooke's Hospital; Dr Luke Twelves, General Practitioner, Ramsey Health Centre, Cambridgeshire; Dr John Watkins, Clinical Senior Lecturer/Consultant in Public Health Medicine, Cardiff University and National Public Health Service Wales; Dr Anthony S Wierzbicki, Consultant in Metabolic Medicine/Chemical Pathology, Guy's and St Thomas' Hospitals NHS Trust; Dr Olivia Wu, Reader in Health Economics, University of Glasgow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Committee members are asked to declare any interests in the technology to be appraised. If it is considered there is a conflict of interest, the member is excluded from participating further in that appraisal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Quick reference guide. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 2 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186/QuickRefGuide/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol, adalimumab, etanercept and infliximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Audit support. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 9 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186/AuditSupport/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Costing statement. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 3 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186/CostingStatement/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Evidence review group report. West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration; 2009 Oct. 112 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=45795&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Evidence review group report - errors. West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration; 2009 Oct. 3 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=45796&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Certolizumab pegol for rheumatoid arthritis. Understanding NICE Guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Feb. 4 p. (Technology appraisal 186). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186/PublicInfo/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in Welsh from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA186/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on February 21, 2011. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on October 12, 2011 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory on Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF&amp;alpha;) Blockers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their Technology Appraisal guidance with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects the original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE technology appraisal guidance is prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
