<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure: HFSA 2010 comprehensive heart failure practice guideline.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Heart Failure Society of America, Lindenfeld J, Albert NM, Boehmer JP, Collins SP, Ezekowitz JA, Givertz MM, Katz SD, Klapholz M, Moser DK, Rogers JG, Starling RC, Stevenson WG, Tang WH, Teerlink JR, Walsh MN. Surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure: HFSA 2010 comprehensive heart failure practice guideline. J Card Fail. 2010 Jun;16(6):e122-5. [41 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Heart Failure Society of America. Surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure. J Card Fai 2006 Feb;12(1):e76-9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Congestive heart failure, unspecified  (428.0); Heart failure, unspecified  (428.9); Heart transplantation  (37.51); Organ or tissue replaced by other means, heart assist device  (V43.21)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Cardiac Surgical Procedures ; Heart Failure ; Heart Transplantation ; Heart Valve Prosthesis ; Heart Valve Prosthesis Implantation ; Heart-Assist Devices "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Cardiac Surgery procedures ; Congestive heart failure ; Heart failure ; Heart Transplantation ; Heart Valve Prosthesis ; Mitral valvuloplasty ; Replacement of mitral valve (procedure) "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Cardiac valve prosthesis  (25510005); Congestive heart failure  (42343007); Heart failure  (84114007); Mitral valve prosthesis  (17107009); Mitral valvuloplasty  (265472007); Mitral valvuloplasty  (384641003); Mitral valvuloplasty  (384642005); Operation on heart  (64915003); Repair of mitral valve with prosthesis  (26977004); Repair of mitral valve without replacement  (387642000); Replacement of mitral valve  (53059001); Resection of left ventricle of heart  (31484008); Transplantation of heart  (32413006)"/><FieldValue Value="SPN: VALVE, PROSTHESIS "/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Prostheses, Cardiac Valve  (13-138); Ventricular Restraint Implants  (23-995)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heart failure&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Heart failure is a syndrome caused by cardiac dysfunction, generally resulting from myocardial muscle dysfunction or loss and characterized by either left ventricular (LV) dilation or hypertrophy or both.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Cardiology" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Thoracic Surgery" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To provide recommendations for surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To update and expand the previous 2006 clinical practice guidelines &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with heart failure who are candidates for surgical treatment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Heart transplantation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Mitral valve repair or replacement (not generally recommended) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Partial left ventricular (LV) resection (not recommended in nonischemic cardiomyopathy) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Mechanical support devices &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The following emerging techniques were also discussed, but not recommended: infarct exclusion surgery, passive restraint.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Survival &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse events of therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A literature search with relevant key words and phrases for each guideline section were provided to members of the subcommittees and the full Guideline Committee. Members of each subcommittee were asked to review the search and identify any additional relevant medical evidence for each assigned section.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following databases were searched:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Ovid Medline (1950 to the updated date when the search was conducted) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Ovid Medline In-Process and other Non-Indexed Citations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;PubMed &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches focused primarily on the period between the last guideline publication and current, although the authors went back to 2005 to account for publication lag between the completion of the guideline and its publication in 2006 (i.e., 2005&amp;ndash;2010) in the event there was some information that should/could be added to the 2010 updated document. Generally only non-human studies and publications that were non-English were excluded.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following search terms were used: Heart failure; mitral valve; thoracic surgery; cardiac surgical procedures; heart transplantation; heart-assist devices; assisted circulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Hierarchy of Types of Evidence&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Hierarchy of Types of Evidence&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level A&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Randomized, Controlled, Clinical Trials&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            May be assigned based on results of a single methodologically rigorous trial&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level B&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Cohort and Case-Control Studies&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Post hoc, subgroup analysis, and meta-analysis&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Prospective observational studies or registries&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level C&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Expert Opinion&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Observational studies &amp;ndash; epidemiologic findings&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Safety reporting from large-scale use in practice&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heart Failure Society of America (HFSA) Guideline Approach to Medical Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Two considerations are critical in the development of practice guidelines: assessing strength of evidence and determining strength of recommendation. Strength of evidence is determined both by the type of evidence available and the assessment of validity, applicability, and certainty of a specific type of evidence. Following the lead of previous guidelines, strength of evidence in this guideline is heavily dependent on the source or type of evidence used. The HFSA guideline process has used three grades (A, B, or C) to characterize the type of evidence available to support specific recommendations (see Table 1.2 in the original guideline document).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HFSA Guideline Approach to Strength of Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Determining Strength. Although level of evidence is important, the strength given to specific recommendations is critical. The process used to determine the strength of individual recommendations is complex. The goal of guideline development is to achieve the best recommendations for evaluation and management, considering not only efficacy, but the cost, convenience, side effect profile, and safety of various therapeutic approaches. The HFSA guideline committee often determined the strength of a recommendation by the &quot;totality of evidence,&quot; which is a synthesis of all types of available data, pro and con, about a particular therapeutic option. The HFSA guideline employs the categorization for strength of recommendation outlined in Table 1.3 in the original guideline document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process of Guideline Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Key steps in the development of this guideline are listed in Table 1.4 in the original guideline document. Having determined the broad scope of the current guideline, subcommittees of the guideline committee were formed for each section of the guideline. A literature search with relevant key words and phrases for each guideline section were provided to members of the subcommittees and the full Guideline Committee. Members of each subcommittee were asked to review the search and identify any additional relevant medical evidence for each assigned section. Changes in recommendation and background were carried out by each subcommittee with conference calls directed by the Guideline Committee chair. Each section was presented for comments and consensus approval to the Guideline Committee. Once subsections were complete, the Executive Council reviewed and commented on each section and these comments were returned to the Guideline Committee for changes and once complete, for final approval by the Executive Council.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Heart Failure Society of America (HFSA) Guideline Committee sought resolution of difficult cases through consensus building. An open, dynamic discussion meant that no single voice was allowed to dominate. Written documents were essential to this process, because they provided the opportunity for feedback from all members of the group. On occasion, consensus of opinion was sufficient to override positive or negative results of almost any form of evidence. The HFSA process had a strong commitment to recommendations based on objective evidence rigorously reviewed by a panel of experts. Issues that caused difficulty for the HFSA guideline process were some of the more important ones faced by the committee, because they mirrored those that are often most challenging to clinicians in day-to-day practice. The foundation of the HFSA guideline process was the belief that the careful judgment of recognized opinion leaders in these controversial areas is more likely to be correct than ad hoc decisions made &quot;on the spot&quot; by physicians in practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classifying the Strength of the Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Classifying the Strength of the Recommendations&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Is recommended&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Part of routine care&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Exceptions to therapy should be minimized. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Should be considered&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Majority of patients should receive the intervention.&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Some discretion in application to individual patients should be allowed.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;May be considered&quot; &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Individualization of therapy is indicated.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Is not recommended&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Therapeutic intervention should not be used&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developer reviewed published cost analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each section was presented for comments and consensus approval to the Guideline Committee. Once subsections were complete, the Executive Council reviewed and commented on each section and these comments were returned to the Guideline Committee for changes and once complete, for final approval by the Executive Council.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strength of evidence (A, B, C) and strength of recommendations are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;It is recommended that the decision to undertake surgical intervention for severe heart failure (HF) be made in light of functional status and prognosis based on severity of underlying HF and comorbid conditions. Procedures should be done at centers with demonstrable expertise and multidisciplinary medical and surgical teams experienced in the selection, care, and perioperative and long-term management of high risk patients with severe HF. (Strength of Evidence = C) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Evaluation for heart transplantation is recommended in selected patients with severe HF, debilitating refractory angina, or ventricular arrhythmia that cannot be controlled despite drug, device, or alternative surgical therapy. (Strength of Evidence = B) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Isolated mitral valve repair or replacement for severe mitral regurgitation secondary to ventricular dilatation in the presence of severe left ventricular (LV) systolic dysfunction is not generally recommended. (Strength of Evidence = C) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Partial LV resection (&quot;Batista procedure&quot;) is not recommended in nonischemic cardiomyopathy. (Strength of Evidence = B) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients awaiting heart transplantation who have become refractory to all means of medical circulatory support should be considered for a mechanical support device as a bridge to transplant. (Strength of Evidence = B) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Permanent mechanical assistance using an implantable assist device may be considered in highly selected patients with severe HF refractory to conventional therapy who are not candidates for heart transplantation, particularly those who cannot be weaned from intravenous inotropic support at an experienced HF center. (Strength of Evidence = B) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients with refractory HF and hemodynamic instability, and/or compromised end-organ function, with relative contraindications to cardiac transplantation or permanent mechanical circulatory assistance expected to improve with time or restoration of an improved hemodynamic profile should be considered for urgent mechanical circulatory support as a &quot;bridge to decision.&quot; These patients should be referred to a center with expertise in the management of patients with advanced HF. (Strength of Evidence = C) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strength of Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Hierarchy of Types of Evidence&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Hierarchy of Types of Evidence&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level A&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Randomized, Controlled, Clinical Trials&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            May be assigned based on results of a single methodologically rigorous trial&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level B&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Cohort and Case-Control Studies&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Post hoc, subgroup analysis, and meta-analysis&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Prospective observational studies or registries&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level C&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Expert Opinion&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Observational studies &amp;ndash; epidemiologic findings&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Safety reporting from large-scale use in practice&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strength of Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Classifying the Strength of the Recommendations&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Is recommended&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Part of routine care&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Exceptions to therapy should be minimized. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Should be considered&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Majority of patients should receive the intervention.&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            Some discretion in application to individual patients should be allowed.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;May be considered&quot; &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Individualization of therapy is indicated.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&quot;Is not recommended&quot;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Therapeutic intervention should not be used&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of surgical treatment options in patients with heart failure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of left ventricular assist devices (LVADs) is associated with complications, including infection, bleeding, neurologic dysfunction, and device malfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Widely accepted contraindications to cardiac transplantation include diabetes mellitus with widespread microvascular complications, irreversible chronic kidney disease, and pulmonary hypertension, or other medical or psychosocial issues that would impact survival. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients with a recent history of non-skin malignancy have a relative contraindication for heart transplantation, but should be evaluated in collaboration with oncology experts. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It must be recognized that the evidence supporting recommendations is based largely on population responses that may not always apply to individuals within the population. Therefore, data may support overall benefit of one treatment over another but cannot exclude that some individuals within the population may respond better to the other treatment. Thus, guidelines can best serve as evidence-based recommendations for management, not as mandates for management in every patient. Furthermore, it must be recognized that trial data on which recommendations are based have often been carried out with background therapy not comparable to therapy in current use. Therefore, physician decisions regarding the management of individual patients may not always precisely match the recommendations. A knowledgeable physician who integrates the guidelines with pharmacologic and physiologic insight and knowledge of the individual being treated should provide the best patient management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The value of a practice guideline is significantly influenced by the scope of its dissemination. The first and second Heart Failure Society of America guidelines were available on the Internet, and thousands of copies were downloaded. The current document will be implemented on the Internet both for file transfer and as a hypertext source of detailed knowledge concerning heart failure (HF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Slide Presentation" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Heart Failure Society of America, Lindenfeld J, Albert NM, Boehmer JP, Collins SP, Ezekowitz JA, Givertz MM, Katz SD, Klapholz M, Moser DK, Rogers JG, Starling RC, Stevenson WG, Tang WH, Teerlink JR, Walsh MN. Surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure: HFSA 2010 comprehensive heart failure practice guideline. J Card Fail. 2010 Jun;16(6):e122-5. [41 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="1999 (revised 2010 Jun)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="Heart Failure Society of America, Inc - Disease Specific Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heart Failure Society of America, Inc&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heart Failure Society of America Guideline Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guideline Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: JoAnn Lindenfeld, MD (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Nancy M. Albert, RN, PhD; John P. Boehmer, MD; Sean P. Collins, MD, MSc; Justin A. Ezekowitz, MBBCh; Michael M. Givertz, MD; Stuart D. Katz, MD; Marc Klapholz, MD; Debra K. Moser, RN, DNSc; Joseph G. Rogers, MD; Randall C. Starling, MD, MPH; William G. Stevenson, MD; W.H. Wilson Tang, MD; John R. Teerlink, MD; Mary N. Walsh, MD&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Executive Council&lt;/em&gt;: Douglas L. Mann, MD, President; Inder S. Anand, MD; J. Malcolm O. Arnold, MD; John C. Burnett, Jr., MD; John Chin, MD; Jay N. Cohn, MD; Thomas Force, MD; Barry H. Greenberg, MD; Steven R. Houser, PhD; Mariell L. Jessup, MD; Barry M. Massie, MD; Mandeep R. Mehra, MD; Mariann R. Piano, RN, PhD; Clyde W. Yancy, MD; Michael R. Zile, MD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Committee members and reviewers from the Executive Council received no direct financial support from the Heart Failure Society of America (HFSA) or any other source for the development of the guideline. Support was provided by the HFSA administrative staff, but the writing of the document was performed on a volunteer basis primarily by the Committee. Financial relationships that might represent conflicts of interest were collected annually from all members of the Guideline Committee and the Executive Council. Current relationships are shown in Appendix C of the &quot;2010 HFSA Guideline Executive Summary&quot; companion document (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Heart Failure Society of America. Surgical approaches to the treatment of heart failure. J Card Fai 2006 Feb;12(1):e76-9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartfailureguideline.org/&quot; title=&quot;HFSA Web site&quot;&gt;Heart Failure Society of America, Inc. Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from the Heart Failure Society of America, Inc., Court International - Suite 240 S, 2550 University Avenue West, Saint Paul, Minnesota 55114; Phone: (651) 642-1633&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Heart Failure Society of America. Executive summary: The 2010 HFSA comprehensive heart failure practice guideline. J Card Fail 2010 Jun. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onlinejcf.com/article/S1071-9164%2810%2900174-0/fulltext&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&quot;&gt;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Heart Failure Society of America. Development and implementation of a comprehensive heart failure practice guideline. J Card Fail 2010 Jun;16(6):e3-6. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onlinejcf.com/article/S1071-9164%2810%2900174-0/fulltext&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&quot;&gt;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Heart Failure Society of America. Conceptualization and working definition of heart failure. J Card Fail 2010 Jun;16(6):e34-7. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onlinejcf.com/article/S1071-9164%2810%2900174-0/fulltext&quot; title=&quot;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&quot;&gt;Journal of Cardiac Failure Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;PowerPoint slides. HFSA 2010 comprehensive heart failure guideline. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartfailureguideline.org/slide_sets_all_recommendations/42&quot; title=&quot;HFSA Web site&quot;&gt;Heart Failure Society of America, Inc. Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from the Heart Failure Society of America, Inc., Court International - Suite 240 South, 2550 University Avenue West, Saint Paul, Minnesota 55114; Phone: (651) 642-1633&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI on July 31, 2006. The information was verified by the guideline developer on August 10, 2006. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on October 15, 2010. The updated information was verified by the guideline developer on November 23, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions. Please direct inquiries to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@hfsa.org&quot;&gt;info@hfsa.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
