<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 73 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 195).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates previous versions: National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Rituximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2007 Aug. 26 p. (Technology appraisal guidance; no. 126).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2008 Apr. 29 p. (Technology appraisal guidance; no. 141).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Rheumatoid arthritis  (714.0)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Anti-Inflammatory Agents ; Antibodies, Monoclonal ; Antirheumatic Agents ; Arthritis, Rheumatoid ; Drug Therapy, Combination ; Immunoconjugates ; Immunosuppressive Agents ; Methotrexate ; Treatment Failure ; Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Anti-Inflammatory Agents ; Antirheumatic Agents ; Combination Drug Therapy ; Etanercept ; Immunoconjugates ; Immunosuppressive Agents ; infliximab ; Methotrexate ; Monoclonal Antibodies ; Rheumatoid Arthritis ; treatment failure ; Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: etanercept ; infliximab ; methotrexate ; rituximab ; tumor necrosis factor alpha "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Abatacept  (421412005); Abatacept  (421777009); Adalimumab  (398728003); Adalimumab  (407317001); Anti-inflammatory agent  (330901000); Anti-inflammatory agent  (373283003); Anti-rheumatic agent  (372888006); Anti-rheumatic agent  (88279005); Disease activity score 28 joint in rheumatoid arthritis  (443728000); Etanercept  (118259007); Etanercept  (387045004); Immunosuppressant  (372823004); Immunosuppressant  (69431002); Infliximab  (108675009); Infliximab  (386891004); Methotrexate  (387381009); Methotrexate  (68887009); Monoclonal antibody  (49616005); Rheumatoid arthritis  (69896004); Rituximab  (108809004); Rituximab  (386919002); Tumor necrosis factor alpha  (39525005); Tumor necrosis factor alpha  (8612007)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severe active rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Rheumatology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, and abatacept for the treatment of severe active rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a tumor necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults with severe active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to, or are intolerant of, other disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs), including at least one tumor necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Rituximab in combination with methotrexate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, and abatacept, each in combination with methotrexate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab monotherapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Etanercept monotherapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Monitoring of treatment, with assessment of disease activity score (DAS28) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical effectiveness&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Withdrawals (with reason) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Treatment response (American College of Rheumatology criteria [ACR]) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Disease activity (disease activity score [DAS]) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Physical function (Health Assessment Questionnaire [HAQ]) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Pain &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Joint damage/radiological progression &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Fatigue &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Serious adverse events (including death) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Other adverse events potentially associated with treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Health related quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Unpublished Data" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare a Technology Assessment Report. The assessment report for this technology appraisal was prepared by the West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following resources were searched for relevant studies:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Bibliographic databases: Cochrane Library (CENTRAL) 2009 Issue 3, MEDLINE (Ovid) 1950 &amp;ndash; July week 1 2009, MEDLINE In-Process &amp;amp; Other Non-Indexed Citations (Ovid) 13 July 2009, EMBASE (Ovid) 1980 - 2009 week 28. Searches were based on index and text words that encompassed the condition: rheumatoid arthritis and the interventions: adalimumab, infliximab, etanercept, rituximab and abatacept. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Citations of included studies were examined. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reference lists of identified systematic reviews were checked. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Further information was sought from contacts with experts. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Research registries of ongoing trials including National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Clinical Research Network Portfolio Database, Current Controlled Trials and Clinical Trials.gov using terms for the particular drugs. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manufacturer submissions. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches were not limited by date of publication or language.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Search strategies can be found in Appendix 10.1 of the assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All articles identified in the searches were imported into a Reference Manager database (Reference Manager v.11, Thomson ResearchSoft). Duplicate entries were allowed to be removed by the inbuilt feature in Reference Manager and also removed when encountered by reviewers. Titles and abstracts were independently checked for relevance based on the population and intervention by two reviewers. If articles were considered relevant by at least one of the reviewers, a full paper copy was ordered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Full papers were assessed for relevance by two independent reviewers using an inclusion/exclusion checklist (see Appendix 10.6 of the assessment report) based on the following criteria:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Population: a majority of adults with active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to a tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intervention: adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, or abatacept &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Outcomes: clinical outcomes related to efficacy, safety or tolerability &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study design: primary study (except case reports) or a systematic review &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study duration: at least 12 weeks &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Participant numbers: for non-randomised studies - at least 20 patients in one arm &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Disagreements were resolved by discussion with involvement of a third reviewer when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conference abstracts were not sought. If they were identified as relevant in the first stage of study selection, an attempt was made to match them with journal publications. If this was not possible, contact with authors was not attempted due to time constraints and they were not included in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A list of excluded studies and the reason for exclusion were recorded (see Appendix 10.4 of the assessment report).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Included systematic reviews were not themselves systematically reviewed but were utilised to identify further primary studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additional references identified from systematic reviews or industry submissions were entered into the Reference Manager database. The same process was applied to them as to the references identified from initial searches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing Studies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing primary studies were identified in the searches. They were not included in the systematic review, but discussed in the assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Articles on the cost and cost-effectiveness of drugs for rheumatoid arthritis (RA) after the failure of a TNF inhibitor were identified from the searches for clinical effectiveness. In addition, National Health Service Economic Evaluation Database (NHS EED), Cochrane Library 2009 (Issue 3), and the internet sites of national economic units were searched.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All articles identified in the searches were imported into the same Reference Manager database (Reference Manager v.11, Thomson ResearchSoft) as for clinical effectiveness. Titles and abstracts were independently checked for relevance based on the population and intervention by two reviewers alongside selection of papers for clinical effectiveness. If articles were considered relevant by at least one of the reviewers, a full paper copy was ordered. A flow chart presenting the process of selection of studies for the systematic review can be found in Appendix 10.3 of the assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One reviewer applied the inclusion and exclusion criteria using a standard checklist (see Appendix 10.7 of the assessment report). Data were extracted by one reviewer using a predesigned data extraction form and were independently checked by a second reviewer. Data on the following were extracted:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study characteristics, such as form of economic analysis, population, interventions, comparators, perspective, time-horizon and modelling used &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Effectiveness and cost parameters, such as effectiveness data, health state valuations (utilities), resource-use data, unit cost data, and key assumptions &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Results and sensitivity analyses &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There were 35 studies described in 44 papers meeting the inclusion criteria. Five of the studies were randomised controlled trials (RCTs), one was a comparative study, one was a non-randomised controlled study and 28 uncontrolled studies (including one long term extension of an RCT).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A flow diagram presenting the process of identification of relevant studies can be found in Appendix 10.3 of the assessment report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Four studies met the inclusion criteria - two abatacept studies and two rituximab economic evaluations. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;All five manufacturers submitted economic analyses. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare a Technology Assessment Report. The assessment report for this technology appraisal was prepared by the West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Extraction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data was extracted into a standard form (see Appendix 1.1 of the assessment report) for all included studies by one reviewer. A second reviewer checked the accuracy of extracted information. Disagreements were resolved by consensus or by referral to a third reviewer if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Information regarding study design and characteristics of study participants was extracted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data on the following outcomes was sought from included studies:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Treatment withdrawal (and reasons for withdrawal) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;American College of Rheumatology (ACR)20, ACR50, ACR70 &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Disease activity (e.g., Disease Activity Score [DAS]28 or DAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Physical function (e.g., Health Assessment Questionnaire) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Joint damage/radiological progression (measured by a scoring system) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Pain &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Fatigue &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Extra-articular manifestations of the disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Serious adverse events (including death) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Other adverse effects potentially associated with treatments &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health-related quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data for any outcomes other than those listed above was also extracted if it was considered relevant to this report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additional data from industry submissions was extracted by only one reviewer due to time constraints.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quality of included studies was assessed independently by two reviewers. Any disagreements were resolved by discussion and if necessary a third reviewer was consulted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For randomised trials, the following criteria were considered:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Randomisation &amp;ndash; whether allocation was truly random. Randomisation using computer or random number table was considered adequate whereas the use of alternation, case record numbers, or dates of birth and day of the week was considered inadequate. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Allocation concealment &amp;ndash; whether allocation concealment was adequate. Any of the following methods was considered adequate: centralised (e.g., allocation by a central office unaware of subject characteristics) or pharmacy-controlled randomisation; prenumbered or coded identical containers which are administered serially to participants; on-site computer system combined with allocations kept in a locked unreadable computer file that can be accessed only after the characteristics of an enrolled participant have been entered; sequentially numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Blinding &amp;ndash; use of blinding and who was blinded (patients, study investigators/outcome assessors, data analysts). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients withdrawn &amp;ndash; what was the percentage of patients withdrawn from the study. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intention to Treat (ITT) analysis &amp;ndash; whether ITT analysis was used. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For non-randomised studies, the following criteria were considered:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study design &amp;ndash; if the study was controlled or uncontrolled, prospective or retrospective. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Inclusion criteria &amp;ndash; if inclusion criteria were clearly stated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consecutive patients &amp;ndash; if consecutive patients were included in the study. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patients withdrawn &amp;ndash; what was the percentage of patients withdrawn from the study. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Analysis/Synthesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comparisons with Supportive Care&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Studies were considered separately for each of the interventions. In addition tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitors were discussed together as a class of drugs. Results were presented in figures and discussed in the assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For dichotomous measures data is presented as relative risks (for randomised controlled trials [RCTs]) and percentages (for other study designs). For continuous outcomes mean differences (for RCTs) and means (for other study designs) were used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pooling of results was not attempted for the assessment of effectiveness of individual technologies because the majority of included studies had no control group and there is substantial methodological and clinical heterogeneity between included studies. Given the relatively small number of patients that can be analysed in subgroup analyses, some pooling of data using random effects model was attempted. The results were presented with I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; statistics mainly for demonstrating consistency of findings between studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 5 of the assessment report for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systematic Review of Existing Cost-Effectiveness Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Four studies met the inclusion criteria and the key features of these studies are summarised in Table 69 of the assessment report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). Further details of the four studies are presented in Appendix 10.9 of the assessment report; their quality was assessed using a simplified version of the Drummond and Jefferson checklist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modelling Approach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each study used a different modelling approach. One of the studies used a simple decision-tree structure and modelled cost and outcomes over 2 years. The second study used a patient-simulation model exploring two time horizons: 10 years and lifetime. The third study used a Markov model structure with a lifetime time horizon and a 6-month cycle length. The fourth study used a patient-level simulation model. The time horizon of the model appears to be lifetime although this was not explicitly stated in the paper. The model runs for continuous time with no fixed cycle length.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A direct comparison of incremental cost-effectiveness ratios (ICERs) between studies is not possible because of different approaches to modelling, in particular time-horizon, country of origin and perspective chosen &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;All studies used a decision-analytic model. Published models vary in some important aspects: the type of model used, the sequence of drugs, comparator therapies, and time-horizon &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incremental analyses, to which appropriate sensitivity analyses had been applied, were reported without exception &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;All but one study carried out a cost-utility analysis and reported results in cost per quality-adjusted life year (QALY). One study carried out a cost-effectiveness analysis and reported results in cost per additional case of 'low disease-activity state' gained (disease activity score [DAS]28 &amp;lt;2.6) and cost per additional remission gained (DAS28 &amp;le;3.2) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;There was disparity in the selection of perspectives chosen for the analyses. One study reported costs that include both those from a healthcare perspective as well as indirect costs and costs of informal care; inclusion of these costs improves the cost-effectiveness of the drug. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critique of Manufacturers' Submissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A submission was received from each company with each submission containing an economic analysis. However, only four manufacturers included a model. Table 71 of the assessment report and sections 2, 3, and 4 of the addendum to the assessment report provide a brief summary of the five economic analyses provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independent Economic Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Assessment Group's own independent analysis was carried out using the Birmingham Rheumatoid Arthritis Model (BRAM), which has been further updated to allow for a non-linear relationship between Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) and utility. Additional coding has been added to the model to facilitate the use of probabilistic sensitivity analysis (PSA). This means putting a distribution around all parameters in the model. Unless there is a good reason to treat a parameter as fixed, some distribution has been used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The BRAM is an individual sampling model. A large number of virtual patient histories is simulated with the accumulation of costs and QALYs. The basic model structure is shown in Figure 93 of the assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 6 of the assessment report and to the addendum to the assessment report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field) for further details on cost-effectiveness analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technology appraisal recommendations are based on a review of clinical and economic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology Appraisal Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) invites 'consultee' and 'commentator' organisations to take part in the appraisal process. Consultee organisations include national groups representing patients and carers, the bodies representing health professionals, and the manufacturers of the technology under review. Consultees are invited to submit evidence during the appraisal and to comment on the appraisal documents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Commentator organisations include manufacturers of the products with which the technology is being compared, the National Health Service (NHS) Quality Improvement Scotland and research groups working in the area. They can comment on the evidence and other documents but are not asked to submit evidence themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE then commissions an independent academic centre to review published evidence on the technology and prepare an 'assessment report'. Consultees and commentators are invited to comment on the report. The assessment report and the comments on it are then drawn together in a document called the evaluation report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An independent Appraisal Committee then considers the evaluation report. It holds a meeting where it hears direct, spoken evidence from nominated clinical experts, patients and carers. The Committee uses all the evidence to make its first recommendations, in a document called the 'appraisal consultation document' (ACD). NICE sends all the consultees and commentators a copy of this document and posts it on the NICE website. Further comments are invited from everyone taking part.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the Committee meets again it considers any comments submitted on the ACD; then it prepares its final recommendations in a document called the 'final appraisal determination' (FAD). This is submitted to NICE for approval.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consultees have a chance to appeal against the final recommendations in the FAD. If there are no appeals, the final recommendations become the basis of the guidance that NICE issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Is on the Appraisal Committee?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE technology appraisal recommendations are prepared by an independent committee. This includes health professionals working in the NHS and people who are familiar with the issues affecting patients and carers. Although the Appraisal Committee seeks the views of organisations representing health professionals, patients, carers, manufacturers and government, its advice is independent of any vested interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manufacturers' Submissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All five manufacturers provided economic analyses to support their submissions. One analysis (etanercept, Pfizer) was provided only as a narrative summary and not as a fully executable model. All submissions were based on cost&amp;ndash;utility analyses run over a lifetime horizon and from the perspective of the healthcare provider. All but one submission (abatacept, Bristol-Myers Squibb) used conventional disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs) as the base-case comparator.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to section 4 of the original guideline document for details of these submissions and a discussion of the evidence by the Appraisal Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Birmingham Rheumatoid Arthritis Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Assessment Group carried out an independent economic analysis using the Birmingham Rheumatoid Arthritis Model. The model simulated people with rheumatoid arthritis based on the baseline characteristics of people in the British Society for Rheumatology Biologics Register. The model sampled people individually and compared each of the technologies (followed by a sequence of conventional DMARDs) with one another or with conventional DMARDs alone. It allowed for two stages of stopping treatment early. The first stage represented the possibility of stopping treatment after 6 weeks (assumed to be because of toxicity) and the second stage represented stopping treatment at between 6 and 24 weeks (assumed to be because of either toxicity or lack of efficacy). The model did not allow for stopping rituximab early because it was necessary to model the full costs of each cycle of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to section 4 for of the original guideline document for further details.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Appraisal Committee's Key Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Rituximab was considered to be a cost-effective option, based on data from most of the models available for this appraisal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Based on the evidence available, the incremental cost-effectiveness ratios (ICERs) for adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab and abatacept compared with rituximab were either very high, or these drugs were dominated by rituximab (that is, rituximab was both more effective and less costly). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;For people who are unable to take rituximab or methotrexate, the appropriate comparator was conventional DMARDs. Based on the evidence available, adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab and abatacept compared with conventional DMARDs were considered cost-effective options based on data from most of the models available for this appraisal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 4 of the original guideline document for additional information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultee organisations from the following groups were invited to comment on the draft scope, Assessment Report and the Appraisal Consultation Document (ACD) and were provided with the opportunity to appeal against the Final Appraisal Determination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manufacturer/sponsors &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Professional/specialist and patient/carer groups &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Commentator organisations (without the right of appeal) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, individuals selected from clinical expert and patient advocate nominations from the professional/specialist and patient/carer groups were also invited to comment on the ACD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note from the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This guidance replaces NICE technology appraisal guidance 126 and 141 issued in August 2007 and April 2008, respectively. It also replaces the remaining recommendations in NICE technology appraisal guidance 36 issued in March 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The appraisal of adalimumab and the review of the appraisals of etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis have resulted in changes in the guidance. Rituximab in combination with methotrexate is still recommended as an option for the treatment of adults with severe active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to, or have an intolerance of, other disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs), including at least one tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor. Additional treatment options are now recommended for these adults if rituximab therapy is contraindicated or withdrawn because of an adverse event, specifically:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;If rituximab is contraindicated or withdrawn, adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab and abatacept, each in combination with methotrexate, are now recommended as treatment options. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;If rituximab therapy cannot be given because methotrexate is contraindicated or withdrawn because of an adverse event, adalimumab and etanercept, each as monotherapy, are now recommended as treatment options. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rituximab in combination with methotrexate is recommended as an option for the treatment of adults with severe active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to, or are intolerant of, other DMARDs, including at least one TNF inhibitor. Treatment with rituximab should be given no more frequently than every 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment with rituximab in combination with methotrexate should be continued only if there is an adequate response following initiation of therapy and if an adequate response is maintained following retreatment with a dosing interval of at least 6 months. An adequate response is defined as an improvement in disease activity score (DAS28) of 1.2 points or more.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab and abatacept, each in combination with methotrexate, are recommended as treatment options only for adults with severe active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to, or have an intolerance of, other DMARDs, including at least one TNF inhibitor, and who cannot receive rituximab therapy because they have a contraindication to rituximab, or when rituximab is withdrawn because of an adverse event.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Adalimumab monotherapy and etanercept monotherapy are recommended as treatment options for adults with severe active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to, or have an intolerance of, other DMARDs, including at least one TNF inhibitor, and who cannot receive rituximab therapy because they have a contraindication to methotrexate, or when methotrexate is withdrawn because of an adverse event.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment with adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab and abatacept should be continued only if there is an adequate response (as defined above) 6 months after initiation of therapy. Treatment should be monitored, with assessment of DAS28, at least every 6 months and continued only if an adequate response is maintained.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When using DAS28, healthcare professionals should take into account any physical, sensory or learning disabilities, communication difficulties, or disease characteristics that could adversely affect patient assessment and make any adjustments they consider appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A team experienced in the diagnosis and treatment of rheumatoid arthritis and working under the supervision of a rheumatologist should initiate, supervise and assess response to treatment with rituximab, adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab or abatacept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations are based on evidence from randomised controlled trials (RCTs), a comparative study, a non-randomised controlled study, and uncontrolled studies (including two long-term RCT extensions).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, and abatacept for the treatment of severe active rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a tumour necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Common adverse effects of adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab, and abatacept include acute injection-site reactions, infections, delayed hypersensitivity reactions, and allergic reactions. Before initiating therapy, physicians should evaluate people for both active and inactive (latent) tuberculosis infection.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects, contraindications, special warnings, and precautions for use, see the summary of product characteristics (SPC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adalimumab&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;infliximab&lt;/em&gt; are contraindicated in people with moderate to severe heart failure, those with active tuberculosis, or those with other severe or opportunistic infections. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Etanercept&lt;/em&gt; is contraindicated in people with sepsis or risk of sepsis, and those with other active infections. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rituximab&lt;/em&gt; is contraindicated in people with severe heart failure or severe, uncontrolled cardiac disease, and those with active, severe infections. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abatacept&lt;/em&gt; is contraindicated in people with severe, uncontrolled infections, and opportunistic infections. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects, contraindications, special warnings, and precautions for use see the summary of product characteristics (SPC).&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. However, the guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way which would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has issued directions to the National Health Service (NHS) on implementing National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) technology appraisal guidance. When a NICE technology appraisal recommends use of a drug or treatment, or other technology, the NHS must provide funding and resources for it within 3 months of the guidance being published. If the Department of Health issues a variation to the 3-month funding direction, details will be available on the NICE website. The NHS is not required to fund treatments that are not recommended by NICE.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE has developed tools to help organisations put this guidance into practice (listed below). These are available on the NICE website (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/TA195&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk/guidance/TA195&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Costing template and report to estimate the national and local savings and costs associated with implementation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Audit support for monitoring local practice &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 73 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 195).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2007 Aug (revised 2010 Aug)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appraisal Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Dr Amanda Adler (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Consultant Physician, Addenbrooke's Hospital; Dr Ray Armstrong, Consultant Rheumatologist, Southampton General Hospital; Dr Jeff Aronson, Reader in Clinical Pharmacology, University Department of Primary Health Care, University of Oxford; Dr Peter Barry, Consultant in Paediatric Intensive Care, Leicester Royal Infirmary; Dr Michael Boscoe, Consultant Cardiothoracic Anaesthetist, Royal Brompton and Harefield NHS Foundation Trust; Professor John Cairns, Professor of Health Economics, Public Health and Policy, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine; Dr Mark Chakravarty, External Relations Director &amp;ndash; Pharmaceuticals and Personal Health, Oral Care Europe; Dr Fergus Gleeson, Consultant Radiologist, Churchill Hospital, Oxford; Ms Sally Gooch, Independent Nursing and Healthcare Consultant; Mrs Eleanor Grey, Lay member; Mr Sanjay Gupta, YPD Service Case Manager, Southwark Health and Social Care, Southwark, Primary Care Trust; Dr Neil Iosson, General Practitioner; Mr Terence Lewis, Lay member; Dr Ruairidh Milne, Director of Strategy and Development and Director for Public Health Research NIHR Evaluation, Trials and Studies Coordinating Centre, University of Southampton; Mr Stephen Palmer, Senior Research Fellow, Centre for Health Economics, University of York; Dr John Pounsford, Consultant Physician, Frenchay Hospital, Bristol; Mr Navin Sewak, Primary Care Pharmacist, NHS Hammersmith and Fulham; Dr Lindsay Smith, General Practitioner, East Somerset Research Consortium; Mr Roderick Smith; Finance Director, West Kent Primary Care Trust; Mr Cliff Snelling, Lay member; Professor Ken Stein (&lt;em&gt;Vice Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Professor of Public Health, Peninsula Technology Assessment Group (PenTAG), University of Exeter; Professor Andrew Stevens, Professor of Public Health, Department of Public Health and Epidemiology, University of Birmingham; Dr Rod Taylor, Associate Professor in Health Services Research, Peninsula Medical School, Universities of Exeter and Plymouth; Mr Tom Wilson, Director of Contracting and Performance, NHS Tameside and Glossop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Committee members are asked to declare any interests in the technology to be appraised. If it is considered there is a conflict of interest, the member is excluded from participating further in that appraisal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates previous versions: National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Rituximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2007 Aug. 26 p. (Technology appraisal guidance; no. 126).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2008 Apr. 29 p. (Technology appraisal guidance; no. 141).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. Quick reference guide. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 2 p. (Technology appraisal 195). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195/QuickRefGuide/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. Audit support. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. 8 p. (Technology appraisal 195). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195/AuditSupport/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. Costing template. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug. (Technology appraisal 195). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195/CostingTemplate/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis after the failure of a TNF inhibitor. Assessment report. West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Collaboration; 2010 Mar. 345 p. (Technology appraisal 195). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=47685&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, rituximab and abatacept for rheumatoid arthritis. Understanding NICE guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Aug 22. 4 p. (Technology appraisal 195). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195/PublicInfo/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in Welsh from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA195/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on October 17, 2007. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on October 8, 2008 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Rituxan (rituximab). This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on February 22, 2011. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on October 12, 2011 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory on Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF&amp;alpha;) Blockers. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 21, 2013 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Arzerra (ofatumumab) and Rituxan (rituximab).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their Technology Appraisal guidance with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects the original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE technology appraisal guidance is prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
