<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;EFNS guideline on the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis in adult patients.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Einhaupl K, Stam J, Bousser MG, De Bruijn SF, Ferro JM, Martinelli I, Masuhr F. EFNS guideline on the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis in adult  patients. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Oct;17(10):1229-35. [37 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=20402748&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Einhaupl K, Bousser MG, de Bruijn SF, Ferro JM, Martinelli I, Masuhr F, Stam J. EFNS guideline on the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis. Eur J Neurol 2006 Jun;13(6):553-9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Cerebral edema  (348.5); Cerebral thrombosis without mention of cerebral infarction  (434.00); Edema  (782.3); Nonpyogenic thrombosis of intracranial venous sinus  (437.6); Other venous embolism and thrombosis of unspecified site  (453.9)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Acetazolamide ; Administration, Oral ; Anticoagulants ; Anticonvulsants ; Cerebrospinal Fluid Shunts ; Chemoprevention ; Edema ; Heparin ; Heparin, Low-Molecular-Weight ; Intracranial Thrombosis ; Sinus Thrombosis, Intracranial ; Spinal Puncture ; Thromboembolism ; Thrombolytic Therapy ; Tissue Plasminogen Activator ; Urokinase-Type Plasminogen Activator ; Venous Thrombosis "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Acetazolamide ; alteplase ; Anticoagulants ; Anticonvulsants ; Cerebral arterial thrombosis ; Cerebral Edema ; Cerebrospinal fluid shunts procedure ; Chemoprevention ; edema ; Heparin ; Heparin, Low-Molecular-Weight ; Intracranial Thrombosis ; Spinal Puncture ; Thromboembolism ; Urokinase ; Venous Thrombosis "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: cerebral edema ; heparin ; recombinant tissue plasminogen activator ; thromboembolism ; thrombolytic therapy ; urokinase "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Acetazolamide  (33664007); Acetazolamide  (372709008); Alteplase  (108997009); Alteplase  (27638005); Alteplase  (37411004); Alteplase  (387152000); Anticoagulant  (372862008); Anticoagulant  (81839001); Anticonvulsant  (255632006); Anticonvulsant  (63094006); Cerebral edema  (2032001); Cerebral thrombosis  (71444005); Cerebral venous sinus thrombosis  (192759008); Creation of cerebrospinal fluid shunt  (119566000); Edema  (20741006); Edema  (267038008); Edema  (423666004); Edema  (79654002); Heparin  (372877000); Heparin  (84812008); Heparin  (96382006); Intracranial venous thrombosis  (297157005); Low molecular weight heparin  (373294004); Low molecular weight heparin  (87233003); Lumbar puncture  (277762005); Medication administration: oral  (386359008); Nonpyogenic thrombosis of intracranial venous sinus  (42970005); Prophylactic chemotherapy  (268500004); Thromboembolic disorder  (13713005); Thromboembolic disorder  (371039008); Thrombolytic therapy  (426347000); Thrombosis of cerebral veins  (95455008); Urokinase  (319826005); Urokinase  (59082006); Venous thrombosis  (111293003)"/><FieldValue Value="SPN: HEPARIN "/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Critical Care" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Neurological Surgery" /><FieldValue Value="Neurology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To review the strength of evidence for the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST) and provide recommendations on the therapy of CVST based on the best available evidence for the efficacy and safety of anticoagulant therapy, thrombolysis and symptomatic therapy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management/Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Heparin therapy&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Body weight-adjusted subcutaneous low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH) or dose-adjusted intravenous heparin &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Oral anticoagulation therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Symptomatic treatment&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Control of seizures (e.g., prophylactic antiepileptic therapy) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Treatment of elevated intracranial pressure (e.g., lumbar puncture, acetazolamide and incidentally cerebrospinal fluid-shunting procedures, antiedema treatment) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Systemic and local thrombolysis was considered but not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST) severity scale (evaluates headache, focal signs, and level of consciousness) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Late seizures &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Recurrent episodes of CVST &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse effects of therapy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;MEDLINE 1966&amp;ndash;2009 and EMBASE 1966&amp;ndash;2009 were examined with appropriate MESH and free subject terms: 1. CVST, 2. cerebral venous thrombosis, 3. cortical vein thrombosis 4. intracranial thrombosis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One to four was combined with the terms: 7. treatment, 8. medication, 9. therapy, 10. controlled clinical trial, 11. randomized controlled trial, 12. multicentre study, 13. meta-analysis, 14. anticoagulation (AC), 15. thrombolysis, 16. local thrombolysis, 17. antiepileptic therapy, 18. intracranial pressure, 19. steroids, 20. hyperventilation, 21. osmotic diuretics, 22. craniectomy, 23. decompressive surgery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials and the Cochrane Library and references of selected articles were also searched. Review articles and book chapters were also included if they were considered to provide comprehensive reviews of the topic. The search included reports of research in human beings only and in English language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Classification Scheme for a Therapeutic Intervention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class I&lt;/strong&gt;: An adequately powered prospective, randomized, controlled clinical trial with masked outcome assessment in a representative population or an adequately powered systematic review of prospective randomized controlled clinical trials with masked outcome assessment in representative populations. The following are required:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: lower-alpha;&quot;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Randomization concealment&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Primary outcome(s) is/are clearly defined&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusion/inclusion criteria are clearly defined&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adequate accounting for dropouts and crossovers with numbers sufficiently low to have minimal potential for bias&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Relevant baseline characteristics are presented and substantially equivalent among treatment groups or there is appropriate statistical adjustment for differences&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class II&lt;/strong&gt;: Prospective matched-group cohort study in a representative population with masked outcome assessment that meets a&amp;ndash;e above or a randomized, controlled trial in a representative population that lacks one criteria a&amp;ndash;e.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class III&lt;/strong&gt;: All other controlled trials (including well-defined natural history controls or patients serving as own controls) in a representative population, where outcome assessment is independent of patient treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class IV&lt;/strong&gt;: Evidence from uncontrolled studies, case series, case reports, or expert opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The classification for evidence levels for therapeutic interventions was made according to the guidance for the preparation of neurological management guidelines by European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) scientific task forces (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; field and &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force included six neurologists and one specialist in Internal Medicine with an expertise in the field of haemostasis and thrombosis (I. M.). The literature search was performed by K.E. and F.M. who also prepared a first draft of the manuscript. The manuscript was sent via e-mail and was reviewed by all members of the Task Force, and suggestions and corrections were incorporated. Recommendations were reached by consensus of all Task Force members and were also based on their own awareness and clinical experience. Where there was a lack of evidence but consensus was clear, the Task Force members stated their opinion as good practice points. The final draft of the manuscript was approved by all members of the Task Force. All necessary steps for the preparation of the presented recommendation were performed via e-mail correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating of Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level A rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least one convincing class I study or at least two consistent, convincing class II studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level B rating&lt;/strong&gt; (probably effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least one convincing class II study or overwhelming class III evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level C rating&lt;/strong&gt; (possibly effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least two convincing class III studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good practice point (GPP)&lt;/strong&gt; Where there was lack of evidence but consensus was clear the Task Force members have stated their opinion as good practice points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines were validated according to the European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) criteria (See &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). The final draft of the manuscript was approved by all members of the Task Force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The levels of evidence (Class I-IV) supporting the recommendations and ratings of recommendations (A-C, Good practice point [GPP]) are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Heparin Therapy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Current evidence shows that patients with cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST) without contraindications for anticoagulation (AC) should be treated either with body weight-adjusted subcutaneous low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH) or with dose-adjusted intravenous heparin with an at least doubled activated partial thromboplastin time (&lt;strong&gt;Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). Concomitant intracranial haemorrhage (ICH) related to CVST is not a contraindication for heparin therapy. For the reasons mentioned in the original guideline document under &quot;Heparin therapy,&quot; LMWH should be preferred in uncomplicated CVST cases.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Thrombolysis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is insufficient evidence to support the use of either systemic or local thrombolysis in patients with CVST. If patients deteriorate despite adequate AC and other causes of deterioration have been ruled out, thrombolysis may be a therapeutic option in selected cases, possibly in those without ICH or impending herniation from large haemorrhagic infarcts (&lt;strong&gt;Good Practice Point [GPP]&lt;/strong&gt;). The optimal substance, dosage, route (systemic or local) or method of administration (repeated bolus or bolus plus infusion) are not known.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Oral Anticoagulation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are insufficient data about the optimal duration of oral anticoagulation therapy (OAT) in patients with CVST. Analogous to patients with a first episode of extracerebral venous thrombosis, OAT may be given for 3 months if CVST was secondary to a transient risk factor, for 6 to 12 months in patients with idiopathic CVST and in those with &quot;mild&quot; thrombophilia. Indefinite OAT should be considered in patients with two or more episodes of CVST and in those with one episode of CVST and &quot;severe&quot; thrombophilia (&lt;strong&gt;GPP&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Symptomatic Treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control of Seizures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prophylactic antiepileptic therapy may be a therapeutic option in patients with focal neurological deficits and supratentorial lesions on admission computed tomography/magnetic resonance imaging (CT/MRI) (&lt;strong&gt;GPP&lt;/strong&gt;). The optimal duration of treatment for patients with seizures is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treatment of Elevated Intracranial Pressure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In patients with isolated intracranial hypertension (IIH) and threatened vision, possible therapeutic measures may include one or more lumbar punctures, acetazolamide and incidental cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)-shunting procedures. There are no controlled data about the risks and benefits of certain therapeutic measures to reduce an elevated intracranial pressure in patients with CVST. However, based on the available evidence, steroids seem not to be useful and should be avoided (&lt;strong&gt;GPP&lt;/strong&gt;). Antioedema treatment should be carried out according to general principles of therapy of raised intracranial pressure. In a small subgroup of patients with severe CVST and impending herniation attributable to large haemorrhagic infarcts, decompressive craniectomy can be life-saving (&lt;strong&gt;GPP&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Classification Scheme for a Therapeutic Intervention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class I&lt;/strong&gt;: An adequately powered prospective, randomized, controlled clinical trial with masked outcome assessment in a representative population or an adequately powered systematic review of prospective randomized controlled clinical trials with masked outcome assessment in representative populations. The following are required:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: lower-alpha;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Randomization concealment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Primary outcome(s) is/are clearly defined &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusion/inclusion criteria are clearly defined &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adequate accounting for dropouts and crossovers with numbers sufficiently low to have minimal potential for bias &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Relevant baseline characteristics are presented and substantially equivalent among treatment groups or there is appropriate statistical adjustment for differences &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class II&lt;/strong&gt;: Prospective matched-group cohort study in a representative population with masked outcome assessment that meets a&amp;ndash;e above or a randomized, controlled trial in a representative population that lacks one criteria a&amp;ndash;e.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class III&lt;/strong&gt;: All other controlled trials (including well-defined natural history controls or patients serving as own controls) in a representative population, where outcome assessment is independent of patient treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class IV&lt;/strong&gt;: Evidence from uncontrolled studies, case series, case reports, or expert opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating of Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level A rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least one convincing class I study or at least two consistent, convincing class II studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level B rating&lt;/strong&gt; (probably effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least one convincing class II study or overwhelming class III evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level C rating&lt;/strong&gt; (possibly effective, ineffective, or harmful) requires at least two convincing class III studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good practice point (GPP)&lt;/strong&gt; Where there was lack of evidence but consensus was clear the Task Force members have stated their opinion as good practice points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for selected recommendations (see &amp;quot;Major Recommendations&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis (CVST)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prolonged oral anticoagulation (OAT) may expose some patients to an unnecessary bleeding risk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guideline provides the view of an expert task force appointed by the Scientific Committee of the European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS). It represents a peer-reviewed statement of minimum desirable standards for the guidance of practice based on the best available evidence. It is not intended to have legally binding implications in individual cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The European Federation of Neurological Societies has a mailing list and all guideline papers go to national societies, national ministries of health, World Health Organisation, European Union, and a number of other destinations. Corporate support is recruited to buy large numbers of reprints of the guideline papers and permission is given to sponsoring companies to distribute the guideline papers from their commercial channels, provided there is no advertising attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Einhaupl K, Stam J, Bousser MG, De Bruijn SF, Ferro JM, Martinelli I, Masuhr F. EFNS guideline on the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis in adult  patients. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Oct;17(10):1229-35. [37 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=20402748&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2006 Jun (revised 2010 Oct)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="European Academy of Neurology - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies Task Force on the Treatment of Cerebral Venous and Sinus Thrombosis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Task Force Members&lt;/em&gt;: K. Einh&amp;auml;upl, Department of Neurology, Charit&amp;eacute;-Universitatsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany; J. Stam, Department of Neurology, Academic Medical Centre Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands; M.-G. Bousser, Department of Neurology, H&amp;ocirc;pital Lariboisi&amp;egrave;re, Paris, France; S. F. T. M. de Bruijn, Department of Neurology, Haga Hospital The Hague and LUMC, Leiden, The Netherlands; J. M. Ferro, Department of Neurology, Hospital Santa Maria, Lisboa, Portugal; I. Martinelli, A. Bianchi Bonomi Hemophilia and Thrombosis Center, IRCCS Maggiore Hospital, University of Milan, Milan, Italy; and F. Masuhr, Department of Neurology, Charit&amp;eacute;-Universitatsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Einhaupl K, Bousser MG, de Bruijn SF, Ferro JM, Martinelli I, Masuhr F, Stam J. EFNS guideline on the treatment of cerebral venous and sinus thrombosis. Eur J Neurol 2006 Jun;13(6):553-9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.efns.org/fileadmin/user_upload/guidline_papers/EFNS_guideline_2010_treatment_of_cerebral_venous_and_sinus_thrombosis.pdf&quot; title=&quot;EFNS Web site&quot;&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from Karl Einh&amp;auml;upl, Department of Neurology, Charit&amp;eacute; Medical School, Humboldt-University, Schumann Strasse 20-21, 10117 Berlin, Germany; Phone: 0049-30-450-560102; Fax: 0049-30-450-560932; E-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:karl.einhaeupl@charite.de&quot;&gt;karl.einhaeupl@charite.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Brainin M, Barnes M, Baron JC, Gilhus NE, Hughes R, Selmaj K, Waldemar G; Guideline Standards Subcommittee of the EFNS Scientific Committee. Guidance for the preparation of neurological management guidelines by EFNS scientific task forces &amp;ndash; revised recommendations 2004. Eur J Neurol. 2004 Sep;11(9):577-81. Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.efns.org/fileadmin/user_upload/guidline_papers/EFNS_guideline_2004_neurological_management_guidelines.pdf&quot; title=&quot;European Federation of Neurological Societies Web site&quot;&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI on March 27, 2007. The information was verified by the guideline developer on September 18, 2007. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on March 14, 2008, following the updated FDA advisory on heparin sodium injection. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on December 26, 2008, following the FDA advisory on Innohep (tinzaparin). This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on May 1, 2009, following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on antiepileptic drugs. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on July 27, 2010, following the FDA drug safety communication on Heparin. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on February 11, 2011. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on March 10, 2014 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory on Low Molecular Weight Heparins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the Blackwell-Synergy copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
