<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Oct. 46 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 203).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Diabetes with other coma, type II or unspecified type, not stated as uncontrolled  (250.30)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2 ; Drug Therapy, Combination ; Glucagon-Like Peptide 1 ; Hypoglycemic Agents ; Incretins ; Metformin ; Sulfonylurea Compounds ; Thiazolidinediones "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Combination Drug Therapy ; Diabetes Mellitus, Non-Insulin-Dependent ; Glucagon-Like Peptide 1 ; Incretins ; Sulfonylurea Compounds ; Thiazolidinediones "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Antidiabetic preparation  (373245004); Antidiabetic preparation  (384953001); Glucagon-like peptide 1  (43004008); Hypoglycemic agent  (312064005); Hypoglycemic agent  (373299009); Incretin  (417524005); Metformin  (109081006); Metformin  (372567009); Sulfonylurea  (259552008); Sulfonylurea  (34012005); Sulfonylurea  (372711004); Thiazolidinedione  (109086001); Thiazolidinedione  (372568004); Type 2 diabetes mellitus  (44054006)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type 2 diabetes mellitus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Assessment of Therapeutic Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Endocrinology" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess the clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide 1.2 mg in triple therapy regimens in combination with metformin and a sulphonylurea, or metformin and a thiazolidinedione &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide 1.2 mg in dual therapy regimens in combination with metformin or a sulphonylurea &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Liraglutide 1.8 mg was considered but not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical effectiveness&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Weight gain or loss &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Blood pressure &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Fasting plasma glucose &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Lipids &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Adverse effects &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cost-effectiveness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Unpublished Data" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by Aberdeen Health Technology Assessment Group (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The submitted evidence of clinical effectiveness came mainly from the series of studies known as the Liraglutide Effect and Action on Diabetes (LEAD) programme. The most relevant amongst these were the studies in which liraglutide was used as part of triple therapy, and compared with an active comparator. These were LEAD-5, which compared liraglutide with the long-acting insulin, glargine, and LEAD-6, which compared liraglutide with another glucagon like peptide (GLP)-1 agonist, exenatide. The list of all trials identified by the manufacturer in the industry submission and ERG reasons to exclude some from the Cochrane review (in preparation) are included in Appendix 1 of the ERG report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ERG considered the manufacturer's submission to be of good quality. All relevant trials were included. The ERG cross-checked against their own searches for the Cochrane review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Literature Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One study on cost-effectiveness was found. This was a study sponsored by the manufacturer, and with co-authors from the company. It was based only on the LEAD-1 trial, which was of dual therapy, not all costs were included, and the perspective was from a US health care payer one. It used the Center for Outcomes Research (CORE) model. The ERG thinks this study is superseded by the industry submission, and it is not included here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Six randomised controlled trials (RCTs) were identified and presented in the manufacturer's submission.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer of liraglutide submitted an economic model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) commissioned an independent academic centre to perform a systematic literature review on the technology considered in this appraisal and prepare an Evidence Review Group (ERG) report. The ERG report for this technology appraisal was prepared by Aberdeen Health Technology Assessment Group (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ERG identified a number of discrepancies between different parts of the submission, and between the submission and published papers, but these were mostly minor, and arose because of rounding in some papers but not others, or because some figures came from different analyses such as intention to treat, or as observed, or adjusted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ERG used the manufacturer's submission, the published papers, and the full clinical trial reports for LEAD-5 and LEAD-6, and 1860 trial, which were provided by the manufacturer. One author attended a satellite symposium at the 20th World Diabetes Congress (WDC) in Montreal in October 2009, where the Liraglutide Effect and Action on Diabetes (LEAD) studies were presented and discussed, and there were also presentations and posters at the main WDC.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In line with the NICE guideline on type 2 diabetes (CG 87) the ERG started by considering use of liraglutide as third drug, and then as second.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to section 3 of the full ERG report for details of the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The CORE Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The industry submission uses the well-developed CORE (Center for Outcomes Research) model which has been used for many studies in the past. A description of the model and its validation has been attached as Appendix 4 of the ERG report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). It does not meet the criteria for acceptability by NICE on a number of grounds, such as software used and transparency. However diabetes is a very complex disease, and it would have been wasteful for the manufacturer to have commissioned a new model in one of diabetes. NICE therefore, with the ERG agreement, allowed the use of this non-standard software. In brief, the ERG considers the CORE model to be satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See Appendix 6, &quot;Additional Sensitivity Analyses Undertaken by the ERG,&quot; in the ERG report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Section 4 of the ERG report for more information on economic evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Technology appraisal recommendations are based on a review of clinical and economic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology Appraisal Process &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) invites 'consultee' and 'commentator' organisations to take part in the appraisal process. Consultee organisations include national groups representing patients and carers, the bodies representing health professionals, and the manufacturers of the technology under review. Consultees are invited to submit evidence during the appraisal and to comment on the appraisal documents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Commentator organisations include manufacturers of the products with which the technology is being compared, the National Health Service (NHS) Quality Improvement Scotland and research groups working in the area. They can comment on the evidence and other documents but are not asked to submit evidence themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE then commissions an independent academic centre to review published evidence on the technology and prepare an 'assessment report'. Consultees and commentators are invited to comment on the report. The assessment report and the comments on it are then drawn together in a document called the evaluation report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An independent Appraisal Committee then considers the evaluation report. It holds a meeting where it hears direct, spoken evidence from nominated clinical experts, patients and carers. The Committee uses all the evidence to make its first recommendations, in a document called the 'appraisal consultation document' (ACD). NICE sends all the consultees and commentators a copy of this document and posts it on the NICE website. Further comments are invited from everyone taking part.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the Committee meets again it considers any comments submitted on the ACD; then it prepares its final recommendations in a document called the 'final appraisal determination' (FAD). This is submitted to NICE for approval.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consultees have a chance to appeal against the final recommendations in the FAD. If there are no appeals, the final recommendations become the basis of the guidance that NICE issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Is on the Appraisal Committee?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE technology appraisal recommendations are prepared by an independent committee. This includes health professionals working in the NHS and people who are familiar with the issues affecting patients and carers. Although the Appraisal Committee seeks the views of organisations representing health professionals, patients, carers, manufacturers and government, its advice is independent of any vested interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer submitted a &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; economic model (based on the Center for Outcomes Research [CORE] model). The CORE diabetes model was used to predict the cost effectiveness of liraglutide in all of the comparisons presented in the manufacturer's submission. The base-case assumptions used in the model incorporated a time horizon of 40 years. Treatment duration was set to 5 years (after which patients were assumed to have their treatment switched to a basal insulin regimen) in an attempt to replicate clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer's submission presented the results as pairwise comparisons based on individual clinical trials against the comparator used in the relevant trial. The results from the manufacturer's submission were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The comparison of liraglutide 1.8 mg with exenatide 10 &amp;micro;g (both drugs in combination with metformin and a sulphonylurea, based on the LEAD-6 trial) showed the incremental quality-adjusted life year (QALY) gain was 0.163 with an incremental cost of &amp;pound;1638, resulting in an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) of &amp;pound;10,054 per QALY gained for liraglutide. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The comparison of liraglutide 1.8 mg with insulin glargine (both in combination with metformin and a sulphonylurea, based on the LEAD-5 trial) showed the incremental QALY gain was 0.241 with an incremental cost of &amp;pound;3638, resulting in an ICER of &amp;pound;15,130 per QALY gained for liraglutide. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The comparison of liraglutide 1.2 mg and liraglutide 1.8 mg with sitagliptin 100 mg (all in combination with metformin, based on the 1860 trial) resulted in ICERs of &amp;pound;9851 (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.187 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;1842) and &amp;pound;10,465 per QALY gained (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.308 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;3224) for liraglutide 1.2 mg and 1.8 mg respectively. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The comparison of liraglutide 1.2 mg and liraglutide 1.8 mg with rosiglitazone (all in combination with a sulphonylurea, based on the LEAD-1 trial) resulted in ICERs of &amp;pound;6226 (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.331 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;2064) and &amp;pound;9376 per QALY gained (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.398 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;3730) for liraglutide 1.2 mg and 1.8 mg respectively. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The comparison of liraglutide 1.2 mg and liraglutide 1.8 mg with glimepiride (all in combination with metformin, based on the LEAD-2 trial) resulted in ICERs of &amp;pound;13,257 (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.238 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;3157) and &amp;pound;19,837 per QALY gained (with an incremental QALY gain of 0.245 and incremental cost of &amp;pound;4858) for liraglutide 1.2 mg and 1.8 mg respectively. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appraisal Committee's Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Most Likely Cost-Effectiveness Estimate (Given as an ICER)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There were many ICERs presented for different comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For liraglutide versus exenatide (triple therapy), the Committee accepted the ICER of &amp;pound;10,100 per QALY gained (although the Committee noted that this ICER related to liraglutide 1.8 mg).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Committee did not consider the ICERs presented for other oral therapies in both dual and triple therapy regimens to be robust enough to allow them to recommend liraglutide as a cost-effective alternative.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Committee noted the lack of clinical trial evidence showing a significant benefit from increasing the liraglutide dose from 1.2 mg to 1.8 mg, the widely varying ICERs and the uncertainty in the economic analysis. The Committee concluded that liraglutide 1.8 mg would not be a cost-effective use of National Health Service (NHS) resources, and therefore was not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to Sections 3 and 4 of the original guideline document for details of the economic analyses provided by the manufacturer, the ERG comments, and the Appraisal Committee considerations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultee organisations from the following groups were invited to comment on the draft scope, Assessment Report and the Appraisal Consultation Document (ACD) and were provided with the opportunity to appeal against the Final Appraisal Determination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Manufacturer/sponsors &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Professional/specialist and patient/carer groups &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Commentator organisations (without the right of appeal) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, individuals selected from clinical expert and patient advocate nominations from the professional/specialist and patient/carer groups were also invited to comment on the ACD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liraglutide 1.2 mg daily in triple therapy regimens (in combination with metformin and a sulphonylurea, or metformin and a thiazolidinedione) is recommended as an option for the treatment of people with type 2 diabetes, only if used as described for exenatide in the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) clinical guideline 87, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/CG87&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Type 2 diabetes: the management of type 2 diabetes&lt;/a&gt;; that is, when control of blood glucose remains or becomes inadequate (glycated haemoglobin [HbA1c] &amp;ge;7.5%, or other higher level agreed with the individual), and the person has:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A body mass index (BMI) &amp;ge;35 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in those of European descent (with appropriate adjustment for other ethnic groups) and specific psychological or medical problems associated with high body weight, &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A BMI &amp;lt;35 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and therapy with insulin would have significant occupational implications or weight loss would benefit other significant obesity-related comorbidities. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment with liraglutide 1.2 mg daily in a triple therapy regimen should only be continued as described for exenatide in the NICE clinical guideline 87, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/CG87&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Type 2 diabetes: the management of type 2 diabetes&lt;/a&gt;; that is, if a beneficial metabolic response has been shown (defined as a reduction of at least 1 percentage point in HbA1c and a weight loss of at least 3% of initial body weight at 6 months).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Liraglutide 1.2 mg daily in dual therapy regimens (in combination with metformin or a sulphonylurea) is recommended as an option for the treatment of people with type 2 diabetes, only if:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The person is intolerant of either metformin &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; a sulphonylurea, or treatment with metformin &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; a sulphonylurea is contraindicated, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The person is intolerant of thiazolidinediones &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors, or treatment with thiazolidinediones &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; DPP-4 inhibitors is contraindicated. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treatment with liraglutide 1.2 mg daily in a dual therapy regimen should only be continued if a beneficial metabolic response has been shown (defined as a reduction of at least 1 percentage point in HbA1c at 6 months).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Liraglutide 1.8 mg daily is not recommended for the treatment of people with type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People with type 2 diabetes currently receiving liraglutide who do not meet the criteria specified above or who are receiving liraglutide 1.8 mg should have the option to continue their current treatment until they and their clinicians consider it appropriate to stop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Appraisal Committee considered clinical and cost-effectiveness evidence submitted by the manufacturer of liraglutide, and reviews of this submission by the Evidence Review Group and the Decision Support Unit. The evidence for clinical effectiveness comes from six randomised controlled trials. A &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; economic model (based on the CORE model) submitted by the manufacturer was used for cost-effectiveness evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most frequently reported adverse effects of liraglutide are gastrointestinal, including nausea, diarrhoea, vomiting, constipation, abdominal pain, and dyspepsia. These gastrointestinal adverse effects may occur more frequently at the start of treatment with liraglutide, and usually diminish within a few days or weeks on continued treatment. Hypoglycaemia may also be common, and is more common when liraglutide is used in combination with a sulphonylurea. Major hypoglycaemia has primarily been observed when combined with a sulphonylurea.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For full details of side effects and contraindications, see the summary of product characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. However, the guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way which would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State and the Welsh Assembly Minister for Health and Social Services have issued directions to the National Health Service (NHS) on implementing National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) technology appraisal guidance. When a NICE technology appraisal recommends use of a drug or treatment, or other technology, the NHS must usually provide funding and resources for it within 3 months of the guidance being published. If the Department of Health issues a variation to the 3-month funding direction, details will be available on the NICE website. When there is no NICE technology appraisal guidance on a drug, treatment or other technology, decisions on funding should be made locally.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NICE has developed tools to help organisations put this guidance into practice (listed below). These are available on the NICE Web site (&lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203&lt;/a&gt;; see also the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Costing template and report to estimate the national and local savings and costs associated with implementation. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Audit support for monitoring local practice. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010 Oct. 46 p.&amp;nbsp;(Technology appraisal guidance; no. 203).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2010 Oct" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appraisal Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Dr Jane Adam (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Department of Diagnostic Radiology, St George's Hospital; Professor A E Ades, Professor of Public Health Science, Department of Community Based Medicine, University of Bristol; Mrs Elizabeth Brain, Lay member; Professor Karl Claxton, Professor of Health Economics, University of York; Dr Fiona Duncan, Clinical Nurse Specialist, Anaesthetic Department, Blackpool Victoria Hospital, Blackpool; Mr Christopher Earl, Surgical Care Practitioner, Renal Transplant Unit, Manchester Royal Infirmary; Dr Paul Ewings, Statistician, Taunton &amp;amp; Somerset NHS Trust, Taunton; Mr John Goulston, Chief Executive, Barking, Havering and Redbridge Hospitals NHS Trust; Mr Adrian Griffin, VP Strategic Affairs, LifeScan, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson; Dr Terry John, General Practitioner, The Firs, London; Dr Alec Miners, Lecturer in Health Economics, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine; Dr Ann Richardson, Lay member; Mr David Thomson, Lay member; Mr William Turner, Consultant Urologist, Addenbrooke's Hospital; Dr Luke Twelves, General Practitioner, Ramsey Health Centre, Cambridgeshire; Mr Mike Spencer, General Manager, Cardiff and Vale University Health Board &amp;ndash; Facilities and Clinical Support Services; Dr David Newsham, Lecturer (Orthoptics), University of Liverpool; Mrs Angela Schofield, Chairman, Bournemouth and Poole Teaching PCT; Professor Iain Squire, Consultant Physician, University Hospitals of Leicester; Dr Peter Heywood, Consultant Neurologist, Frenchay Hospital; Dr Ian Lewin, Consultant Endocrinologist, North Devon District Hospital; Dr Louise Longworth, Reader in Health Economics, HERG, Brunel University; Dr Anthony S Wierzbicki, Consultant in Metabolic Medicine/Chemical Pathology, Guy's and St Thomas' Hospitals, NHS Trust; Professor Jonathan Grigg, Professor of Paediatric Respiratory and Environmental Medicine, Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University London; Dr John Watkins, Clinical Senior Lecturer/Consultant in Public Health Medicine, Cardiff University and National Public Health Service Wales; Dr Nick Murray, Senior Lecturer and Consultant in Medical Oncology, University of Southampton; Dr Olivia Wu, Reader in Health Economics, University of Glasgow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Committee members are asked to declare any interests in the technology to be appraised. If it is considered there is a conflict of interest, the member is excluded from participating further in that appraisal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) format from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Quick reference guide. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010, 2 p. (Technology appraisal 203). Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203/QuickRefGuide/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Costing template. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010, various pages. (Technology appraisal 203). Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203/CostingTemplate/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Audit support. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010, 7 p. (Technology appraisal 203). Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203/AuditSupport/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Evidence review: liraglutide for the treatment of type 2 diabetes. Aberdeen Health Technology Assessment Group; 2010, 118 p. (Technology appraisal 203). Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=47393&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Evidence review group addendum. 2010, 1 p. Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=47509&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;NICE pathways. Diabetes. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011, various pages. Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pathways.nice.org.uk/pathways/diabetes&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Liraglutide for type 2 diabetes. Understanding NICE guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2010, 4 p. (Technology appraisal 203). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203/PublicInfo/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/TA203/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Welsh&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on June 23, 2011. This summary was updated by ECRI Institute on April 4, 2014 following the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory on Rosiglitazone-containing Diabetes Medicines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their Technology Appraisal guidance with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects the original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE technology appraisal guidance is prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
