<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Use of imaging in cerebrovascular disease.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Irimia P, Asenbaum S, Brainin M, Chabriat H, Martinez-Vila E, Niederkorn K, Schellinger PD, Seitz RJ, Masdeu JC. Use of imaging in cerebrovascular disease. In: Gilhus N, Barnes MP, Brainin M, editor(s). European handbook of neurological management. 2nd ed. Vol. 1. Oxford (UK): Wiley-Blackwell; 2011. p. 19-34. [207 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Masdeu JC, Irimia P, Asenbaum S, Bogousslavsky J, Brainin M, Chabriat H, Herholz K, Markus HS, Martinez-Vila E, Niederkorn K, Schellinger PD, Seitz RJ, EFNS. EFNS guideline on neuroimaging in acute stroke. Report of an EFNS task force. Eur J Neurol 2006 Dec;13(12):1271-83. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Cerebral embolism with cerebral infarction  (434.11); Unspecified cerebrovascular disease  (437.9)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Acute Disease ; Angiography ; Angiography, Digital Subtraction ; Cerebrovascular Disorders ; Diagnostic Imaging ; Magnetic Resonance Angiography ; Magnetic Resonance Imaging ; Phlebography ; Positron-Emission Tomography ; Stroke ; Tomography Scanners, X-Ray Computed ; Tomography, Emission-Computed, Single-Photon ; Tomography, X-Ray Computed ; Ultrasonography ; Ultrasonography, Doppler, Transcranial "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: angiogram ; Cerebrovascular accident ; Cerebrovascular Disorders ; Computed Tomography Scanning Systems ; Diagnostic Imaging ; Magnetic Resonance Angiography ; Magnetic Resonance Imaging ; Positron-Emission Tomography ; Tomography, Emission-Computed, Single-Photon ; Ultrasonography ; Venography - procedure ; X-Ray Computed Tomography "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: angiography ; computed tomography ; diagnostic imaging ; magnetic resonance imaging ; tomography, emission computed, single photon ; ultrasonography "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Acute disease  (2704003); Angiography  (77343006); Cerebral venography  (241222008); Cerebrovascular accident  (230690007); Cerebrovascular disease  (62914000); Computed tomography venography  (431676002); Computerized axial tomography  (77477000); CT angiography  (418272005); CT venography of cerebral vein  (432841000); CT venography of intracranial vein  (432842007); Digital subtraction angiography  (312246005); Imaging  (363679005); Magnetic resonance imaging  (113091000); Magnetic resonance imaging  (312250003); Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of vessels  (241663008); Magnetic resonance imaging unit  (90003000); Positron emission tomography  (363678002); Positron emission tomography  (82918005); Positron emission tomography unit  (39821008); Positron emission tomography unit  (462323006); Single photon emission computerized tomography  (105371005); Single photon emission computerized tomography  (260222006); Transcranial doppler ultrasonography  (431648005); Ultrasonography  (16310003); Ultrasonography  (278292003); Ultrasonography  (359659005); Venography  (4970003)"/><FieldValue Value="SPN: SYSTEM, IMAGING, PULSED DOPPLER, ULTRASONIC ; SYSTEM, NUCLEAR MAGNETIC RESONANCE IMAGING ; SYSTEM, TOMOGRAPHY, COMPUTED, EMISSION ; SYSTEM, X-RAY, TOMOGRAPHY, COMPUTED "/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Scanning Systems, Computed Tomography  (13-469); Scanning Systems, Gamma Camera, Single Photon Emission Tomography  (18-444); Scanning Systems, Magnetic Resonance Imaging  (16-260); Scanning Systems, Positron Emission Tomography  (16-375); Scanning Systems, Ultrasonic  (14-278); Scanning Systems, Ultrasonic, Vascular  (15-957)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute stroke (cerebrovascular disease)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Technology Assessment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Emergency Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Neurology" /><FieldValue Value="Nuclear Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Radiology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Health Care Providers" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To actualize the European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) Guideline on the use of neuroimaging for the management of acute stroke published in 2006 &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To provide updated and evidence-based recommendations regarding the use of diagnostic neuroimaging techniques, including cerebrovascular ultrasonography (US), in patients with stroke and thus guide neurologists, other healthcare professionals and healthcare providers in clinical decision making and in the elaboration of clinical protocols &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with acute stroke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol start=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Computed tomography (CT), perfusion CT (PCT)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), diffusion-weighted (DWI) and perfusion-weighted (PWI) MRI&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Magnetic resonance angiography (MRA)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Positron emission tomography (PET) (considered but not recommended)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Ultrasonography (US)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;CT angiography (CTA)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Digital subtraction angiography (DSA)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Transcranial Doppler (TCD)&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;CT venography&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sensitivity, specificity, and usefulness of diagnostic tests&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cochrane Library was consulted and no studies were found regarding the use of neuroimaging techniques in stroke. A comprehensive literature review using the Medline database has been conducted by searching for the period 1965&amp;ndash;2009. Relevant literature in English including existing guidelines, meta-analyses, systematic reviews, randomized controlled trials, and observational studies has been critically assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Classification Scheme for a Diagnostic Measure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class I&lt;/strong&gt;: A prospective study in a broad spectrum of persons with the suspected condition, using a 'gold standard' for case definition, where the test is applied in a blinded evaluation, and enabling the assessment of appropriate tests of diagnostic accuracy&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class II&lt;/strong&gt;: A prospective study of a narrow spectrum of persons with the suspected condition, or a well-designed retrospective study of a broad spectrum of persons with an established condition (by 'gold standard') compared to a broad spectrum of controls, where test is applied in a blinded evaluation, and enabling the assessment of appropriate tests of diagnostic accuracy&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class III&lt;/strong&gt;: Evidence provided by a retrospective study where either persons with the established condition or controls are of a narrow spectrum, and where test is applied in a blinded evaluation&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class IV&lt;/strong&gt;: Any design where test is not applied in blinded evaluation OR evidence provided by expert opinion alone or in descriptive case series (without controls)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selected articles have been rated based on the quality of study design, according to European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) criteria (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The author panel critically assessed the topic through analysis of the medical literature. Clinical practice recommendations have been developed and stratified to reflect the quality and the content of the evidence according to European Federation of Neurological Societies criteria (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). A draft guideline with specific recommendations was circulated to all panel members. Each panellist studied and commented in writing on this draft, which was revised to progressively accommodate the panel consensus. After the approval of the panellists, two independent experts gave their opinion on the final version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating of Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level A rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least one convincing class I study or at least two consistent, convincing class II studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level B rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as probably useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least one convincing class II study or overwhelming class III evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level C rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as possibly useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least two convincing class III studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Clinical Practice Point&lt;/strong&gt; Where there was lack of evidence but consensus was clear the task force members have stated their opinion as Good Clinical Practice Points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines were validated according to the European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) criteria (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The levels of evidence (Class I-IV) supporting the recommendations and ratings of recommendations (A-C, Good Clinical Practice Point [GCPP]) are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imaging of the Brain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Either non-contrast computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) should be used for the definition of stroke type and treatment of stroke (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The presence of early CT infarct signs cannot be construed as an absolute contraindication to thrombolysis in the first 3 h after stroke (&lt;strong&gt;Class IV, GCPP&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MRI has a higher sensitivity than conventional CT for the documentation of infarction within the first hours of stroke onset, lesions in the posterior fossa, identification of small lesions, and documentation of vessel occlusion and brain oedema (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;In conjunction with MRI and magnetic resonance angiography (MRA), perfusion and diffusion MR are very helpful for the evaluation of patients with acute ischaemic stroke (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) is helpful to predict the malignant course of brain swelling with large hemispheric infarctions (&lt;strong&gt;Class III, Level C&lt;/strong&gt;). SPECT is also helpful in the evaluation of cerebral perfusion in non-acute cerebrovascular disease, for instance in the days after a subarachnoid haemorrhage (SAH) (&lt;strong&gt;Class III, Level C&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detection of Hemorrhagic Stroke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MRI can detect acute and chronic intracerebral haemorrhage (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Although the detection of SAH is possible with MRI, currently CT scan is the diagnostic procedure of choice (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). In case of doubt or negative CT scan, lumbar puncture and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) analysis is recommended (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imaging of Extracranial Vessels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Although MRA has slightly higher sensitivity and specificity than ultrasonography (US) to determine carotid stenosis and occlusion, the usefulness of either procedure may be determined by other factors, such as availability (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;CT angiography (CTA) has a sensitivity and specificity similar to MR for carotid occlusion and similar to US for the detection of severe stenosis (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Digital subtraction angiography (DSA) is generally recommended for grading carotid stenosis prior to endarterectomy (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;), but when there is concordance of non-invasive methods cerebral arteriography may not be necessary (&lt;strong&gt;Class IV, GCPP&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imaging of Intracranial Vessels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Transcranial Doppler (TCD) is very useful for assessing stroke risk of children aged 2 to 16 years with sickle cell disease (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;), detection and monitoring of vasospasm after SAH (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;), diagnosis of intracranial steno-occlusive disease (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;), diagnosis of right-to-left shunts (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;), and for monitoring arterial recanalization after thrombolysis of acute middle cerebral artery (MCA) occlusions (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;TCD can detect cerebral emboli and impaired cerebral haemodynamics. The presence of embolic signals with carotid stenosis predicts early recurrent stroke risk (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). The detection of impaired cerebral haemodynamics in carotid occlusion may identify a group at high risk of recurrent stroke (&lt;strong&gt;Class III, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MRA and CTA are very useful for the diagnosis of intracranial stenosis and cerebral aneurysms &amp;gt;5 mm (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). MRA and CTA are the recommended techniques for screening cerebral aneurysms in individuals with a history of aneurysms or SAH in a first-degree relative (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;DSA is the recommended technique for the diagnosis of cerebral aneurysm as the cause of SAH (&lt;strong&gt;Class I, Level A&lt;/strong&gt;). CTA can be used as a reliable alternative to DSA in patients with SAH, particularly in cases in which the risk of delaying surgery for a catheter study is not justified (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MRI with MRA is recommended for the diagnosis and follow-up of cerebral venous thrombosis (&lt;strong&gt;Class II, Level B&lt;/strong&gt;). Alternatively, CT venography is accurate and can be used for the same purpose (&lt;strong&gt;Class III, Level C&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Classification Scheme for a Diagnostic Measure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class I&lt;/strong&gt;: A prospective study in a broad spectrum of persons with the suspected condition, using a 'gold standard' for case definition, where the test is applied in a blinded evaluation, and enabling the assessment of appropriate tests of diagnostic accuracy&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class II&lt;/strong&gt;: A prospective study of a narrow spectrum of persons with the suspected condition, or a well-designed retrospective study of a broad spectrum of persons with an established condition (by 'gold standard') compared to a broad spectrum of controls, where test is applied in a blinded evaluation, and enabling the assessment of appropriate tests of diagnostic accuracy&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class III&lt;/strong&gt;: Evidence provided by a retrospective study where either persons with the established condition or controls are of a narrow spectrum, and where test is applied in a blinded evaluation&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class IV&lt;/strong&gt;: Any design where test is not applied in blinded evaluation OR evidence provided by expert opinion alone or in descriptive case series (without controls)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating of Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level A rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least one convincing class I study or at least two consistent, convincing class II studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level B rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as probably useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least one convincing class II study or overwhelming class III evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level C rating&lt;/strong&gt; (established as possibly useful/predictive or not useful/predictive) requires at least two convincing class III studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Clinical Practice Point&lt;/strong&gt; Where there was lack of evidence but consensus was clear the task force members have stated their opinion as Good Clinical Practice Points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is identified and graded for&amp;nbsp;each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate use of neuroimaging for the diagnosis of acute stroke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angiography carries the risk of stroke and death, and many centres are not using digital subtraction angiography (DSA) prior to carotid endarterectomy, particularly when non-invasive methods are concordant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Pregnancy, diabetes, renal failure, and allergy to contrast material are relative contraindications to performing a perfusion brain computed tomography (CT).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Limitations and contraindications for the use of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) are: claustrophobia, agitation, morbid obesity, the presence of intracranial ferromagnetic elements, an aneurysm recently clipped or coiled, otic or cochlear implants, some old prosthetic heart valves, pacemakers, and some, not all, neurostimulators.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guideline provides the view of an expert task force appointed by the Scientific Committee of the European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS). It represents a peer-reviewed statement of minimum desirable standards for the guidance of practice based on the best available evidence. It is not intended to have legally binding implications in individual cases. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The original guideline is intended to provide updated and evidence-based recommendations regarding the use of diagnostic neuroimaging techniques, including cerebrovascular ultrasonography (US), in patients with stroke and thus guide neurologists, other healthcare professionals and healthcare providers in clinical decision making and in the elaboration of clinical protocols. It is not intended to have legally binding implications in individual situations. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The European Federation of Neurological Societies has a mailing list and all guideline papers go to national societies, national ministries of health, World Health Organisation, European Union, and a number of other destinations. Corporate support is recruited to buy large numbers of reprints of the guideline papers and permission is given to sponsoring companies to distribute the guideline papers from their commercial channels, provided there is no advertising attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Timeliness " /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Irimia P, Asenbaum S, Brainin M, Chabriat H, Martinez-Vila E, Niederkorn K, Schellinger PD, Seitz RJ, Masdeu JC. Use of imaging in cerebrovascular disease. In: Gilhus N, Barnes MP, Brainin M, editor(s). European handbook of neurological management. 2nd ed. Vol. 1. Oxford (UK): Wiley-Blackwell; 2011. p. 19-34. [207 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2006 Dec (revised 2011)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="European Academy of Neurology - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies Task Force on Use of Imaging in Cerebrovascular Disease&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Task Force Members&lt;/em&gt;: P. Irimia, University of Navarra, Pamplona, Spain; S. Asenbaum, Medical University of Vienna, Austria; M. Brainin, Donauklinikum and Donau-Universit&amp;auml;t, Maria Gugging, Austria; H. Chabriat, Lariboisiere Hospital, University of Paris, France; E. Mart&amp;iacute;nez-Vila, University of Navarra, Pamplona, Spain; K. Niederkorn, Karl Franzens University, Graz, Austria; P. D. Schellinger, University Clinic at Erlangen, Germany; R. J. Seitz, University Hospital D&amp;uuml;sseldorf, Germany; J. C. Masdeu, University of Navarra, Pamplona, Spain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;J. Masdeu received an honorarium as Editor-in-Chief of the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroimaging&lt;/em&gt;. With regard to this manuscript there is no conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;P. D. Schellinger has received travel stipends, advisory board and speaker's honoraria from Boehringer Ingelheim, the manufacturers of Alteplase.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rest of authors have reported no conflicts of interest relevant to this manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Masdeu JC, Irimia P, Asenbaum S, Bogousslavsky J, Brainin M, Chabriat H, Herholz K, Markus HS, Martinez-Vila E, Niederkorn K, Schellinger PD, Seitz RJ, EFNS. EFNS guideline on neuroimaging in acute stroke. Report of an EFNS task force. Eur J Neurol 2006 Dec;13(12):1271-83. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.efns.org/fileadmin/user_upload/guidline_papers/EFNS_guideline_2011_Use_of_imaging_in_CVD.pdf&quot; title=&quot;EFNS Web site&quot;&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Brainin M, Barnes M, Baron JC, Gilhus NE, Hughes R, Selmaj K, Waldemar G; Guideline Standards Subcommittee of the EFNS Scientific Committee. Guidance for the preparation of neurological management guidelines by EFNS scientific task forces &amp;ndash; revised recommendations 2004. Eur J Neurol. 2004 Sep;11(9):577-81. Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.efns.org/fileadmin/user_upload/guidline_papers/EFNS_guideline_2004_neurological_management_guidelines.pdf&quot; title=&quot;European Federation of Neurological Societies Web site&quot;&gt;European Federation of Neurological Societies Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI on April 13, 2007. The information was verified by the guideline developer on May 15, 2007. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on February 20, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the Blackwell-Synergy copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
