<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Management of hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Management of hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. 19 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical guideline; no. 130).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Diabetes with other coma, type I [juvenile type], not stated as uncontrolled  (250.31); Diabetes with other coma, type II or unspecified type, not stated as uncontrolled  (250.30); Intermediate coronary syndrome  (411.1); Other abnormal glucose  (790.29)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Acute Coronary Syndrome ; Angina, Unstable ; Blood Glucose Self-Monitoring ; Diabetes Mellitus ; Hyperglycemia ; Insulin ; Risk Assessment "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Angina, Unstable ; Blood glucose measurement ; Diabetes Mellitus ; Fasting blood glucose measurement ; Hemoglobin A1c measurement ; Hyperglycemia ; Insulin ; Patient Monitoring ; Risk Assessment "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: insulin "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Acute coronary syndrome  (394659003); Blood glucose monitoring equipment  (354068006); Diabetes mellitus  (73211009); Fasting blood glucose measurement  (271062006); Glucose measurement, blood  (33747003); Hemoglobin A1c measurement  (43396009); Hyperglycemia  (237598005); Hyperglycemia  (80394007); Impending infarction  (25106000); Insulin  (39487003); Insulin  (412222002); Insulin  (67866001); Monitoring of patient  (182777000); Risk assessment  (225338004); Self-monitoring of blood glucose  (308113006)"/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Monitors, Personal, Glucose  (20-184)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperglycaemia associated with acute coronary syndrome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Counseling" /><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Cardiology" /><FieldValue Value="Endocrinology" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Hospitals" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To offer best practice advice on the management of hyperglycaemia in all adults admitted to hospital for an acute coronary syndrome regardless of whether or not they have a diagnosis of diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To address the role of intensive insulin therapy in managing hyperglycaemia within the first 48 hours in people admitted to hospital for acute coronary syndromes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adults with acute coronary syndromes and hyperglycaemia with a diagnosis of diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adults with acute coronary syndromes and hyperglycaemia without a diagnosis of diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Subgroups who are at higher risk of mortality and poorer outcomes associated with acute coronary syndrome, as appropriate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Groups not covered:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul class=&quot;contentListFont&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adults with hyperglycaemia who do not have acute coronary syndromes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adults with acute coronary syndromes who do not have hyperglycaemia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Managing hyperglycaemia in inpatients within 48 hours of acute coronary syndrome (ACS)&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Dose-adjusted insulin infusion to keep blood glucose levels below 11.0 mmol/litre while avoiding hypoglycaemia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Regular monitoring of blood glucose levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Identifying patients with hyperglycaemia after ACS who are at high risk of developing diabetes&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Tests for glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt; levels) before discharge &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Fasting blood glucose levels no earlier than 4 days after the onset of ACS &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Advice and ongoing monitoring for patients with hyperglycaemia after ACS and without known diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;All-cause mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cardiovascular mortality &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cardiovascular events such as non-fatal reinfarction, heart failure and stroke &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Measures and control of blood glucose levels &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health related quality of life &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse events associated with metabolic management of hyperglycaemia, including hypoglycaemia and hypokalaemia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Resource use and costs, such as length of hospital stay &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Unpublished Data" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre (NCGC) at the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The evidence reviews used to develop the guideline recommendations were underpinned by systematic literature searches, following the methods described in 'The guidelines manual' (2009) (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). The aim of the systematic searches was to comprehensively identify the published evidence to answer the review questions developed by the Guideline Development Group and Short Clinical Guidelines Technical Team.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The search strategies for the review questions were developed by the Information Services Team with advice from the Short Clinical Guidelines Technical Team. Structured questions were developed using the PICO (population, intervention, comparison, outcome) model and translated into search strategies using subject heading and free text terms. The strategies were run across a number of databases with no date restrictions imposed on the searches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The NHS Economic Evaluation Database (NHS EED) and the Health Economic Evaluations Database (HEED) were searched for economic evaluations. Search filters for economic evaluations and quality of life studies were used on bibliographic databases. There were no date restrictions imposed on the searches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guideline Development Group members were also asked to alert the Short Clinical Guidelines Technical Team to any additional evidence, published, unpublished or in press, that met the inclusion criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The searches were undertaken between June 2010 and September 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scoping Searches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scoping searches were undertaken in May 2010 using the websites and databases listed in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=56801&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Appendix D&lt;/a&gt; of the full version of the original guideline document; browsing or simple search strategies were employed. The search results were used to provide information for scope development and project planning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review Questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What is the optimal inpatient metabolic management of patients presenting with hyperglycaemia and acute coronary syndrome (ACS) who have diagnosed diabetes mellitus and hyperglycaemia? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What is the optimal inpatient metabolic management of patients presenting with hyperglycaemia and ACS without a diagnosis of diabetes mellitus? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What risk factors are associated with diabetes in patients with hyperglycaemia and ACS who have not previously been diagnosed? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;What information should patients with peri-ACS and hyperglycaemia (who are at high risk of developing diabetes) be provided while waiting for a referral for diagnostic investigations for diabetes? &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Searches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following sources were searched:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Clinical Trials.gov &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Current Controlled Trials &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews &amp;ndash; CDSR (Wiley) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials &amp;ndash; CENTRAL (Wiley) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Database of Abstracts of Reviews of Effects &amp;ndash; DARE (CRD) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health Technology Assessment Database &amp;ndash; HTA (CRD) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;CINAHL (EBSCO) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;EMBASE (Ovid) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MEDLINE (Ovid) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;MEDLINE In-Process (Ovid) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;National Research Register Archive &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;UK Clinical Research Network &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Refer to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/index.jsp?action=download&amp;amp;o=56801&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Appendix D&lt;/a&gt; of the full version of the original guideline for details of the search strategies used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Review Question 1: 3 studies were included in the quantitative summary &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Review Question 2: 3 studies were included in the quantitative summary &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Review Question 3:&amp;nbsp;4 studies were included in the quantitative summary &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Review Question 4: 0 studies were included in the quantitative summary &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See the &quot;Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence&quot; field for the review questions.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre (NCGC) at the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Review &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/Guidance/Appendices/E/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Appendix E&lt;/a&gt; of the full version of the original guideline document for detailed evidence tables and forest plots for the review questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre (NCGC) at the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forming and Running the Short Clinical Guideline Development Group (GDG)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each short clinical guideline is developed by a unique GDG consisting of 10&amp;ndash;12 members, supported by the Short Clinical Guidelines Team. Each GDG has a Chair, healthcare professional members and a minimum of two patient and carer members. Co-opted expert advisers are recruited, as appropriate. A Clinical Adviser, who has specific content expertise and additional responsibilities, may also be appointed depending on the topic. Recruitment of the GDG Chair and members is carried out in accordance with NICE's policy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The GDG makes its decisions using the best available evidence presented to it at GDG meetings by the Short Clinical Guidelines Team. The use of formal consensus methods within the GDG will be considered on a case-by-case basis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing Review Questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A short clinical guideline has a narrow scope and covers only part of a care pathway. It addresses a maximum of three subject areas covering clinical management. This will result in a small number of key clinical issues. These are broken down into a defined number of review questions &amp;mdash; usually one or two per clinical management area. The exact number will be dictated by the size of the short clinical guideline remit and the amount of development time available.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating Guideline Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explicit methods of linking the evidence to recommendations are used for short clinical guidelines if the topic is suitable. This involves using the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation (GRADE) approach.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Research recommendations are formulated for short clinical guidelines. Their number is dependent on the size of the short clinical guideline remit and the amount of development time available.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing the Guideline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are usually three versions of short clinical guidelines:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The full guideline &amp;ndash; all the recommendations, details of how they were developed and summaries of the evidence they are based on. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The quick reference guide &amp;ndash; a summary of the recommendations for healthcare professionals. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;'Understanding NICE guidance' &amp;ndash; a summary for patients and carers. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The full guideline is written by the Short Clinical Guidelines Team, following the principles in chapters 9 and 10 of 'The guidelines manual' (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults with Acute Coronary Syndromes and Hyperglycaemia with a Diagnosis of Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After careful consideration and discussion, the Guideline Development Group (GDG) concluded that the evidence did not show intensive insulin therapy to be significantly associated with a reduction in outcomes such as inpatient mortality, long-term mortality and reinfarction. The GDG also took into account the increased risk of harm (hypoglycaemia) associated with intensive insulin therapy. The GDG recommended that intensive insulin therapy should not be routinely used to manage hyperglycaemia in people with pre-existing diabetes who present with a primary diagnosis of acute coronary syndromes (ACS).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It would be inappropriate to conduct an economic analysis because there is a lack of evidence to support the use of intensive insulin therapy, and it is clearly more expensive than standard care. The incremental cost of using intensive insulin therapy to manage hyperglycaemia in patients with ACS and pre-existing diabetes was estimated to be &amp;pound;103. Table 3 in the full version of the original guideline document provides an estimate of resource use and unit costs for managing hyperglycaemia using intensive insulin therapy compared with standard care.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intensive insulin therapy is defined as an intravenous infusion of insulin and glucose with or without potassium. Based on GDG consensus, standard care (current practice) for people with pre-existing diabetes would include pre-filled insulin, diabetes specialist nurse time and an intravenous cannula. Those on intensive insulin therapy will require 12&amp;ndash;24 glucose strip tests daily compared with 8&amp;ndash;12 a day for standard care. Thus up to 24 additional test strips would be needed over 48 hours for intensive insulin therapy. See table 3 in the full version of the original guideline document for further details.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults with Acute Coronary Syndromes and Hyperglycaemia without a Previous Diagnosis of Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The review of clinical evidence did not show intensive insulin therapy to be more effective than standard care in managing hyperglycaemia in patients presenting with ACS without pre-existing diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It would be inappropriate to conduct an economic analysis because there is a lack of evidence to support the use of intensive insulin therapy and it is clearly more expensive than standard care. The incremental cost of using intensive insulin therapy to manage hyperglycaemia in patients with ACS without pre-existing diabetes was estimated to be &amp;pound;85.15 per hospital stay (see Table 6 in the full version of the original guideline document).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The GDG recommended that intensive insulin therapy should not be routinely used to manage hyperglycaemia in patients presenting with ACS without pre-existing diabetes. Table 6 in the full version of the original guideline provides an estimate of resource use and unit cost of managing hyperglycaemia using intensive insulin therapy compared with standard care.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intensive insulin therapy is defined as an intravenous infusion of insulin and glucose with or without potassium. Based on GDG consensus, people without pre-existing diabetes would neither receive insulin nor need care from a diabetes nurse as part of standard care. Those on intensive insulin therapy would need 12&amp;ndash;24 glucose strip tests daily compared with 2&amp;ndash;4 a day for standard care. Thus up to 40 additional test strips would be needed over 48 hours for those on intensive insulin therapy. See Table 3 in the full version of the original guideline for further details.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identifying People who are at High Risk of Developing Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No health economic analysis was conducted for this question.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patient Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No health economic analysis was conducted for this question.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guideline was validated through two consultations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The first draft of the guideline (the full guideline, National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence [NICE] guideline, and Quick Reference Guide) were consulted with Stakeholders and comments were considered by the Guideline Development Group (GDG) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The final consultation draft of the Full guideline, the NICE guideline and the Information for the Public were submitted to stakeholders for final comments. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The final draft was submitted to the Guideline Review Panel for review prior to publication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: This guideline was developed by the National Clinical Guideline Centre (NCGC) at the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). See the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field for the full version of this guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Hyperglycaemia in Inpatients within 48 Hours of Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recommendations in this section partially update recommendation 1.12.3.6 in the NICE guideline &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/CG15&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Type 1 diabetes&lt;/a&gt;. Recommendation 1.12.3.6 is updated for the treatment of patients with threatened or actual myocardial infarction, but not stroke.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manage hyperglycaemia in patients admitted to hospital for an ACS by keeping blood glucose levels below 11.0 mmol/litre while avoiding hypoglycaemia. In the first instance, consider a dose-adjusted insulin infusion with regular monitoring of blood glucose levels.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Do not routinely offer intensive insulin therapy (an intravenous infusion of insulin and glucose with or without potassium) to manage hyperglycaemia (blood glucose above 11.0 mmol/litre) in patients admitted to hospital for an ACS unless clinically indicated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identifying Patients with Hyperglycaemia after ACS Who Are at High Risk of Developing Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Offer all patients with hyperglycaemia after ACS and without known diabetes tests for:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt;) levels before discharge and &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Fasting blood glucose levels no earlier than 4 days after the onset of ACS &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These tests should not delay discharge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Do not routinely offer oral glucose tolerance tests to patients with hyperglycaemia after ACS and without known diabetes if HbA&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt; and fasting blood glucose levels are within the normal range.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice and Ongoing Monitoring for Patients with Hyperglycaemia after ACS and without Known Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Offer patients with hyperglycaemia after ACS and without known diabetes lifestyle advice on the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Healthy eating in line with the NICE guidelines &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG48&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Post myocardial infarction: secondary prevention in primary and secondary care for patients following a myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/CG43&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Obesity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Physical exercise in line with the NICE guidelines &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG48&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Post myocardial infarction: secondary prevention in primary and secondary care for patients following a myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/PH2&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Four commonly used methods to increase physical activity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Weight management in line with the NICE guidelines &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG48&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Post myocardial infarction: secondary prevention in primary and secondary care for patients following a myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/CG43&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Obesity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Smoking cessation in line with the NGC summaries of the NICE guidelines &lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=16393&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #7891&quot;&gt;Unstable angina and NSTEMI: the early management of unstable angina and non-ST-segment-elevation myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/PH10&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Smoking cessation services in primary care, pharmacies, local authorities and workplaces, particularly for manual working groups, pregnant women and hard to reach communities&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG48&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Post myocardial infarction: secondary prevention in primary and secondary care for patients following a myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt;, and the NICE guideline &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/PH1&quot; title=&quot;title=&quot;&gt;Brief interventions and referral for smoking cessation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Alcohol consumption in line with the NGC summary of the NICE guideline &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG48&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;Post myocardial infarction: secondary prevention in primary and secondary care for patients following a myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Advise patients without known diabetes that if they have had hyperglycaemia after an ACS they:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Are at increased risk of developing type 2 diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Should consult their general practitioner (GP) if they experience the following symptoms:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Frequent urination &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Excessive thirst &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Weight loss &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Fatigue &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Should be offered tests for diabetes at least annually &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inform GPs that they should offer at least annual monitoring of HbA&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt; and fasting blood glucose levels to people without known diabetes who have had hyperglycaemia after an ACS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes care pathway is provided in the full version of the original guideline document (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appropriate management of patients admitted to hospital for acute coronary syndrome who have hyperglycaemia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse events associated with metabolic management of hyperglycaemia, including hypoglycaemia and hypokalaemia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Risk of adverse events associated with hyperglycaemia that is not managed appropriately &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;This guidance represents the view of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), which was arrived at after careful consideration of the evidence available. Healthcare professionals are expected to take it fully into account when exercising their clinical judgement. However, the guidance does not override the individual responsibility of healthcare professionals to make decisions appropriate to the circumstances of the individual patient, in consultation with the patient and/or guardian or carer, and informed by the summary of product characteristics of any drugs they are considering. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Implementation of this guidance is the responsibility of local commissioners and/or providers. Commissioners and providers are reminded that it is their responsibility to implement the guidance, in their local context, in light of their duties to avoid unlawful discrimination and to have regard to promoting equality of opportunity. Nothing in this guidance should be interpreted in a way that would be inconsistent with compliance with those duties. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guideline does not make recommendations on drug dosage; prescribers should refer to the &quot;British national formulary&quot; for this information. The guideline also assumes that prescribers will use a drug's summary of product characteristics to inform decisions made with individual patients. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has developed tools to help organisations implement this guidance (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130&lt;/a&gt;; see also the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Chart Documentation/Checklists/Forms" /><FieldValue Value="Clinical Algorithm" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Slide Presentation" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /><FieldValue Value="Timeliness " /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Management of hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. 19 p.&amp;nbsp;(Clinical guideline; no. 130).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2011 Oct" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) - National Government Agency [Non-U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guideline Development Group&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guideline Development Group&lt;/em&gt;: Damien Longson (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Consultant Liaison Psychiatrist, Manchester Mental Health and Social Care Trust; Sunil Angris, GP, Staffordshire; Bernard Clarke, Consultant Cardiologist, Central Manchester University Hospital NHS Foundation Trust; Simon Corbett, Consultant Cardiologist, Wessex Cardiothoracic Centre, Southampton University Hospitals NHS Trust; Phillip Dyer, Consultant Physician, Heart of England NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham; Ian Lewin, Consultant Physician, North Devon Healthcare NHS Foundation Trust; Lesley Mills, Senior Diabetes Nurse Specialist, Warrington and Halton Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust; David Peachey, Patient member; Steven Williams, Consultant Pharmacist in Medicine and Medication Safety, University Hospital of South Manchester NHS Foundation Trust&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See Appendix A in the full version of the original guideline for a list of all declarations made by members of the Guideline Development Group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Management of hyperglycaemia in people with acute coronary syndromes. Full guideline. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. 64 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/Guidance&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. NICE pathway. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. Various pages. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pathways.nice.org.uk/pathways/hyperglycaemia-in-acute-coronary-syndromes&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Baseline assessment. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011. Various p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/BaselineAssessment/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Clinical audit tool. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011. 9 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/ClinicalAudit/doc/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Costing statement. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. 7 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/CostingStatement/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Electronic audit tool. Implementing NICE guidance. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011. Various p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/ElectronicAudit/xls/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Hyperglycaemia in acute coronary syndromes. Implementing NICE guidance. Slide set. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2011 Oct. 21 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/SlideSet&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guidelines manual 2009. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE); 2009 Jan. Electronic copies: Available in PDF from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk/aboutnice/howwework/developingniceclinicalguidelines/clinicalguidelinedevelopmentmethods/GuidelinesManual2009.jsp&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;High blood glucose after an acute coronary syndrome: understanding NICE guidance. Information for people who use NHS services. London (UK): National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence; 2011 Oct. 8 p. (Clinical guideline; no. 130). Electronic copies: Available in English from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/PublicInfo/pdf/English&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. Also available in Welsh from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://guidance.nice.org.uk/CG130/PublicInfo/doc/Welsh&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;NICE Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on April 25, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) has granted the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) permission to include summaries of their clinical guidelines with the intention of disseminating and facilitating the implementation of that guidance. NICE has not yet verified this content to confirm that it accurately reflects that original NICE guidance and therefore no guarantees are given by NICE in this regard. All NICE clinical guidelines are prepared in relation to the National Health Service in England and Wales. NICE has not been involved in the development or adaptation of NICE guidance for use in any other country. The full versions of all NICE guidance can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nice.org.uk&quot; title=&quot;NICE Web site&quot;&gt;www.nice.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
