<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Marcus CL, Brooks LJ, Draper KA, Gozal D, Halbower AC, Jones J, Schechter MS, Sheldon SH, Spruyt K, Ward SD, Lehmann C, Shiffman RN. Diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics. 2012 Sep;130(3):576-84. [17 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22926173&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Academy of Pediatrics, Subcommittee on Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome, Section on Pediatric Pulmonology. Clinical practice guideline: diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics 2002 Apr;109(4):704-12.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All policy statements from the American Academy of Pediatrics automatically expire 5 years after publication unless reaffirmed, revised, or retired at or before that time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="HCPCS: Continuous positive airway pressure (cpap) device "/><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: General physical examination  (89.7); Loss of weight  (783.21); Obesity, unspecified  (278.00); Obstructive sleep apnea (adult)(pediatric)  (327.23); Polysomnogram  (89.17); Tonsillectomy with adenoidectomy  (28.3)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Adrenal Cortex Hormones ; Continuous Positive Airway Pressure ; Medical History Taking ; Monitoring, Ambulatory ; Obesity ; Oximetry ; Oxygen Inhalation Therapy ; Physical Examination ; Polysomnography ; Referral and Consultation ; Sleep Apnea, Obstructive ; Snoring ; Video Recording ; Weight Loss "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Adrenal Cortex Hormones ; Body Weight decreased ; Continuous Positive Airway Pressure ; Obesity ; Oximeter ; Oxygen saturation measurement ; Oxygen Therapy Care ; Patient Monitoring ; physical examination ; Polysomnography ; Sleep Apnea, Obstructive ; Snoring "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: obesity "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Continuing positive airway pressure unit  (37874008); Continuous positive airway pressure ventilation treatment  (47545007); Corticoid preparation  (21568003); Corticoid preparation  (79440004); Monitoring of patient  (182777000); Obesity  (414915002); Obesity  (414916001); Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome  (78275009); Oxygen saturation measurement  (104847001); Oxygen saturation measurement  (264598005); Oxygen therapy  (57485005); Physical assessment  (302199004); Physical assessment  (5880005); Physical assessment  (81375008); Polysomnography  (164773008); Polysomnography  (60554003); Snoring  (162375000); Snoring  (72863001); Tonsillectomy and adenoidectomy  (28913000); Topical form corticosteroids  (331645009); Weight decreased  (161832001); Weight decreased  (262285001); Weight decreased  (89362005)"/><FieldValue Value="SPN: DEVICE, SLEEP ASSESSMENT ; OXIMETER "/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Analyzers, Physiologic, Somnography  (17-456); Oximeters  (12-853); Positive Airway Pressure Units, Continuous  (11-001)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Diagnosis" /><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Risk Assessment" /><FieldValue Value="Screening" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Otolaryngology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Pulmonary Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Sleep Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Allied Health Personnel" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To increase the recognition of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) by primary care clinicians to minimize delay in diagnosis and to avoid serious sequelae of OSAS &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To evaluate diagnostic techniques &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To describe treatment options &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To provide guidelines for follow-up &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To discuss areas requiring further research &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otherwise healthy children older than 1 year of age with uncomplicated obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS), such as OSAS associated with adenotonsillar hypertrophy and/or obesity, who are being treated in the primary care setting&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The guidelines specifically &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;exclude&lt;/span&gt; the following: infants younger than 1 year, patients with central apnea or hypoventilation syndromes, patients with OSAS associated with other medical disorders, including but not limited to Down syndrome, craniofacial anomalies, neuromuscular disease (including cerebral palsy), chronic lung disease, sickle cell disease, metabolic disease, or laryngomalacia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnosis/Evaluation/Screening&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Screening for snoring and other signs and symptoms of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;History and physical examinations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Polysomnography &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Alternative diagnostic tests&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Nocturnal video recording &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Nocturnal oximetry &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Daytime nap polysomnography &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Ambulatory polysomnography &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management/Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot; start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Referral to a sleep specialist or otolaryngologist for a more extensive evaluation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adenotonsillectomy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Monitoring high-risk patients undergoing adenotonsillectomy as inpatients postoperatively &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Postoperative evaluation and monitoring, including objective testing of high-risk patients &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) with monitoring for adherence &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Weight loss (in addition to other therapies if patient is overweight or obese) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Topical intranasal corticosteroids &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) and primary snoring &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Sequelae of OSAS (e.g., cardiovascular, growth, and neurobehavioral abnormalities, and possibly inflammation) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reliability of diagnostic screening tests (positive/negative predictive values, sensitivity, specificity of tests) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Symptoms of OSAS (e.g., snoring, apnea hypopnea index) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse effects or complications of treatment of OSAS &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A literature search was performed that included English-language articles, children and adolescents aged 1 through 17.9 years, and publication between 1999 and 2008. Animal studies, abstracts, letters, case reports, and reviews were excluded. The Medical Subject Heading terms that were used in all fields were snoring, apnea, sleep-disordered breathing (SDB), sleep-related breathing disorders, upper airway resistance, polysomnography (PSG), sleep study, adenoidectomy, tonsillectomy, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), obesity, adiposity, hypopnea, hypoventilation, cognition, behavior, and neuropsychology. Search engines used were PubMed, Scopus, Ovid, PsycINFO, EBSCO (including Health Source [Nursing], Child Development and Adolescent Studies), and CINAHL. Articles covering special populations (e.g., infants aged &amp;lt;1 year, those with craniofacial anomalies or syndromes) were excluded during the title and abstract reviews.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Titles and available abstracts of articles found by the literature search were reviewed by the committee members in several rounds. In the first round, duplicates and erroneous hits from the literature search were excluded. In the second round, titles were reviewed for relevancy by 2 committee members. Articles with relevant titles were then reviewed by 2 reviewers each, on the basis of the abstract. Because of the large number of remaining articles, text-mining (Statistica, StatSoft version 9; StatSoft, Inc, Tulsa, OK) was performed on the method section of the articles to reduce the large amount of articles for the final step of quality assessment. Text-mining is the combined, automated process of analyzing unstructured, natural language text to discover information and knowledge that are typically difficult to retrieve.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, text-mining revealed that few articles reported research methods, such as the study design (e.g., clinical case series, retrospective, observational, clinical experiment), blinding of the assessment, and recruitment and/or scoring, that could have been applied for further selection. A manual screening of the questionable articles after text-mining resulted in a pool of 605 articles. The committee decided on a final round of title selection; that is, each member was assigned a random batch of articles and selected titles based on relevance with respect to the guideline categories. These remaining articles were each reviewed and graded by a committee member. Because of the large volume of articles requiring detailed evaluation, some committee members recruited trainees and colleagues to assist them in the performance of these reviews, under their supervision. A literature search of more recent articles (2008&amp;ndash;2011) was performed by individual committee members, per guideline category, and discussed during the committee meeting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The automated Medical Subject Heading search resulted in 3166 hits. The final round of title selection resulted in 397 articles for detailed review. An additional 47 articles were found to not meet criteria during the detailed review. Thus, a total of 350 articles were included. On the basis of the final 350 articles, one-third were epidemiologic studies, 26% were diagnostic studies, and 23% were treatment studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Grading System for the Assessment of Clinical Utility of Diagnostic Tests*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Evidence Grading System for the Assessment of Clinical Utility of Diagnostic Tests&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;I&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Evidence provided by a prospective study in a broad spectrum of persons who have the suspected condition, by using a reference (gold) standard for case definition, in which the test is applied in a blinded fashion, and enabling the assessment of appropriate test of diagnostic accuracy. All persons undergoing the diagnostic test have the presence or absence of the disease determined. Level I studies are judged to have a low risk of bias.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;II&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Evidence provided by a prospective study of a narrow spectrum of persons who have the suspected condition, or a well-designed retrospective study of a broad spectrum of persons who have an established condition (by gold standard) compared with a broad spectrum of controls, in which the test is applied in a blinded evaluation, and enabling the assessment of appropriate tests of diagnostic accuracy. Level II studies are judged to have a moderate risk of bias.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;III&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Evidence provided by a retrospective study in which either persons who have the established condition or controls are of a narrow spectrum, and in which the reference standard, if not objective, is applied by someone other than the person who performed (interpreted) the test. Level III studies are judged to have a moderate to high risk of bias.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;IV&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Any study design where the test is not applied in an independent evaluation or evidence is provided by expert opinion alone or in descriptive case series without controls. There is no blinding or there may be inadequate blinding. The spectrum of persons tested may be broad or narrow. Level IV studies are judged to have a very high risk of bias.&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Adapted from the American Academy of Neurology.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Quality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Evidence Quality&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Evidence Quality&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Preponderance of Benefit or Harm&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Balance of Benefit and Harm&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A. Well-designed randomized controlled trials (RCTs) or diagnostic studies on&amp;nbsp;relevant population&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;B. RCTs or diagnostic studies with minor limitations; overwhelmingly consistent evidence from observational studies&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation/Strong Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;C. Observational studies (case-control and cohort design)&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;D. Expert opinion, case reports, reasoning from first principles&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;X. Exceptional situations where validating studies cannot be performed and there is a clear preponderance of benefit or harm&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation/Strong Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Integrating evidence quality appraisal with an assessment of the anticipated balance between benefits and harms if a policy is carried out leads to designation of a policy as a strong recommendation, recommendation, option, or no recommendation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The previous literature review form was modified to include the evidence grading system developed by the American Academy of Neurology for the assessment of clinical utility of diagnostic tests (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; field). A specific customized software (OSA Taskforce; copyright Francesco Rundo and Karen Spruyt) was developed for the literature review form to standardize this part of the process. Of note, the quality assessment levels were comparable to the grading levels applied previously. The quality assessment applied involved 4 tiers of evidence, with level I studies being judged to have a low risk of bias and level IV studies judged to have a very high level of bias. A weaker level of evidence indicates the need to integrate greater clinical judgment when applying results to clinical decision-making. The committee's quality assessment of data took into account not only the levels of evidence in relevant articles but also the number of articles identified, the magnitude and direction of various findings, and whether articles demonstrated convergent or divergent conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The evidence-based approach to guideline development requires that the evidence in support of each key action statement be identified, appraised, and summarized and that an explicit link between evidence and recommendations be defined. Evidence-based recommendations reflect the quality of evidence and the balance of benefit and harm that is anticipated when the recommendation is followed. The American Academy of Pediatrics' policy statement &quot;Classifying Recommendations for Clinical Practice Guidelines&quot; was followed in designating levels of recommendations (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; and &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) selected a subcommittee composed of pediatricians and other experts in the fields of sleep medicine, pulmonology, and otolaryngology, as well as experts from epidemiology and pediatric practice to develop an evidence base of literature on this topic. The committee included liaison members from the AAP Section on Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, American Thoracic Society, American Academy of Sleep Medicine, American College of Chest Physicians, and the National Sleep Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For initial guideline drafts, committee members were assigned sections of the report that were not directly in their area of research, and the evidence, search results, and conclusions thereof were discussed by all committee members at a face-to-face meeting. Subsequent drafts of the guidelines and technical report were reviewed by all committee members.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definitions and Recommendation Implications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Definitions and Recommendation Implications&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Statement&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Implication&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A strong recommendation in favor or a particular action is made when the anticipated benefits of the recommended intervention clearly exceed the harms (as a strong recommendation against an action is made when the anticipated harms clearly exceed the benefits) and the quality of the supporting evidence is excellent. In some clearly identified circumstances, strong recommendations may be made when high-quality evidence is impossible to obtain and the anticipated benefits strongly outweigh the harms. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should follow a strong recommendation unless a clear and compelling rationale for an alternative approach is present. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A recommendation in favor of a particular action is made when the anticipated benefits exceed the harms but the quality of evidence is not as strong. Again, in some clearly identified circumstances, recommendations may be made when high-quality evidence is impossible to obtain but the anticipated benefits outweigh the harms. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;It would be prudent for clinicians to follow a recommendation, but they should remain alert to new information and sensitive to patient preferences. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Options define courses that may be taken when either the quality of evidence is suspect or carefully performed studies have shown little clear advantage to one approach over another. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should consider the option in their decision-making, and patient preferences may have a substantial role. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No recommendation &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No recommendation indicates that there is a lack of pertinent published evidence and that the anticipated balance of benefits and harms is presently unclear. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should be alert to new published evidence that clarifies the balance of benefit versus harm. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Not stated" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definitions for the quality of the evidence (&lt;strong&gt;A-D, X&lt;/strong&gt;) and the strength of the recommendation (&lt;strong&gt;strong recommendation, recommendation, option&lt;/strong&gt;) are provided at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 1: Screening for Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome (OSAS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of routine health maintenance visits, clinicians should inquire whether the child or adolescent snores. If the answer is affirmative or if a child or adolescent presents with signs or symptoms of OSAS (see Table below), clinicians should perform a more focused evaluation. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Early identification of OSAS is desirable, because it is a high-prevalence condition, and identification and treatment can result in alleviation of current symptoms, improved quality of life, prevention of sequelae, education of parents, and decreased health care utilization. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Provider time, patient and parent time. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Panelists believe that identification of a serious medical condition outweighs the time expenditure necessary for screening. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;br /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Symptoms and Signs of OSAS&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Table. Symptoms and Signs of OSAS&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History&lt;/strong&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Frequent snoring (&amp;ge;3 nights/week) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Labored breathing during sleep &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Gasps/snorting noises/observed episodes of apnea &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Sleep enuresis (especially secondary enuresis)&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Sleeping in a seated position or with the neck hyperextended &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Cyanosis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Headaches on awakening &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Daytime sleepiness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Learning problems &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Examination&lt;/strong&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Underweight or overweight &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Tonsillar hypertrophy &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Adenoidal facies &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Micrognathia/retrognathia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;High-arched palate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Failure to thrive &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;                &lt;li&gt;Hypertension &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;Enuresis after at least 6 months of continence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 2A: Polysomnography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a child or adolescent snores on a regular basis and has any of the complaints or findings shown in the table above, clinicians should either (1) obtain a polysomnogram &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality A, Key Action strength: Recommendation)&lt;/strong&gt; OR (2) refer the patient to a sleep specialist or otolaryngologist for a more extensive evaluation &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence quality D, Key Action strength: Option)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade A for polysomnography; Grade D for specialist referral, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits: Establish diagnosis and determine severity of OSAS. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time, anxiety/discomfort. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Panelists weighed the value of establishing a diagnosis as more important than the minor potential harms listed. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Small because of preponderance of evidence that polysomnography is the most accurate way to make a diagnosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: See Key Action Statement 2B regarding lack of availability. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 2A: Referral&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits: Subspecialist may be better able to establish diagnosis and determine severity of OSAS. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time, anxiety/discomfort. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Panelists weighed the value of establishing a diagnosis as more important than the minor potential harms listed. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Large. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 2B: Alternative Testing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If polysomnography is not available, then clinicians may order alternative diagnostic tests, such as nocturnal video recording, nocturnal oximetry, daytime nap polysomnography, or ambulatory polysomnography. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade C, Recommendation Strength: Option.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 2B&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Varying positive and negative predictive values for establishing diagnosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: False-negative and false-positive results may underestimate or overestimate severity, expense, time, anxiety/discomfort. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Equilibrium of benefits and harms. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Opinion of the panel that some objective testing is better than none. Pragmatic decision based on current shortage of pediatric polysomnography facilities (this may change over time). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Small, if choices are limited by availability; families may choose to travel to centers where more extensive facilities are available. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 3: Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a child is determined to have OSAS, has a clinical examination consistent with adenotonsillar hypertrophy, and does not have a contraindication to surgery (see the &quot;Contraindications&quot; field), the clinician should recommend adenotonsillectomy as the first line of treatment. If the child has OSAS but does not have adenotonsillar hypertrophy, other treatment should be considered (see Key Action Statement 6). Clinical judgment is required to determine the benefits of adenotonsillectomy compared with other treatments in obese children with varying degrees of adenotonsillar hypertrophy. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Improve OSAS and accompanying symptoms and sequelae. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Pain, anxiety, dehydration, anesthetic complications, hemorrhage, infection, postoperative respiratory difficulties, velopharyngeal incompetence, nasopharyngeal stenosis, death. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: The panel sees the benefits of treating OSAS as more beneficial than the low risk of serious consequences. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Low; continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is an option but involves prolonged, long-term treatment as compared with a single, relatively low-risk surgical procedure. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: See the &quot;Contraindications&quot; field. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 4: High-Risk Patients Undergoing Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should monitor high-risk patients (see the &quot;Potential Harms&quot; field) undergoing adenotonsillectomy as inpatients postoperatively. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Effectively manage severe respiratory compromise and avoid death. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time, anxiety. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: The panel believes that early recognition of any serious adverse events is critically important. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Minimal; this is an important safety issue. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 5A: Reevaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should clinically reassess all patients with OSAS for persisting signs and symptoms after therapy to determine whether further treatment is required. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 5A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Determine effects of treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Data show that a significant proportion of children continue to have abnormalities postoperatively; therefore, the panel determined that the benefits of follow-up outweigh the minor inconveniences. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Minimal; follow-up is good clinical practice. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 5B: Reevaluation of High-Risk Patients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should reevaluate high-risk patients for persistent OSAS after adenotonsillectomy, including those who had a significantly abnormal baseline polysomnogram, have sequelae of OSAS, are obese, or remain symptomatic after treatment, with an objective test (see Key Action Statement 2) or refer such patients to a sleep specialist. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 5B&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Determine effects of treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time, anxiety/discomfort. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Given the panel's concerns about the consequences of OSAS and the frequency of postoperative persistence in high-risk groups, the panel believes that the follow-up costs are outweighed by benefits of recognition of persistent OSAS. A minority of panelists believed that all children with OSAS should have follow-up polysomnography because of the high prevalence of persistent postoperative abnormalities on polysomnography, but most panelists believed that persistent polysomnographic abnormalities in uncomplicated children with mild OSAS were usually mild in patients who were asymptomatic after surgery. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Minimal. Further evaluation is needed to determine the need for further treatment. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 6: CPAP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should refer patients for CPAP management if symptoms/signs (see table above) or objective evidence of OSAS persists after adenotonsillectomy or if adenotonsillectomy is not performed. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality:&lt;strong&gt; B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Improve OSAS and accompanying symptoms and sequelae. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Expense, time, anxiety; parental sleep disruption; nasal and skin adverse effects; possible midface remodeling; extremely rare serious pressure-related complications, such as pneumothorax; poor adherence. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: Panelists believe that CPAP is the most effective treatment of OSAS that persists postoperatively and that the benefits of treatment outweigh the adverse effects. Other treatments (e.g., rapid maxillary expansion) may be effective in specially selected patients. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Other treatments may be effective in specially selected patients.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: Rare patients at increased risk of severe pressure complications. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Policy level: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 7: Weight Loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians should recommend weight loss in addition to other therapy if a child/adolescent with OSAS is overweight or obese. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade C, Recommendation Strength: Recommendation.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Improve OSAS and accompanying symptoms and sequelae; non&amp;ndash;OSAS-related benefits of weight loss. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Hard to achieve and maintain weight loss. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: The panel agreed that weight loss is beneficial for both OSAS and other health issues, but clinical experience suggests that weight loss is difficult to achieve and maintain, and even effective weight loss regimens take time; therefore, additional treatment is required in the interim. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Strong role for patient and family preference regarding nutrition and exercise. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Action Statement 8: Intranasal Corticosteroids&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians may prescribe topical intranasal corticosteroids for children with mild OSAS in whom adenotonsillectomy is contraindicated or for children with mild postoperative OSAS. &lt;strong&gt;(Evidence Quality: Grade B, Recommendation Strength: Option.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidence Profile Key Action Statement 8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Aggregate evidence quality: &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefit: Improves mild OSAS and accompanying symptoms and sequelae. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Harm: Some subjects may not have an adequate response. It is not known whether therapeutic effect persists long-term; therefore, long-term observation is required. Low risk of steroid-related adverse effects. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Benefits-harms assessment: Preponderance of benefit over harm. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Value judgments: The panel agreed that intranasal steroids provide a less invasive treatment than surgery or CPAP and, therefore, may be preferred in some cases despite lower efficacy and lack of data on long-term efficacy. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Role of patient preferences: Moderate role for patient and family preference if OSAS is mild. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Exclusions: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intentional vagueness: None. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Strength: &lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Quality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Evidence Quality&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Evidence Quality&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Preponderance of Benefit or Harm&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Balance of Benefit and Harm&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A. Well-designed randomized controlled trials (RCTs) or diagnostic studies on&amp;nbsp;relevant population&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;B. RCTs or diagnostic studies with minor limitations; overwhelmingly consistent evidence from observational studies&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation/Strong Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;C. Observational studies (case-control and cohort design)&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;D. Expert opinion, case reports, reasoning from first principles&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;X. Exceptional situations where validating studies cannot be performed and there is a clear preponderance of benefit or harm&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation/Strong Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Integrating evidence quality appraisal with an assessment of the anticipated balance between benefits and harms if a policy is carried out leads to designation of a policy as a strong recommendation, recommendation, option, or no recommendation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definitions and Recommendation Implications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; summary=&quot;Table: Definitions and Recommendation Implications&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Statement&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Implication&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A strong recommendation in favor or a particular action is made when the anticipated benefits of the recommended intervention clearly exceed the harms (as a strong recommendation against an action is made when the anticipated harms clearly exceed the benefits) and the quality of the supporting evidence is excellent. In some clearly identified circumstances, strong recommendations may be made when high-quality evidence is impossible to obtain and the anticipated benefits strongly outweigh the harms. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should follow a strong recommendation unless a clear and compelling rationale for an alternative approach is present. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A recommendation in favor of a particular action is made when the anticipated benefits exceed the harms but the quality of evidence is not as strong. Again, in some clearly identified circumstances, recommendations may be made when high-quality evidence is impossible to obtain but the anticipated benefits outweigh the harms. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;It would be prudent for clinicians to follow a recommendation, but they should remain alert to new information and sensitive to patient preferences. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Options define courses that may be taken when either the quality of evidence is suspect or carefully performed studies have shown little clear advantage to one approach over another. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should consider the option in their decision-making, and patient preferences may have a substantial role. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No recommendation &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;No recommendation indicates that there is a lack of pertinent published evidence and that the anticipated balance of benefits and harms is presently unclear. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Clinicians should be alert to new published evidence that clarifies the balance of benefit versus harm. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is specifically stated for each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurate diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) and improvement in accompanying symptoms and sequelae of OSAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For benefits of specific interventions considered in the guideline, see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Harms include expense, time, anxiety, parental sleep disruption, nasal and skin adverse effects, possible midface remodeling, and extremely rare serious pressure-related complications, such as pneumothorax; poor adherence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although serious complications (including death) may occur in obese children, the rate of these complications is low, and the risks of complications need to be weighed against the consequences of untreated obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS). Other treatment options, such as anti-inflammatory medications, weight loss, or tracheostomy, are less effective, are difficult to achieve, or have higher morbidity, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Risks of Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Minor&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Pain &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Dehydration attributable to postoperative nausea/vomiting and poor oral intake &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Major&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Anesthetic complications &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Acute upper airway obstruction during induction or emergence from anesthesia &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Postoperative respiratory compromise &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Hemorrhage &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Velopharyngeal incompetence &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Nasopharyngeal stenosis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Death &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-Risk Patients Undergoing Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Patients with OSAS may develop respiratory complications, such as worsening of OSAS or pulmonary edema, in the immediate postoperative period. Death attributable to respiratory complications in the immediate postoperative period has been reported in patients with severe OSAS. High-risk patients should undergo surgery in a center capable of treating complex pediatric patients. They should be hospitalized overnight for close monitoring postoperatively. Children with an acute respiratory infection on the day of surgery, as documented by fever, cough, and/or wheezing, are at increased risk of postoperative complications and, therefore, should be rescheduled or monitored closely postoperatively. Clinicians should decide on an individual basis whether these patients should be rescheduled, taking into consideration the severity of OSAS in the particular patient and keeping in mind that many children with adenotonsillar hypertrophy have chronic rhinorrhea and nasal congestion, even in the absence of viral infections.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Risk Factors for Postoperative Respiratory Complications in Children with OSAS Undergoing Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Younger than 3 y of age &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Severe OSAS on polysomnography&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cardiac complications of OSAS &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Failure to thrive &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Obesity &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Craniofacial anomalies&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Neuromuscular disorders&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Current respiratory infection &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;It is difficult to provide exact polysomnographic criteria for severity, because these criteria will vary depending on the age of the child; additional comorbidities, such as obesity, asthma, or cardiac complications of OSAS; and other polysomnographic criteria that have not been evaluated in the literature, such as the level of hypercapnia and the frequency of desaturation (as compared with lowest oxygen saturation). Nevertheless, on the basis of published studies, it is recommended that all patients with a lowest oxygen saturation &amp;lt;80% (either on preoperative polysomnography or during observation in the recovery room postoperatively) or an apnea hypopnea index &amp;ge;24/h be observed as inpatients postoperatively as they are at increased risk for postoperative respiratory compromise. Additionally, on the basis of expert consensus, it is recommended that patients with significant hypercapnia on polysomnography (peak PCO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;ge;60 mm Hg) be admitted postoperatively. The committee noted that that most published studies were retrospective and not comprehensive, and therefore these recommendations may change if higher-level studies are published. Clinicians may decide to admit patients with less severe polysomnographic abnormalities based on a constellation of risk factors (age, comorbidities, and additional polysomnographic factors) for a particular individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;Not discussed in these guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intranasal Corticosteroids&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the long-term effect of this treatment is unknown, the clinician should continue to observe the patient for symptoms of recurrence and adverse effects of corticosteroids.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For additional harms of specific interventions considered in the guideline, see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="430" OrdBy="800" Name="Contraindications"><Field FieldID="144" OrdBy="805" ID="431" Name="Contraindications" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contraindications for Adenotonsillectomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Absolute contraindications&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;No adenotonsillar tissue (tissue has been surgically removed) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Relative contraindications&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Very small tonsils/adenoid &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Morbid obesity and small tonsils/adenoid &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Bleeding disorder refractory to treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Submucus cleft palate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Other medical conditions making patient medically unstable for surgery &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations in this report do not indicate an exclusive course of treatment or serve as a standard of medical care. Variations, taking into account individual circumstances, may be appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Living with Illness" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Marcus CL, Brooks LJ, Draper KA, Gozal D, Halbower AC, Jones J, Schechter MS, Sheldon SH, Spruyt K, Ward SD, Lehmann C, Shiffman RN. Diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics. 2012 Sep;130(3):576-84. [17 references] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22926173&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2002 Apr (revised 2012 Sep)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="American Academy of Pediatrics - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The American Academy of Pediatrics has neither solicited nor accepted any commercial involvement in the development of the content of this publication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subcommittee on Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subcommittee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Carole L. Marcus, MBBCh (&lt;em&gt;Chairperson&lt;/em&gt;); Lee Jay Brooks, MD; Kari A. Draper, MD; David Gozal, MD; Ann Carol Halbower, MD; Jacqueline Jones, MD; Michael S. Schechter, MD, MPH; Stephen Howard Sheldon, DO; Karen Spruyt, PhD; Sally Davidson Ward, MD; Christopher Lehmann, MD; Richard N. Shiffman, MD&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staff&lt;/em&gt;: Caryn Davidson, MA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All authors have filed conflict of interest statements with the American Academy of Pediatrics. Any conflicts have been resolved through a process approved by the Board of Directors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Carole L. Marcus, MBBCh, Chairperson (sleep medicine, pediatric pulmonologist; liaison, American Academy of Sleep Medicine; research support from Philips Respironics; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Lee J. Brooks, MD (sleep medicine, pediatric pulmonologist; liaison, American College of Chest Physicians; no conflicts; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Sally Davidson Ward, MD (sleep medicine, pediatric pulmonologist; no conflicts; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Kari A. Draper, MD (general pediatrician; no conflicts) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;David Gozal, MD (sleep medicine, pediatric pulmonologist; research support from AstraZeneca; speaker for Merck Company; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Ann C. Halbower, MD (sleep medicine, pediatric pulmonologist; liaison, American Thoracic Society; research funding from ResMed; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Jacqueline Jones, MD (pediatric otolaryngologist; AAP Section on Otolaryngology&amp;ndash;Head and Neck Surgery; liaison, American Academy of Otolaryngology&amp;ndash;Head and Neck Surgery; no conflicts; affiliated with an academic otolaryngologic practice) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Christopher Lehmann, MD (neonatologist, informatician; no conflicts) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Michael S. Schechter, MD, MPH (pediatric pulmonologist; AAP Section on Pediatric Pulmonology; consultant to Genentech, Inc and Gilead, Inc, not related to obstructive sleep apnea; research support from Mpex Pharmaceuticals, Inc, Vertex Pharmaceuticals Incorporated, PTC Therapeutics, and Bayer Healthcare, not related to obstructive sleep apnea) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Stephen Sheldon, MD (sleep medicine, general pediatrician; liaison, National Sleep Foundation; no conflicts; affiliated with an academic sleep center; published research related to OSAS) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Richard N. Shiffman, MD, MCIS (general pediatrics, informatician; no conflicts) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Karen Spruyt, PhD (clinical psychologist, child neuropsychologist, and biostatistician/epidemiologist; no conflicts; affiliated with an academic sleep center) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Academy of Pediatrics, Subcommittee on Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome, Section on Pediatric Pulmonology. Clinical practice guideline: diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics 2002 Apr;109(4):704-12.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All policy statements from the American Academy of Pediatrics automatically expire 5 years after publication unless reaffirmed, revised, or retired at or before that time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/130/3/576.full&quot; title=&quot;AAP Policy Web site&quot;&gt;American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) Policy Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from American Academy of Pediatrics, 141 Northwest Point Blvd., P.O. Box 927, Elk Grove Village, IL 60009-0927.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Technical Report: diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics 2012 Sep;130(3):e714-e755. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/130/3/e714.full&quot; title=&quot;AAP Policy Web site&quot;&gt;American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) Policy Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Print copies: Available from American Academy of Pediatrics, 141 Northwest Point Blvd., P.O. Box 927, Elk Grove Village, IL 60009-0927.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None available&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI on September 6, 2002. The information was verified by the guideline developer on October 11, 2002. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 5, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions. Please contact the Permissions Editor, American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP), 141 Northwest Point Blvd, Elk Grove Village, IL 60007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
