<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Screening of the neonate/infant with prenatal hydronephrosis. In: Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Screening of the neonate/infant with prenatal hydronephrosis. In: American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2010. p. 1-12. [1 reference]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Urological Association (AUA), Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel. Report on the management of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children. Baltimore (MD): American Urological Association, Inc.; 1997 Apr. 88 p. (Clinical practice guidelines; no. 4/97). [249 references]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Hydronephrosis  (591); Other vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy NOS  (593.73); Urinary tract infection, site not specified  (599.0); Vesicoureteral reflux unspecified or without reflux nephropathy  (593.70); Vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy, bilateral  (593.72); Vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy, unilateral  (593.71)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Anti-Bacterial Agents ; Antibiotic Prophylaxis ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Hydronephrosis ; Neonatal Screening ; Prenatal Diagnosis ; Surgical Procedures, Operative ; Urinary Tract Infections ; Urologic Surgical Procedures ; Vesico-Ureteral Reflux ; Watchful Waiting "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Anti-Bacterial Agents ; Antibiotic Prophylaxis ; Antibiotics ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Operative Surgical Procedures ; Patient observation ; Urinary bladder training ; Urinary tract infection ; Voiding urethrocystography "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: observation ; surgery "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Antibacterial agent  (346325008); Antibacterial agent  (419241000); Antibiotic  (255631004); Antibiotic prophylaxis  (422181004); Hydronephrosis  (43064006); Neonatal screening  (60151004); Operation on bladder  (14861000); Patient status observation  (103705002); Surgical  (257556004); Surgical  (387713003); Surgical  (83578000); Urinary bladder training  (37799002); Urinary tract infectious disease  (68566005); Vesicoureteric reflux  (197811007); Voiding urethrocystography  (54810009)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vesicoureteral reflux &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Prenatal hydronephrosis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Screening" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Urology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide recommendations for the screening of the neonate/infant with prenatal hydronephrosis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthy neonates with unilateral mild (Society for Fetal Urology [SFU] grade 1) to moderate (SFU grades 2&amp;ndash;3) hydronephrosis identified on a screening prenatal ultrasound at 30 weeks gestation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Voiding cystourethrogram &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Observation with prompt treatment of urinary tract infection &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incidence of:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vesicoureteral reflux &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Urinary tract infections &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Renal cortical abnormalities &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. This process is described in an accompanying Technical Report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). In addition, specific methodology for each of the five topics was also provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A wide literature search was performed with the headings of vesicoureteral reflux covering the years 1997 through June 2008. For screening, the search covered as far back as 1992. The panel chairs scrutinized independently the results from this search (1,501 articles) from the abstracts and determined the articles that would follow to the phase of systematic data extraction.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the next phase, panel members independently collected information using customized extraction forms including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Bibliographic information: year of publication and authors. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study characteristics: design, period, location and inclusion/exclusion criteria. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patient population: number of children assessed with VUR with a cystogram (in either screening or management), descriptives of age at diagnosis (mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum), and sex distribution. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;VUR specific: severity scale, laterality, presentation or symptoms (prenatal hydronephrosis [PNH], urinary tract infection [UTI], other), renal damage at diagnosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Management specific: treatment regimen (antibiotic prophylaxis, open surgery, endoscopic surgery), outcomes (reflux resolution, cortical renal abnormalities, UTI incidence). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Renal outcomes: use of scintigraphy vs. intravenous pyelography (IVP, earlier years) for the screening aims, scintigraphy modality used (dimercaptosuccinic acid [DMSA], diethylenetriamine pentaacetic acid [DTPA], or mercaptoacetyltriglycine [MAG3]), explicit definition of renal cortical abnormalities. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also, additional information was collected specific to each index case as follows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 1&lt;/span&gt;: Presence/proportion of duplex cases in the cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 2&lt;/span&gt;: Circumcision status.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 3&lt;/span&gt;: Number of children with bladder/bowel dysfunction (BBD), distribution of BBD symptoms and BBD management (bladder training, anticholinergics, biofeedback).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 4&lt;/span&gt;: Number of and relationship with index cases.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 5&lt;/span&gt;: Prenatal and post-natal anteroposterior renal pelvis diameter (RPD) thresholds as measured by ultrasound (US), time of pre-natal and early post-natal evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of the second phase, each extractor excluded articles based on a set of pre-defined rejection criteria either without extracting the complete article or after the complete extraction. The criteria for rejection without extraction included:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The absence of relevant outcomes or complications data &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cannot interpret the data to fit the extraction form &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Insufficient treatment efficacy follow-up (less than 3 months) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The article did not deal with either management or screening &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In specific cases, the extractor considered that the article had problems but rather than excluding it subjected the article to the review of the entire panel which determined whether the article should finally be rejected or included in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Criteria for Acceptance of Studies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To be accepted, a study should have assessed primarily a cohort of children, clearly stated the number of children undergoing screening for VUR or number of children with VUR undergoing a particular management regimen. For management cases, reflux resolution should have been assessed at least three months after the intervention with a cystogram and renal outcomes assessed by nuclear scintigraphy. Review articles found were scrutinized and scanned in order to determine that all articles complying with selection criteria were included.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A literature search, review of the evidence, and data extraction from the relevant clinical studies and case series were performed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the 43 studies selected for meta-analysis involving at least 6,579 infants with PNH (who were evaluated postnatally), there were 34 studies reporting VUR incidence among 4,756 infants with PNH, 12 studies providing information on renal abnormalities in 530 infants, and eight studies reporting UTI in 616 infants. There was large variability across these studies regarding the definition of PNH, indications and timing of postnatal evaluation; therefore, the percentage of patients undergoing renal ultrasonography, cystography, or other investigations also varied. Articles that included other diagnoses, (such as posterior urethral valves, ureterocele, etc.) that could not be separated were excluded from analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;43 studies were selected for meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. This process is described in an accompanying Technical Report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). In addition, specific methodology for each of the five topics was also provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Conditioning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After extraction and acceptance of the article, the data were conditioned for analysis in two steps. First, it was verified that all the necessary fields were complete and if data were missing it was confirmed that the data did not appear in the articles. The second step consisted in assessing apparently repeated/overlapping articles. The different sets of related studies and the articles selected from each of those sets are indicated in the corresponding chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Studies or arms which included less than 10 patients or renal units for analysis were excluded due to the imprecision of estimates that they would generate. This exclusion was done at the analysis stage by the methodologist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Study Quality Evaluation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines for reporting of meta-analysis of observational studies elaborated by the Meta-analysis of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group indicate the need to assess the quality of the studies included in the literature synthesis. A quality score was developed to assess the quality of the studies extracted and accepted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Twenty items were common to the quality scores across the different index cases (or topics). Four items (1-4) corresponded to study design (basic score). Eleven items were specific to the assessment of reflux (5-15, reflux score), three to the assessment of renal outcomes (16-18, renal score) and two to the assessment of urinary tract infection (UTI) (20-21, UTI score). Additional items were included for specific issues related to each index case (extra score). A total score was built by adding all the individual items. In any of the scores, each characteristic received one quality point when present. In particular situations a half point rather than a point was provided. For example, for management of children with bladder/bowel dysfunction (BBD) the articles described the sample in terms of age and sex; however these two characteristics were not provided for the strata built with BBD status, in this case half points were given to these items in the quality score. The quality score was used in a descriptive manner to determine the possible relation between individual estimates and study quality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A meta-analysis of the existing literature was performed to determine the impact of postnatal management of neonates/infants with prenatal hydronephrosis (PNH) in prevention of UTI, pyelonephritis, and new renal scarring, and to develop recommendations for screening to detect VUR. Outcomes included the incidence of VUR (stratified by sex, laterality, and postnatal diagnosis of reflux), incidence of UTI, and incidence of renal cortical abnormalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The supporting systematic literature review and the drafting of the guideline document were conducted by the Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel (the Panel) created in 2006 by the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA). The Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC) of the AUA selected the Panel Chair and Vice-Chair, who in turn appointed the additional Panel members with specific expertise in this disease. The mission of the Panel was to develop either analysis- or consensus-based recommendations, depending on the type of evidence available and Panel processes, to support optimal clinical practices in the management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) nomenclature, the statements are graded with respect to the degree of flexibility in application. A &quot;standard&quot; is the most rigid treatment policy. A &quot;recommendation&quot; has significantly less rigidity and an &quot;option&quot; the least. These terms are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a standard if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) there is virtual unanimity among panel members about which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a recommendation if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) an appreciable, but not unanimous majority of the panel members agrees on which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is an option if (1) the health outcomes of the interventions are not sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions or (2) preferences are unknown or equivocal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document was submitted to approximately 75 urologists and other health care professionals for peer review. After revision of the document based upon the peer review comments, the guideline was submitted to and approved by the Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC) and the Board of Directors of the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. The other four topics are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=23923&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8002&quot;&gt;Management of vesicoureteral reflux in the child over one year of age&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24027&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8018&quot;&gt;Management of infants less than one year of age with vesicoureteral reflux&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24028&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8019&quot;&gt;Management of children with vesicoureteral reflux and bladder/bowel dysfunction&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24029&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8020&quot;&gt;Screening of siblings and offspring of patients with vesicoureteral reflux&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Definitions of the strength of the recommendations &lt;strong&gt;(standard, recommendation, option)&lt;/strong&gt; are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screening of the Neonate/Infant with Prenatal Hydronephrosis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Voiding cystourethrogram is recommended for children with high-grade (Society of Fetal Urology [SFU] grade 3 and 4) hydronephrosis, hydroureter or an abnormal bladder on ultrasound (late term prenatal or postnatal), or who develop a urinary tract infection on observation. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: An observational approach without screening for vesicoureteral reflux (VUR), with prompt treatment of any urinary tract infection, may be taken for children with prenatally detected hydronephrosis (SFU grade 1 or 2), given the unproven value of identifying and treating VUR. It is also considered an option to perform a voiding cystourethrogram in these patients to screen for VUR. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) nomenclature, the statements are graded with respect to the degree of flexibility in application. A &quot;standard&quot; is the most rigid treatment policy. A &quot;recommendation&quot; has significantly less rigidity and an &quot;option&quot; the least. These terms are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a standard if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) there is virtual unanimity among panel members about which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a recommendation if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) an appreciable, but not unanimous majority of the panel members agrees on which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is an option if (1) the health outcomes of the interventions are not sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions or (2) preferences are unknown or equivocal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is not specifically stated for each recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations contained in the guideline are based on a review of the data and panel consensus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postnatal evaluation of prenatal hydronephrosis (PNH) offers the opportunity to diagnose and manage vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) before secondary damage occurs from urinary tract infection (UTI). Evaluation of affected infants could additionally provide insights into the benefits, if any, of early identification of VUR and institution of continuous antibiotic prophylaxis to prevent UTI, pyelonephritis, and renal scarring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guideline document provides guidance only and does not establish a fixed set of rules or define the legal standard of care. As medical knowledge expands and technology advances, the guidelines may change. Today they represent not an absolute mandate but rather current proposals or recommendations for treatment under the specific conditions described. For all these reasons, the Guidelines do not preempt physician judgment in individual cases. Also, treating physicians must take into account variations in resources, and in patient tolerances, needs and preferences. Conformance with the recommendations reflected in this document cannot guarantee a successful outcome. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guideline document may also include information or recommendations about certain drug uses ('off label') that are not approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), or about medications or substances not subject to the FDA approval process. American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) urges strict compliance with all government regulations and protocols for prescription and use of these substances. The physician is encouraged to carefully follow all available prescribing information about indications, contraindications, precautions and warnings. These guidelines are not intended to provide legal advice about use and misuse of these substances. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Although the development of a clinical guideline is often limited by the availability of quality data, which is notably true with respect to the vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) literature, recommendations can be based on general principles developed from a formal meta-analysis as well as experience and clinical judgment. These guidelines for management of VUR were based upon risk assessment, considering the probability for spontaneous resolution versus perceived risk for recurrent urinary tract infection (UTI) and renal injury. In the absence of definitive evidence, stronger guidelines cannot appropriately be made and the final decisions regarding clinical care reside with the physician and family. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Screening of the neonate/infant with prenatal hydronephrosis. In: American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2010. p. 1-12. [1 reference]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: This guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="1997 Apr (revised 2010)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panel Members&lt;/em&gt;: Craig A. Peters, M.D. (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Steven J. Skoog, M.D. (&lt;em&gt;Vice-Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Billy S. Arant, Jr., M.D.; Hillary L. Copp, M.D.; Jack S. Elder, M.D. (Facilitator); R. Guy Hudson, M.D.; Antoine E. Khoury, M.D.; Armando J. Lorenzo, M.D.; Hans G. Pohl, M.D.; Ellen Shapiro, M.D.; Warren T. Snodgrass, M.D.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consultants&lt;/em&gt;: Mireya Diaz, Ph.D.; Linda Whetter, D.V.M, Ph.D.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All panel members completed Conflict of Interest disclosures. Those marked with (C) indicate that compensation was received; relationships designated by (U) indicate no compensation was received.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientific Study or Trial&lt;/strong&gt;: Jack S. Elder, QMed Scandinavia (U); &lt;strong&gt;Meeting Participant or Lecturer&lt;/strong&gt;: Billy Arant, Novartis (C); &lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt;: Jack S. Elder, FSC Laboratories (U); &lt;strong&gt;Investment Interest&lt;/strong&gt;: Antoine E. Khoury, Covalon (U), Interface Biologics (U)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Urological Association (AUA), Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel. Report on the management of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children. Baltimore (MD): American Urological Association, Inc.; 1997 Apr. 88 p. (Clinical practice guidelines; no. 4/97). [249 references]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/content/guidelines-and-quality-care/clinical-guidelines/main-reports/vur2010/ScreenNeonateinfantWithPrenatalHydronephrosis.pdf&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: American Urological Association Guideline. Summary report. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. 2010. 30 p. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/content/guidelines-and-quality-care/clinical-guidelines/main-reports/vur2010/AuthorsAndSummaryReport.pdf&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Technical Report associated with this guideline is available upon request. Please contact the AUA Guidelines Department at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:guidelines@auanet.org&quot;&gt;guidelines@auanet.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vesicoureteral reflux. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association (AUA) Education and Research, Inc.; 2009 Jul. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urologyhealth.org/urology/index.cfm?article=55&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;AUA Foundation Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Urinary tract infections in children. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association (AUA) Education and Research, Inc.; 2010 Jan. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urologyhealth.org/urology/index.cfm?article=46&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;AUA Foundation Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Voiding cystourethrogram. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association (AUA) Education and Research, Inc.; 2003 Jan. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urologyhealth.org/urology/index.cfm?article=87&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;AUA Foundation Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summary was completed by ECRI on March 26, 1999. The information was verified by the guideline developer as of May 14, 1999. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 23, 2010. The updated information was verified by the guideline developer on February 28, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is copyrighted by the American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse™ (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
