<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Management of vesicoureteral reflux in the child over one year of age. In: Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Management of vesicoureteral reflux in the child over one year of age. In: American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2010. p. 1-28. [16 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Urological Association (AUA), Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel. Report on the management of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children. Baltimore (MD): American Urological Association, Inc; 1997 Apr. 88 p. (Clinical practice guidelines; no. 4/97). [249 references]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Complications affecting other specified body systems, not elsewhere classified, hypertension  (997.91); Other vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy NOS  (593.73); Renal failure, unspecified  (586); Urinary tract infection, site not specified  (599.0); Vesicoureteral reflux unspecified or without reflux nephropathy  (593.70); Vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy, bilateral  (593.72); Vesicoureteral reflux with reflux nephropathy, unilateral  (593.71)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Anti-Bacterial Agents ; Antibiotic Prophylaxis ; Blood Pressure Determination ; Body Height ; Body Weight ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Hypertension ; Microbial Sensitivity Tests ; Patient Education as Topic ; Radionuclide Imaging ; Technetium Compounds ; Ultrasonography ; Urinalysis ; Urinary Tract Infections ; Urologic Surgical Procedures ; Vesico-Ureteral Reflux ; Watchful Waiting "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Anti-Bacterial Agents ; Antibiotic Prophylaxis ; Antibiotics ; Blood pressure determination ; Body Height ; Body Weight ; Cholinergic Antagonists ; Creatinine measurement, serum (procedure) ; Cystography ; Glomerular Filtration Rate ; Hypertensive disease ; KIDNEY FAILURE ; Microbial Sensitivity Tests ; Patient education (procedure) ; Patient observation ; Radionuclide Imaging ; Ultrasonography ; urinalysis ; Urinary bladder training ; Urinary tract infection "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: observation ; radionuclide imaging ; renal failure ; ultrasonography "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Antibacterial agent  (346325008); Antibacterial agent  (419241000); Antibiotic  (255631004); Antibiotic prophylaxis  (422181004); Blood pressure taking  (46973005); Body height measure  (50373000); Body weight  (27113001); Creatinine measurement, serum  (113075003); Cystography  (168854009); Cystography  (418135007); Glomerular filtration rate  (80274001); Hypertensive disorder  (38341003); Nuclear medicine imaging procedure  (373205008); Operation on bladder  (14861000); Parent education: childrearing family  (386381003); Patient education  (311401005); Patient status observation  (103705002); Renal failure syndrome  (42399005); Technetium compound  (47379009); Ultrasonography  (16310003); Ultrasonography  (278292003); Ultrasonography  (359659005); Urinalysis  (167217005); Urinalysis  (27171005); Urinary bladder training  (37799002); Urinary tract infectious disease  (68566005); Urine for culture  (117010004); Urine for culture  (275885001); Vesicoureteric reflux  (197811007)"/><FieldValue Value="SPN: SYSTEM, IMAGING, PULSED DOPPLER, ULTRASONIC "/><FieldValue Value="UMD: Catheters, Urinary, Urethral, Cystography  (10-763); Scanning Systems, Ultrasonic  (14-278); Tissue Bulking Agents  (20-726)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Primary vesicoureteral reflux &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Febrile urinary tract infection &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Acute pyelonephritis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Renal injury &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Evaluation" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Prevention" /><FieldValue Value="Treatment" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Nephrology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Surgery" /><FieldValue Value="Urology" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux in the child over one year of age&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children over one year of age with vesicoureteral reflux and no clinical evidence of bladder/bowel dysfunction who present initially with febrile urinary tract infection and a subsequent diagnosis of vesicoureteral reflux by cystography&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;General medical evaluation including measurement of height, weight, blood pressure, and serum creatinine if bilateral abnormalities are found &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Urinalysis and urine culture and sensitivity, if infection is indicated &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Renal ultrasound &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Estimate glomerular filtration rate &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Technetium-99m-labeled dimercaptosuccinic acid (DMSA) renal imaging &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Continuous antibiotic prophylaxis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Observational management &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Follow-up management including general evaluation (blood pressure, height, weight); urinalysis and culture and sensitivity, if indicated; imaging (ultrasonography, voiding cystography); DMSA imaging; and periodic upper tract imaging with renal ultrasound &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Open and endoscopic surgical ureteral reimplantation &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Endoscopic injection of bulking agents &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Changing antibiotic agents &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Education regarding hypertension, renal functional loss, recurrent urinary tract infection, and familial vesicoureteral reflux in siblings and offspring &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incidence and character of urinary tract infection &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Morbidity of acute pyelonephritis&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Renal cortical abnormalities &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Renal functional loss &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Resolution vesicoureteral reflux &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse events &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. This process is described in an accompanying Technical Report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). In addition, specific methodology for each of the five topics was also provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A wide literature search was performed with the headings of vesicoureteral reflux covering the years 1997 through June 2008. For screening, the search covered as far back as 1992. The panel chairs scrutinized independently the results from this search (1,501 articles) from the abstracts and determined the articles that would follow to the phase of systematic data extraction.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the next phase, panel members independently collected information using customized extraction forms including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Bibliographic information: year of publication and authors. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study characteristics: design, period, location and inclusion/exclusion criteria. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Patient population: number of children assessed with VUR with a cystogram (in either screening or management), descriptives of age at diagnosis (mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum), and sex distribution. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;VUR specific: severity scale, laterality, presentation or symptoms (prenatal hydronephrosis [PNH], urinary tract infection [UTI], other), renal damage at diagnosis. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Management specific: treatment regimen (antibiotic prophylaxis, open surgery, endoscopic surgery), outcomes (reflux resolution, cortical renal abnormalities, UTI incidence). &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Renal outcomes: use of scintigraphy vs. intravenous pyelography (IVP, earlier years) for the screening aims, scintigraphy modality used (dimercaptosuccinic acid [DMSA], diethylenetriamine pentaacetic acid [DTPA], or mercaptoacetyltriglycine [MAG3]), explicit definition of renal cortical abnormalities. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also, additional information was collected specific to each index case as follows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 1&lt;/span&gt;: Presence/proportion of duplex cases in the cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 2&lt;/span&gt;: Circumcision status.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 3&lt;/span&gt;: Number of children with bladder/bowel dysfunction (BBD), distribution of BBD symptoms and BBD management (bladder training, anticholinergics, biofeedback).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 4&lt;/span&gt;: Number of and relationship with index cases.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Case 5&lt;/span&gt;: Prenatal and post-natal anteroposterior renal pelvis diameter (RPD) thresholds as measured by ultrasound (US), time of pre-natal and early post-natal evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of the second phase, each extractor excluded articles based on a set of pre-defined rejection criteria either without extracting the complete article or after the complete extraction. The criteria for rejection without extraction included:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The absence of relevant outcomes or complications data &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Cannot interpret the data to fit the extraction form &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Insufficient treatment efficacy follow-up (less than 3 months) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The article did not deal with either management or screening &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In specific cases, the extractor considered that the article had problems but rather than excluding it subjected the article to the review of the entire panel which determined whether the article should finally be rejected or included in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Criteria for Acceptance of Studies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To be accepted, a study should have assessed primarily a cohort of children, clearly stated the number of children undergoing screening for VUR or number of children with VUR undergoing a particular management regimen. For management cases, reflux resolution should have been assessed at least three months after the intervention with a cystogram and renal outcomes assessed by nuclear scintigraphy. Review articles found were scrutinized and scanned in order to determine that all articles complying with selection criteria were included.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A literature search, review of the evidence, and data extraction from the relevant clinical studies and case series were performed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In all, 205 articles were evaluable, and data from 84 studies reported from 1994 to 2008 were extracted and meta-analyzed. Some studies included children younger than one year and outcomes were not separable for younger and older children. Also, some evidence may include non-toilet trained children (&amp;gt;1 year of age).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The articles for the sub-analysis to examine the risk factors for renal scarring, which were not all selected in the initial literature review, included only studies in which children had acute pyelonephritis based on technetium-99m-labeled DMSA abnormalities and who were re-evaluated by DMSA more than 6 months after the acute event. These studies were not exclusively comprised of children with VUR. The remaining criteria used in selecting articles for this subanalysis are described in the methodology in the original guideline document. Any study not meeting these strict criteria was excluded. Included in the analysis were eight studies of cohorts assessed between 1992 and 2006, with five (63%) studies being prospective. In all, at least 266 children with VUR and 444 without VUR were examined with a second DMSA for the development of scarring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;205 articles were evaluable, and data from 84 studies reported from 1994 to 2008 were extracted and meta-analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Meta-Analysis" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. This process is described in an accompanying Technical Report (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). In addition, specific methodology for each of the five topics was also provided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Conditioning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After extraction and acceptance of the article, the data were conditioned for analysis in two steps. First, it was verified that all the necessary fields were complete and if data were missing it was confirmed that the data did not appear in the articles. The second step consisted in assessing apparently repeated/overlapping articles. The different sets of related studies and the articles selected from each of those sets are indicated in the corresponding chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Studies or arms which included less than 10 patients or renal units for analysis were excluded due to the imprecision of estimates that they would generate. This exclusion was done at the analysis stage by the methodologist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Study Quality Evaluation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines for reporting of meta-analysis of observational studies elaborated by the Meta-analysis of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group indicate the need to assess the quality of the studies included in the literature synthesis. A quality score was developed to assess the quality of the studies extracted and accepted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Twenty items were common to the quality scores across the different index cases (or topics). Four items (1-4) corresponded to study design (basic score). Eleven items were specific to the assessment of reflux (5-15, reflux score), three to the assessment of renal outcomes (16-18, renal score) and two to the assessment of urinary tract infection (UTI) (20-21, UTI score). Additional items were included for specific issues related to each index case (extra score). A total score was built by adding all the individual items. In any of the scores, each characteristic received one quality point when present. In particular situations a half point rather than a point was provided. For example, for management of children with bladder/bowel dysfunction (BBD) the articles described the sample in terms of age and sex; however these two characteristics were not provided for the strata built with BBD status, in this case half points were given to these items in the quality score. The quality score was used in a descriptive manner to determine the possible relation between individual estimates and study quality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A meta-analysis of the existing literature was performed to define the outcomes of nonoperative and surgical management of VUR among toilet-trained children without evidence of BBD. The analysis defined 19 specific questions upon which clinical decisions are based. The questions were grouped into three categories; 1) those evaluating the causal relationship between VUR, pyelonephritis and renal injury (no causal relationship can be established with the design used in the majority of studies); 2) those determining the outcomes following treatment with continuous antibiotic prophylaxis (CAP); and 3) the outcomes of therapy with curative intent (endoscopic and open surgical intervention).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data were extracted on 11,837 children: 578 children who underwent observation in seven studies, 3,311 children who received continuous antibiotic prophylaxis in 29 studies, 4,587 children who had open surgery in 33 studies, 626 children who received macroplastique injection therapy in 7 studies, and 2,735 children who received dextranomer/hyaluronic acid injection therapy in 17 studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, a sub-analysis was conducted to determine the possible association between acute pyelonephritis, VUR and renal scarring. A meta-analysis was performed comparing the incidence of renal scarring after the occurrence of an episode of acute pyelonephritis in children with VUR to those without VUR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The supporting systematic literature review and the drafting of the guideline document were conducted by the Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel (the Panel) created in 2006 by the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA). The Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC) of the AUA selected the Panel Chair and Vice-Chair, who in turn appointed the additional Panel members with specific expertise in this disease. The mission of the Panel was to develop either analysis- or consensus-based recommendations, depending on the type of evidence available and Panel processes, to support optimal clinical practices in the management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) nomenclature, the statements are graded with respect to the degree of flexibility in application. A &quot;standard&quot; is the most rigid treatment policy. A &quot;recommendation&quot; has significantly less rigidity and an &quot;option&quot; the least. These terms are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a standard if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) there is virtual unanimity among panel members about which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a recommendation if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) an appreciable, but not unanimous majority of the panel members agrees on which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is an option if (1) the health outcomes of the interventions are not sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions or (2) preferences are unknown or equivocal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document was submitted to approximately 75 urologists and other health care professionals for peer review. After revision of the document based upon the peer review comments, the guideline was submitted to and approved by the Practice Guidelines Committee (PGC) and the Board of Directors of the American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the American Urological Association (AUA) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: When the AUA convened to update the 1997 recommendations for the management of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) in children, the panel divided the task into five topics pertaining to a specific management question requiring clarification. The other four topics are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24027&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8018&quot;&gt;Management of infants less than one year of age with vesicoureteral reflux&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24028&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8019&quot;&gt;Management of children with vesicoureteral reflux and bladder/bowel dysfunction&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24029&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8020&quot;&gt;Screening of siblings and offspring of patients with vesicoureteral reflux&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=24030&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8021&quot;&gt;Screening of the neonate/infant with prenatal hydronephrosis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Definitions of the strength of the recommendations &lt;strong&gt;(standard, recommendation, option)&lt;/strong&gt; are defined at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initial Evaluation of the Child with Vesicoureteral Reflux (VUR)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: VUR and urinary tract infections may detrimentally affect the overall health and renal function in affected children. Therefore, on initial presentation the child with VUR should undergo a careful general medical evaluation including measurement of height, weight, and blood pressure, and serum creatinine if bilateral renal abnormalities are found. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: Symptoms indicative of bladder/bowel dysfunction should be sought in the initial evaluation, including urinary frequency and urgency, prolonged voiding intervals, daytime wetting, perineal/penile pain, holding maneuvers (posturing to prevent wetting), constipation/encopresis. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: Family and patient education regarding VUR should include a discussion of the rationale for treating VUR, the potential consequences of untreated VUR, the equivalency of certain treatment approaches, assessment of likely adherence with the care plan, determination of parental concerns and accommodation of parental preferences when treatment choices offer a similar risk-benefit balance. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Urinalysis for proteinuria and bacteriuria. If the urinalysis indicates infection, a urine culture and sensitivity is recommended. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Because VUR and urinary tract infection may affect renal structure and function, performing renal ultrasound to assess the upper urinary tract is recommended. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A baseline serum creatinine may be obtained to establish an estimate of glomerular filtration rate (GFR) for future reference. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: DMSA (technetium-99m-labeled dimercaptosuccinic acid) renal imaging can be obtained to assess the status of the kidneys for scarring and function. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Continuous Antibiotic Prophylaxis in the Treatment of VUR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Continuous antibiotic prophylaxis may be considered for the child with a history of urinary tract infection and VUR in the absence of bladder/bowel dysfunction. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Observational management without continuous antibiotic prophylaxis, with prompt initiation of antibiotic therapy for urinary tract infection, may be considered for the child with VUR in the absence of bladder/bowel dysfunction, recurrent febrile urinary tract infections, or renal cortical abnormalities. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Follow-up Management of the Child with VUR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: General evaluation, including monitoring of blood pressure, height, and weight is recommended annually. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Urinalysis for proteinuria and bacteriuria is indicated annually, including a urine culture and sensitivity if the urinalysis is suggestive of infection. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: The follow-up interval is determined by the likelihood of resolution; for higher grades of VUR, resolution is less likely (Elder et al., 1997) and therefore a longer interval of follow-up is appropriate. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imaging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Imaging, including ultrasonography and voiding cystography (radionuclide cystogram or low-dose fluoroscopy, when available) is recommended every 12 to 24 months, with longer intervals between follow-up studies in patients in whom evidence supports lower rates of spontaneous resolution to limit the number of imaging studies (i.e., those with higher grades of VUR [grades III-V; see clinical chapter 2 and 1997 Guidelines], bladder/bowel dysfunction [see clinical chapter 3], and older age). This is to limit the over-all number of imaging studies performed. If an observational approach is being used, follow-up cystography becomes an option. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: DMSA imaging is recommended when a renal ultrasound is abnormal, when there is a greater concern for scarring (i.e., breakthrough urinary tract infection [BT-UTI]; [see Glossary in the original guideline document for description], higher grades III-V of VUR), or if there is an elevated serum creatinine. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Follow-up cystography may be done after one year of age in patients with VUR grades I&amp;ndash;II; these patients tend to have a high rate of spontaneous resolution and boys have a low risk of recurrent urinary tract infection. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A single normal voiding cystogram (i.e., no evidence of VUR) may serve to establish resolution. The clinical significance of grade I VUR, and the need for ongoing evaluation is undefined. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Periodic upper tract imaging with renal ultrasound may be done to assess renal growth and the presence of gross renal scarring. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: DMSA may be considered for follow-up of children with VUR, to detect new renal scarring, especially after a febrile urinary tract infection. [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Interventions for the Child with a Febrile Breakthrough Urinary Tract Infection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: If symptomatic breakthrough urinary tract infection occurs (manifested by fever, dysuria, frequency, failure to thrive, or poor feeding), a change in therapy is recommended. If symptomatic breakthrough urinary tract infection occurs, the clinical scenario will guide the choice of treatment alternatives; this includes VUR grade, degree of renal scarring, if any, and evidence of abnormal voiding patterns (bladder/bowel dysfunction) that might contribute to urinary tract infection, and parental preferences. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: It is recommended that in patients receiving continuous antibiotic prophylaxis with a febrile breakthrough urinary tract infection be considered for open surgical ureteral reimplantation or endoscopic injection of bulking agents for intervention with curative intent. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: In patients not receiving continuous antibiotic prophylaxis who develop a febrile urinary tract infection, initiation of continuous antibiotic prophylaxis is recommended. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: In patients receiving continuous antibiotic prophylaxis with a single febrile breakthrough urinary tract infection and no evidence of pre-existing or new renal cortical abnormalities, changing to another antibiotic agent is an option prior to intervention with curative intent. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: In patients not receiving continuous antibiotic prophylaxis who develop a non-febrile urinary tract infection, initiation of continuous antibiotic prophylaxis is an option in recognition of the fact that not all cases of pyelonephritis are associated with fever. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Surgical Treatment of VUR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Surgical intervention for VUR, including both open and endoscopic methods, may be used. Prospective randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have shown a reduction in the occurrence of febrile urinary tract infections in patients who have undergone open surgical correction of VUR as compared to those receiving continuous antibiotic prophylaxis. (Jodal et al., 2006; Jodal et al., 1992) [Based on review of the data and Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Management Following Resolution of VUR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Following the resolution of VUR, either spontaneously or by surgical intervention and if both kidneys are normal by ultrasound or DMSA scanning, general evaluation, including monitoring of blood pressure, height, and weight, and urinalysis for protein and urinary tract infection, annually through adolescence is an option. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: Following the resolution of VUR, either spontaneously or by surgical intervention, general evaluation, including monitoring of blood pressure, height, and weight, and urinalysis for protein and urinary tract infection, is recommended annually through adolescence if either kidney is abnormal by ultrasound or DMSA scanning. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: With the occurrence of a febrile urinary tract infection following resolution or surgical treatment of VUR, evaluation for bladder/bowel dysfunction or recurrent VUR is recommended. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: It is recommended that the long-term concerns of hypertension (particularly during pregnancy), renal functional loss, recurrent urinary tract infection, and familial VUR in the child's siblings and offspring be discussed with the family and communicated to the child at an appropriate age. [Based on Panel Consensus]&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) nomenclature, the statements are graded with respect to the degree of flexibility in application. A &quot;standard&quot; is the most rigid treatment policy. A &quot;recommendation&quot; has significantly less rigidity and an &quot;option&quot; the least. These terms are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a standard if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) there is virtual unanimity among panel members about which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is a recommendation if (1) the health outcomes of the alternative interventions are sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions and (2) an appreciable, but not unanimous majority of the panel members agrees on which intervention is preferred. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt;: A guideline statement is an option if (1) the health outcomes of the interventions are not sufficiently well-known to permit meaningful decisions or (2) preferences are unknown or equivocal. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="98" OrdBy="605" ID="425" Name="References Supporting the Recommendations" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Elder JS, Peters CA, Arant BS Jr, Ewalt DH, Hawtrey CE, Hurwitz RS, Parrott TS, Snyder HM 3d, Weiss RA, Woolf SH, Hasselblad V. Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Guidelines Panel summary report on the management of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children. J Urol. 1997 May;157(5):1846-51. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=9112544&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Jodal U, Koskimies O, Hanson E, Lohr G, Olbing H, Smellie J, Tamminen-Mobius T. Infection pattern in children with vesicoureteral reflux randomly allocated to operation or long-term antibacterial prophylaxis. The International Reflux Study  in Children. J Urol. 1992 Nov;148(5 Pt 2):1650-2. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=1433581&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Jodal U, Smellie JM, Lax H, Hoyer PF. Ten-year results of randomized treatment of children with severe vesicoureteral reflux. Final report of the International Reflux Study in Children. Pediatr Nephrol. 2006 Jun;21(6):785-92. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16565873&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of supporting evidence is not specifically stated for each recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations contained in the guideline are based on a review of the data and panel consensus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduced risk of pyelonephritis and permanent renal injury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adverse events following endoscopic or open surgery for vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Postoperative obstruction &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Postoperative voiding disturbances &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Postoperative contralateral VUR after unilateral treatment &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guideline document provides guidance only and does not establish a fixed set of rules or define the legal standard of care. As medical knowledge expands and technology advances, the guidelines may change. Today they represent not an absolute mandate but rather current proposals or recommendations for treatment under the specific conditions described. For all these reasons, the Guidelines do not preempt physician judgment in individual cases. Also, treating physicians must take into account variations in resources, and in patient tolerances, needs and preferences. Conformance with the recommendations reflected in this document cannot guarantee a successful outcome. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The guideline document may also include information or recommendations about certain drug uses ('off label') that are not approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), or about medications or substances not subject to the FDA approval process. American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. (AUA) urges strict compliance with all government regulations and protocols for prescription and use of these substances. The physician is encouraged to carefully follow all available prescribing information about indications, contraindications, precautions and warnings. These guidelines are not intended to provide legal advice about use and misuse of these substances. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Although the development of a clinical guideline is often limited by the availability of quality data, which is notably true with respect to the vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) literature, recommendations can be based on general principles developed from a formal meta-analysis as well as experience and clinical judgment. These guidelines for management of VUR were based upon risk assessment, considering the probability for spontaneous resolution versus perceived risk for recurrent urinary tract infection (UTI) and renal injury. In the absence of definitive evidence, stronger guidelines cannot appropriately be made and the final decisions regarding clinical care reside with the physician and family. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation strategy was not provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Getting Better" /><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Management of vesicoureteral reflux in the child over one year of age. In: American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: AUA guideline. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc.; 2010. p. 1-28. [16 references]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: This guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="1997 Apr (revised 2010)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. - Medical Specialty Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panel Members&lt;/em&gt;: Craig A. Peters, M.D. (&lt;em&gt;Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Steven J. Skoog, M.D. (&lt;em&gt;Vice-Chair&lt;/em&gt;); Billy S. Arant, Jr., M.D.; Hillary L. Copp, M.D.; Jack S. Elder, M.D. (Facilitator); R. Guy Hudson, M.D.; Antoine E. Khoury, M.D.; Armando J. Lorenzo, M.D.; Hans G. Pohl, M.D.; Ellen Shapiro, M.D.; Warren T. Snodgrass, M.D.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consultants:&lt;/em&gt; Mireya Diaz, Ph.D.; Linda Whetter, D.V.M, Ph.D.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All panel members completed Conflict of Interest disclosures. Those marked with (C) indicate that compensation was received; relationships designated by (U) indicate no compensation was received.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientific Study or Trial&lt;/strong&gt;: Jack S. Elder, QMed Scandinavia (U); &lt;strong&gt;Meeting Participant or Lecturer&lt;/strong&gt;: Billy Arant, Novartis (C); &lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt;: Jack S. Elder, FSC Laboratories (U); &lt;strong&gt;Investment Interest&lt;/strong&gt;: Antoine E. Khoury, Covalon (U), Interface Biologics (U)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: American Urological Association (AUA), Pediatric Vesicoureteral Reflux Clinical Guidelines Panel. Report on the management of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children. Baltimore (MD): American Urological Association, Inc; 1997 Apr. 88 p. (Clinical practice guidelines; no. 4/97). [249 references]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/content/guidelines-and-quality-care/clinical-guidelines/main-reports/vur2010/ManageChildVeslRefluxChildOverOne.pdf&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Management and screening of primary vesicoureteral reflux in children: American Urological Association Guideline. Summary report. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association Education and Research, Inc. 2010. 30 p. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auanet.org/content/guidelines-and-quality-care/clinical-guidelines/main-reports/vur2010/AuthorsAndSummaryReport.pdf&quot; title=&quot;AUA Web site&quot;&gt;American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA) Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Technical Report associated with this guideline is available upon request. Please contact the AUA Guidelines Department at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:guidelines@auanet.org&quot;&gt;guidelines@auanet.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Vesicoureteral reflux. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association (AUA) Education and Research, Inc.; 2009 Jul. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urologyhealth.org/urology/index.cfm?article=55&quot; title=&quot;AUA Foundation Web site&quot;&gt;AUA Foundation Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Urinary tract infections in children. Linthicum (MD): American Urological Association (AUA) Education and Research, Inc.; 2010 Jan. Electronic copies: Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urologyhealth.org/urology/index.cfm?article=46&quot; title=&quot;AUA Foundation Web site&quot;&gt;AUA Foundation Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summary was completed by ECRI on March 26, 1999. The information was verified by the guideline developer as of May 14, 1999. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 22, 2010. The updated information was verified by the guideline developer on February 28, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is copyrighted by the American Urological Association, Inc. (AUA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
