<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Public awareness of stroke. In: Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Public awareness of stroke. In: Lindsay MP, Gubitz G, Bayley M, Hill MD, Davies-Schinkel C, Singh S, Phillips S, Canadian Stroke Strategy Best Practices and Standards Writing Group. Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. Ottawa (ON): Canadian Stroke Network; 2010 Dec 8. p. 17-20.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Lindsay P, Bayley M, Hellings C, Hill M, Woodbury E, Phillips S. Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. CMAJ 2008 Dec 2;179(12 Suppl).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care include an ongoing plan to formally update the recommendations every 2 years to ensure that the best practice recommendations remain current and are coordinated with other similar initiatives nationally and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Cerebral artery occlusion, unspecified with cerebral infarction  (434.91); Unspecified intracranial hemorrhage  (432.9); Unspecified transient cerebral ischemia  (435.9)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Brain Ischemia ; Health Education ; Intracranial Hemorrhages ; Ischemic Attack, Transient ; Patient Education as Topic ; Preventive Health Services ; Stroke "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Brain hemorrhage ; Brain Ischemia ; Cerebrovascular accident ; Health education ; Ischemic stroke ; Patient education (procedure) ; Transient Cerebral Ischemia ; Transient Ischemic Attack "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Cerebral artery occlusion  (20059004); Cerebrovascular accident  (230690007); Education of caregiver  (427519008); Education of caregiver  (460617003); Family education  (311403008); Family education  (460616007); Intracranial hemorrhage  (1386000); Ischemic encephalopathy  (389100007); Ischemic stroke  (422504002); Patient education  (311401005); Stroke prevention  (135875009); Transient cerebral ischemia  (266257000)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stroke, including hemorrhagic stroke and&amp;nbsp;ischemic stroke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Counseling" /><FieldValue Value="Management" /><FieldValue Value="Prevention" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Cardiology" /><FieldValue Value="Critical Care" /><FieldValue Value="Emergency Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Geriatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Neurology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation" /><FieldValue Value="Preventive Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Allied Health Personnel" /><FieldValue Value="Emergency Medical Technicians/Paramedics" /><FieldValue Value="Health Care Providers" /><FieldValue Value="Hospitals" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Occupational Therapists" /><FieldValue Value="Patients" /><FieldValue Value="Physical Therapists" /><FieldValue Value="Physician Assistants" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /><FieldValue Value="Utilization Management" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide a synthesis of best practices in stroke care across the continuum of care and serve as a framework for Canadian provinces and territories as they develop and implement stroke strategies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All members of the public&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public education regarding recognition and identification of signs and symptoms of stroke and appropriate actions to take&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Public awareness of stroke warning signs &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Timeliness of care&lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MEDLINE, EMBASE and the Cochrane Library databases were rigorously searched. Also, the grey literature and websites of other best practice recommendation developers were searched for relevant material that may not have been published in an academic journal.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The time frame of each literature search ran from the time the best practice recommendation was last updated (2008) up until September, 2010. Unless invalid, the literature from the previously reviewed recommendations, completed in 2006 and 2008, was included. For new recommendations, the literature search time frame was from 1990 until September, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following studies were included during the search: randomized controlled clinical trials (double-blinded or nonblinded); meta-analyses of randomized studies; nonrandomized controlled clinical trials and case series; population-based, consecutive series; consecutive cases (not population-based); or, non-consecutive cases. Included articles were published in English and were based on human studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All terms used were particular to stroke and the topic being searched. A total of 35 different topics were explored. Specific drug names, treatment names, and therapy names were used to create an inclusive database for each topic. This resulted in a total of 699 references included in the Canadian Stroke Best Practice Recommendations 2010 update.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 699 studies were included.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Definitions for Levels of Evidence*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; summary=&quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Grade&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Criteria&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation. Evidence from randomized controlled trials or meta-analyses of randomized controlled trials. Desirable effects clearly outweigh undesirable effects, or vice versa. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Single randomized controlled trial or well-designed observational study with strong evidence; or well-designed cohort or case&amp;ndash;control analytic study; or multiple time series or dramatic results of uncontrolled experiment. Desirable effects closely balanced with undesirable effects. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;At least one well-designed, nonexperimental descriptive study (e.g., comparative studies, correlation studies, case studies) or expert committee reports, opinions and/or experience of respected authorities, including consensus from development and/or reviewer groups. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Based on Guyatt GH, Cook DJ, Jaeschke R, et al. Grades of recommendation for antithrombotic agents: American College of Chest Physicians Evidence-Based Clinical Practice Guidelines (8th edition). [published erratum in Chest 2008;34:47]. Chest 2008;133(6 Suppl):123S-131S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluating the Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A Stroke Best Practices Recommendations Matrix was developed that mapped other existing stroke-related recommendations and their levels of evidence onto topic areas identified as relevant to optimal stroke care in Canada (i.e., blood pressure management, organization of care).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A list of topics was generated by identifying recommendations with the highest levels of evidence in each of the reference guidelines. Where similar or related recommendations on a particular topic appeared in more than two guidelines, it was added to the topic list. The final list of topics was then cross-referenced with the Stroke Canada Optimization of Rehabilitation through Evidence (SCORE) and the Canadian Stroke Quality of Care Study (CSQCS) studies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Best Practices Recommendations Matrix was created through an iterative process of review and discussion among the members of the sub-group and the Best Practices and Standards Working Group (BPS-WG) as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation of Levels of Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each recommendation included in this document was evaluated against several criteria: strength of the available research evidence to support the recommendation; degree to which the recommendation drives system change or processes of care delivery; overall validity and relevance as a core recommendation for stroke care along the continuum of care. The levels of evidence included in this document are determined through a structured ranking system which measures the strength of the results in a clinical trial or research study. The design of the study (such as a case report for an individual patient or a randomized double-blinded controlled clinical trial) and the endpoints measured (such as survival or quality of life) affect the strength of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The various types of study designs, in descending order of strength, include:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Randomized controlled clinical trials (double-blinded or non-blinded) are considered the gold standard of study design. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Meta-analyses of randomized studies offer a quantitative synthesis of previously conducted studies. The strength of evidence from a meta-analysis is based on the quality of the conduct of individual studies. Meta-analyses of randomized studies are placed in the same category of strength of evidence as are randomized studies. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Nonrandomized controlled clinical trials &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Case series: Population-based, consecutive series, consecutive cases (not population-based) or nonconsecutive cases. These clinical experiences are the weakest form of study design, but often they are the only available or practical information. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Several rating systems are used by guideline developers to evaluate the strength of the evidence for their recommendations. These systems vary in the nomenclature used (alphabetical versus numeric), but there is usually reasonable equivalence in the definitions across the levels of evidence. Each recommendation in this document provides the level of evidence for the recommendation (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; field), as well as the reference for the Primary Guideline(s) that were adapted or contributed most to the wording of the recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus (Consensus Development Conference)" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stroke Guideline Development Framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conceptual framework used to guide the identification, selection, development and updating of the Canadian best practice recommendations was the Practice Guideline Evaluation and Adaptation Cycle of Graham and colleagues. This cycle involves the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Establishing an interprofessional guideline development team &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Establishing a guideline appraisal process using a validated tool &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Systematic searching for existing practice guidelines &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Appraising the quality, currency and content of guideline recommendations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Adopting or adapting guidelines for local use &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Obtaining external expert feedback on the proposed recommendations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Selecting final recommendations &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Obtaining official endorsement &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Establishing an ongoing review and update process &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The methodology for the first edition of the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care (2006)&lt;/em&gt; was based on this framework, and it is applied, with some enhancements, to develop each update. The key activities undertaken in the guideline development process are highlighted below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leadership and Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Stroke Strategy (CSS) Best Practices and Standards Working Group has overall responsibility for the development and update process. The 2010 update cycle was led by a subgroup of the Working Group and managed by the Director of Performance and Standards at the Canadian Stroke Network (CSN).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An interprofessional group of experts in stroke care participated in topic-specific task groups convened to review, draft, and revise recommendation statements for their topic. Recognized experts within the topic area chaired each task group, and members included stroke neurologists, physiatrists, nurses, emergency physicians, paramedics, physical therapists, occupational therapists, dietitians, speech&amp;ndash;language pathologists, pharmacists, stroke survivors, education experts, and professionals from other disciplines as required. This interprofessional approach ensured that all relevant health disciplines for a particular topic area were represented in the development of the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A national interprofessional consensus panel was convened to provide further input into the recommendations and a final review was conducted by an external group of stroke and methods experts before release.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identification of Key Topic Areas and Core Reference Guidelines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The process used to identify key topic areas and core reference guidelines is outlined below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;An ongoing structured literature review is conducted every two to three months to monitor emerging evidence and new or updated stroke-related guidelines. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Scans of the primary research literature focused on meta-analyses, systematic reviews, randomized trials, quasi-experimental studies, other related guidelines and reports, and Canadian consensus statements by healthcare professional groups. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The strength of the research evidence was graded using a standardized grading system (see the &quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; field). In some areas, the levels of evidence for a given topic varied among selected guidelines or research papers depending on the nature of the research. The totality of the information for each topic provided a comprehensive understanding of the strength of the evidence, the state of the research, and gaps for future inquiry. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A detailed literature search for international stroke-related guidelines was also undertaken. The Appraisal of Guidelines Research and Evaluation (AGREE) tool was applied to determine the quality of the guidelines. This tool can be used to assess the process of guideline development based on six domains: identification of a clinical area to promote best practice, stakeholder involvement, rigour of development, clarity and presentation, applicability, and editorial independence. Based on the results of the appraisals, several guidelines met the Working Group criteria to be considered as 'reference guidelines' for the development process. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Once the high-quality guidelines were identified, a content review was conducted to identify a list of stroke topic areas that were supported by the highest levels of evidence. A secondary list of topic areas with lower levels of supporting evidence but considered being key system drivers (such as acute diagnostic imaging with computed tomography scans) was also compiled. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Potential topics that emerged from the research and guideline review were compiled into a &quot;Topic Matrix&quot; to allow easy comparison by topic and strength of evidence. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The topic areas and levels of supporting evidence were reviewed and debated by the Working Group. Using a consensus model, a final list of stroke topic areas that were considered most relevant to optimal stroke care in Canada was developed. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Topic areas were assigned to one of eight task groups to develop detailed recommendation statements. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See Appendix 7 in the original guideline document for a list of guidelines and significant research trials that were considered during the 2010 update process.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synthesis of Best Practice Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Expert task groups (see Appendix 2 in the original guideline document for a list of task group members) were convened for each segment of the continuum of stroke care, to select relevant recommendations arising from the evidence review and if necessary draft new recommendations based on emerging evidence. Task groups were instructed that recommendations could address structure and/or processes of care at either the system level or the patient level, and that they could be taken directly from other existing guidelines, adapted from one or more guidelines, or written by the task group. Appropriate references were to accompany all recommendation statements derived from evidence or existing guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the 2010 update, each task group participated in a series of teleconferences between May 2009 and February 2010 to complete their research reviews and develop the recommendations. The Director of Performance and Standards at the CSN participated in all teleconferences to ensure consistency, standardization, and rigour of development across task groups.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See the original guideline document for more information on the recommendation development process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published costs analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Expert Consensus Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Following completion of the task group work, the draft recommendations and supporting information were presented for discussion and decision-making to a broad group of stakeholders at a national expert consensus meeting held in Toronto, Ontario in April, 2010 (see Appendix 3 of the original guideline document for a list of consensus participants). Consensus participants included the Best Practices Working Group, the chairs of each task group, and invited opinion leaders, stroke survivors, and healthcare professionals external to the development process. The selection of consensus participants was based on ensuring representation from stroke-related health professional disciplines, all sectors of the healthcare continuum, all provinces in Canada, and rural and urban work environments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consensus participants received the draft recommendations, including proposed changes to existing recommendations as well as new recommendations, in advance of the consensus meeting. They were asked to review the information, provide feedback to the Working Group prior to the meeting, and indicate their degree of support for each recommendation. Votes were taken after each topic area discussion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definitions of the levels of evidence (A-C) are provided at the end of the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note from the Canadian Stroke Network/Heart &amp;amp; Stroke Foundation of Canada (CSN/HSFC) and the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC)&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt;, 2010 update, has been divided into individual summaries. In addition to the current summary, the following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34087&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8611&quot;&gt;Prevention of stroke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34088&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8612&quot;&gt;Hyperacute stroke management&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34090&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8613&quot;&gt;Acute stroke management&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34091&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8614&quot;&gt;Stroke rehabilitation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34092&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8615&quot;&gt;Managing stroke care transitions&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content.aspx?id=34094&quot; title=&quot;Guideline #8616&quot;&gt;Cross-continuum topics in stroke management&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's New for 2010?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The 2010 content update focuses on:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Access: Providing good stroke care, quickly &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Continuity: Helping people move smoothly through the stroke continuum, from symptom onset to diagnosis, treatment, management, and recovery &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For 2010 the SCORE (Stroke Canada Optimization of Rehabilitation through Evidence) recommendations for upper and lower limb have been integrated within the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt;. Also new for 2010 is a section on transitions of care to help patients, families, and caregivers access the right type of care in the right settings at the right time. To facilitate uptake of the best practice recommendations by front-line clinicians, the best practice recommendations also include a new section on information about implementation resources.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other significant changes for 2010:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Atrial fibrillation and carotid endarterectomy recommendations were revised to address the findings of two recently published clinical trials (RE-LY and CREST), which have important implications for stroke prevention. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Intracranial hemorrhage and subarachnoid hemorrhage recommendations were revised and expanded to address immediate assessment and management of these patients. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;New recommendations on fall prevention to address an important patient safety issue. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Public Awareness of Stroke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Practice Recommendation: Symptom Recognition and Reaction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All members of the public should be able to recognize the warning signs and symptoms of stroke, and react immediately by calling 9-1-1 or their local emergency number.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: lower-roman;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Public education on stroke should emphasize that stroke is a medical emergency, and that immediate medical attention should be sought. All members of the public should know how to take the appropriate actions &amp;mdash; that is, to call 9-1-1 or their local emergency number [&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Level B&lt;/strong&gt;]. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Public education should include information that stroke can affect persons of any age &amp;mdash; from newborns and children to adults - and be aware of the benefits of early medical attention [&lt;strong&gt;Evidence Level C&lt;/strong&gt;]. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning Signs and Symptoms of Stroke&lt;/strong&gt; (Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.com&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada Web site&quot;&gt;www.heartandstroke.com&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weakness&lt;/strong&gt;: Sudden weakness, numbness or tingling in the face, arm or leg &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trouble speaking&lt;/strong&gt;: Sudden temporary loss of speech or trouble understanding speech &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision problems&lt;/strong&gt;: Sudden loss of vision, particularly in one eye, or double vision &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Headache&lt;/strong&gt;: Sudden severe and unusual headache &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dizziness&lt;/strong&gt;: Sudden loss of balance, especially with any of the above signs&amp;nbsp; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ACTION: Call 9-1-1 or your local emergency number IMMEDIATELY.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rationale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to stroke, &lt;em&gt;time is brain&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stroke is a medical emergency. Most people do not recognize the 5 main symptoms of stroke and therefore do not seek immediate medical attention. It is critical that people with ischemic strokes (caused by a blocked artery) arrive in the emergency department as soon as possible, and within at least 3.5 hours of symptom onset, if they are to be eligible to receive clot-busting treatment. In the case of strokes caused by hemorrhage or leaking arteries in the brain, earlier assessment and treatment may allow time for life-saving intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Efforts to enhance emergency medical system response to stroke calls and to encourage the public to recognize stroke signs and symptoms and contact emergency medical services result in timelier treatment and better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Definitions for Levels of Evidence*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; summary=&quot;Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Grade&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Criteria&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/thead&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Strong recommendation. Evidence from randomized controlled trials or meta-analyses of randomized controlled trials. Desirable effects clearly outweigh undesirable effects, or vice versa. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Single randomized controlled trial or well-designed observational study with strong evidence; or well-designed cohort or case&amp;ndash;control analytic study; or multiple time series or dramatic results of uncontrolled experiment. Desirable effects closely balanced with undesirable effects. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;th class=&quot;Center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;&#xD;&#xA;            &lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;At least one well-designed, nonexperimental descriptive study (e.g., comparative studies, correlation studies, case studies) or expert committee reports, opinions and/or experience of respected authorities, including consensus from development and/or reviewer groups. &lt;/td&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;/tr&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;*Based on Guyatt GH, Cook DJ, Jaeschke R, et al. Grades of recommendation for antithrombotic agents: American College of Chest Physicians Evidence-Based Clinical Practice Guidelines (8th edition). [published erratum in Chest 2008;34:47]. Chest 2008;133(6 Suppl):123S-131S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence is specifically stated for each recommendation (see the &quot;Major Recommendations&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This document is the result of an extensive review of national and international evidence-based stroke best practice recommendations and guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Efforts to enhance emergency medical system response to stroke calls and to encourage the public to recognize stroke signs and symptoms and contact emergency medical services result in timelier treatment and better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="432" OrdBy="900" Name="Qualifying Statements"><Field FieldID="137" OrdBy="905" ID="433" Name="Qualifying Statements" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The Canadian Stroke Strategy (CSS) recognizes that human, financial, and system resource limitations may make it difficult to implement all recommendations in this document. However, the recommendations and performance measures are presented as &quot;gold standard&quot; benchmarks toward which all organizations and systems should strive. Additionally, these recommendations can be valuable tools and information sources for anyone advocating for improved stroke care services. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;The recommendations in this document are better seen as guidelines rather than rigid rules. They are not meant to supplant clinical judgment and consideration of unique patient circumstances. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Every attempt has been made to keep these recommendations up to date; however, given the rapid evolution of stroke research, late-breaking evidence may not be reflected. For this update, the literature review completion date was September 30, 2010. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;It was not feasible to present the expert panel with all available evidence, and therefore the primary evidence was initially screened and evaluated by the task groups. Wherever possible, late-breaking evidence was reviewed by the task group leaders to identify areas where the current recommendations might be significantly altered. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networking and Distribution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Stroke Strategy (CSS) makes the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt; available openly and at no cost, in English and French. Publication and dissemination strategies have changed in response to user needs and feedback. In 2006, printed documents and CDs were provided to all contacts in the CSS database, to others on request, and to interested groups throughout Canada and internationally. The 2008 Update was published through the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Medical Association Journal&lt;/em&gt; (CMAJ) as a supplement to subscribers and posted on the CMAJ website with links to the document on the CSS website; the CSS provided a limited number of printed copies upon request. The 2010 Update is available on the Canadian Stroke Network (CSN) Best Practices web site, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/&quot; title=&quot;CSN Web site&quot;&gt;www.strokebestpractices.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also on the website, patients and the general public can find &lt;em&gt;A Patient's Guide to the Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt;. The CSS created the patient's guide in recognition of the fact that the best practice recommendations are lengthy and written primarily for a healthcare audience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CSS encourages provincial or territorial and regional stroke strategies to adopt the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt; in their entirety. While the process and speed of implementation will vary depending on circumstances, the vision of offering integrated, high quality, and efficient stroke services to all Canadians should be shared and supported across the country.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CSS disseminates the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care&lt;/em&gt; by:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Posting the recommendations on the Canadian Stroke Network Best Practicies website and other central guideline repository websites such as the World Stroke Organization website, the National Guideline Clearinghouse, the Internet Stroke Centre, and the Canadian Medical Association website &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Writing feature articles for publications such as the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Medical Association Journal&lt;/em&gt; and the Canadian Stroke Network &lt;em&gt;Brainwaves&lt;/em&gt; newsletter &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Alerting all contacts in the CSS database of Updates and how to access them &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Encouraging others to set up electronic links to the recommendations (e.g., Canadian Stroke Network, Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada, provincial stroke strategies) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Sharing details with all the CSS working groups to ensure alignment and collaboration in dissemination &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Engaging provincial stroke champions through presentations and discussion &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consulting other national guideline groups in related fields (e.g., hypertension, dyslipidemia, diabetes) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Presenting at national, provincial, and regional meetings of healthcare professionals across healthcare disciplines and across the continuum of stroke care &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Making presentations to front-line healthcare professionals at the local level and using local consensus processes to review and provide structured assessment of the enablers and barriers to guideline implementation, as well as innovative implementation strategies &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;E-mailing key stakeholders and front-line healthcare professionals working with persons with stroke and their families throughout the continuum of stroke care &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Highlighting specific recommendations in stroke-related newsletters such as the National Stroke Nursing Council's newsletter &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Disseminating the recommendations at international stroke meetings through the World Stroke Organization, the Guidelines International Network, and international partners and collaborators &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CSS encourages provincial or territorial and regional stroke strategy leaders to use these or other applicable approaches to further disseminate the recommendations and supporting tools to healthcare professionals, health system planners, decision-makers, and funders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools to Support Implementation of the Best Practice Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The national professional development and training platform of the CSS focuses on developing and implementing an integrated professional development and training plan for stroke professionals who care for patients, families, and caregivers. Professional development and training activities are carried out by a sub-group of the Best Practices and Standards Working Group, using a three-pronged approach that encompasses pre-professional education, professional development, and systems change.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Several point-of-care tools have been developed and are available through the websites of the CSN at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/&quot; title=&quot;CSN Web site&quot;&gt;www.strokebestpractices.ca&lt;/a&gt; and the Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.com&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada Web site&quot;&gt;www.heartandstroke.com&lt;/a&gt;. These tools address pre-hospital care, acute stroke care, stroke unit care, prevention, and long-term care (refer to Appendix 8 of the original guideline document for a list of professional development resources). The target audiences for each tool vary, but generally these tools are relevant to all interprofessional team members in a given setting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See the original guideline document for System Implication Categories and Performance Measures Development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Audit Criteria/Indicators" /><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Staff Training/Competency Material" /><FieldValue Value="Tool Kits" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /><FieldValue Value="Timeliness " /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Public awareness of stroke. In: Lindsay MP, Gubitz G, Bayley M, Hill MD, Davies-Schinkel C, Singh S, Phillips S, Canadian Stroke Strategy Best Practices and Standards Writing Group. Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. Ottawa (ON): Canadian Stroke Network; 2010 Dec 8. p. 17-20.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2006 (revised 2010 Dec 8)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="Canadian Stroke Network - Disease Specific Society" /><FieldValue Value="Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada - Disease Specific Society" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The development of these Canadian stroke care guidelines is funded in its entirety by the Canadian Stroke Strategy, a joint initiative of the Canadian Stroke Network and the Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada. The Canadian Stroke Strategy is funded primarily by the Canadian Stroke Network, which is in turn funded by the Networks of Centres of Excellence program.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No funds for the development of these guidelines come from commercial interests, including pharmaceutical companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Canadian Stroke Strategy Best Practices and Standards Working Group&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working Group Members&lt;/em&gt;: Stephen Phillips (&lt;em&gt;Co-Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Director, Acute Stroke Program, Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Centre, Nova Scotia; Mark Bayley (&lt;em&gt;Co-Chair&lt;/em&gt;), Physiatrist and Medical Director, Neuro Rehabilitation Program, Toronto Rehabilitation Institute, Ontario; Gord Gubitz, Lead, 2010 Best Practices Update; Neurologist, Acute Stroke Unit and Outpatient Neurovascular Clinic, Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Centre, Nova Scotia; Laurie Cameron, Program Coordinator &amp;amp; Executive Assistant, Canadian Stroke Strategy; Corrine Davies-Schinkel, Project Coordinator, Canadian Stroke Network; Michelle Edwards, Occupational Therapist, Foothills Medical Centre, Alberta; Ian Graham, Vice-President, Knowledge Translation, Canadian Institutes of Health Research; Mary Elizabeth Harriman, Associate Executive Director, Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada; Anthony Herd, CAEP Representative, Emergency Physician, Winnipeg Regional Health Authority, Manitoba; Linda Kelloway, Best Practices Lead, Ontario Stroke Network, Ontario; Katie Lafferty, Executive Director, Canadian Stroke Network; Louise-H&amp;eacute;l&amp;egrave;ne LeBrun, Directeur du Centre des maladies vasculairesc&amp;eacute;r&amp;eacute;brales du CHUM, Centre Hospitalier de l'Universit&amp;eacute; de Montr&amp;eacute;al (CHUM), Quebec; Patrice Lindsay, Staff Lead, Director of Performance and Standards, Canadian Stroke Network; Samantha Singh, Project Coordinator, Canadian Stroke Network; Elizabeth Woodbury, Executive Director, Canadian Stroke Strategy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants in the development and review process are required to sign confidentiality agreements and to declare all potential conflicts of interest in writing. Only seven out of 143 participants declared a minor conflict such as receipt of honoraria to speak about stroke in other venues. None of these conflicts were deemed to prevent unbiased participation in the process. The recommendations were approved following a rigorous development process and through a consensus of independent experts and stakeholders, thereby minimizing the potential influence of any one participant. See Appendices 1, 2, 3, and 4 in the original guideline document for complete statements of competing interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: Lindsay P, Bayley M, Hellings C, Hill M, Woodbury E, Phillips S. Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. CMAJ 2008 Dec 2;179(12 Suppl).&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care include an ongoing plan to formally update the recommendations every 2 years to ensure that the best practice recommendations remain current and are coordinated with other similar initiatives nationally and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/2010BPR_ENG.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/2010BPR_FRENCH.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care: 2008 toolkit. Available in English and French from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.on.ca/site/c.pvI3IeNWJwE/b.5398033/k.2C15/Canadian_Best_Practices_Workshop.htm&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&quot;&gt;Heart &amp;amp; Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Secondary prevention best practice workshop tool kit: preventing strokes one at a time. Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.on.ca/site/c.pvI3IeNWJwE/b.5882219/k.48F5/Secondary_Prevention_Tool_Kit.htm&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&quot;&gt;Heart &amp;amp; Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Acute stroke management workshop. Available in English and French from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.on.ca/site/c.pvI3IeNWJwE/b.5346923/k.8D25/HCP__English.htm&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&quot;&gt;Heart &amp;amp; Stroke Foundation of Ontario Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care: educational workshop for emergency medical care of suspected acute care patients. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) in &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS_EMS-Stroke-Wksp_FINAL.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS_EMS_fr.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Canadian Stroke Strategy performance measurement manual: a supplement to the Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. 2008 May. 48 p. Electronic copies: Available in PDF in &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS-Performance-Manual-2008_EN.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS-Performance-Manuel-2008_FR.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Canadian Stroke Strategy core performance indicator update 2010. 2010 Jun. 8 p. Electronic copies: Available in PDF in &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Stroke_Core_ENG.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Stroke_Core_FRE.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A guide to the implementation of stroke unit care. A resource for implementation of Canadian Best Practice Recommendations for Stroke Care. 2009 Dec. 24 p. Available in PDF in &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS-Stroke-Unit-Resource_EN-Final2-for-print.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/CSS-Stroke-Unit-Resource_FR3-Final-for-print.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additional resources are available in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/index.php/resources/&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/index.php/resources/?lang=fr&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Best Practices Web site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A patient's guide to Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care. 2011. 8 p. Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/CSN_PatientsGuide2011_English_WEB11.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/CSN_PatientsGuide2011_French_WEB21.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Best Practices Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Getting on with the rest of your life after stroke: a guide for patients and their families. 68 p. Electronic copies: Available in PDF in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/GettingOn2-EN.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/French-Getting-On.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;A family guide to pediatric stroke. 2011. 34 p. Electronic copies: Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/PEDSGuide-EN.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Best Practices Web site&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strokebestpractices.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/PEDSGuide-FR.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Canadian Stroke Network Best Practices Web site&quot;&gt;French&lt;/a&gt; from the Canadian Stroke Network Best Practices Web site. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a variety of patient information resources, including a list of stroke warning signs, is available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heartandstroke.com/site/c.ikIQLcMWJtE/b.3483933/&quot; title=&quot;Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada Web site&quot;&gt;Heart &amp;amp; Stroke Foundation of Canada Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI Institute on July 7, 2008. The information was verified by the guideline developer on August 27, 2008. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 20, 2009. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on December 1, 2011. The updated information was verified by the guideline developer on January 9, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary is based on the original guideline, which is subject to the guideline developer's copyright restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
