<Version><xmlsource>This XML content was developed by AHRQ's contractor ECRI Institute for the National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC).</xmlsource><Section SecID="390" OrdBy="100" Name="General"><Field FieldID="161" OrdBy="105" ID="391" Name="Guideline Title" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_title&quot;&gt;Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010.&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="110" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010. Washington (DC): U.S. Government Printing Office; 2010 Dec. 99 p. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="115" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture. Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2005. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2005. 84 p.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field Name ="UMLS Concepts"><FieldValue Value="ICD9CM: Cardiovascular disease, unspecified  (429.2); Complications affecting other specified body systems, not elsewhere classified, hypertension  (997.91); Constipation, unspecified  (564.00); Diabetes with other coma, type II or unspecified type, not stated as uncontrolled  (250.30); Eating disorder, unspecified  (307.50); Iron deficiency anemia, unspecified  (280.9); Obesity, unspecified  (278.00); Osteoporosis, unspecified  (733.00); Overweight  (278.02); Unspecified nutritional deficiency  (269.9)"/><FieldValue Value="MSH: Anemia, Iron-Deficiency ; Breast Feeding ; Calcium, Dietary ; Cardiovascular Diseases ; Chronic Disease ; Constipation ; Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2 ; Diet ; Diet Therapy ; Diet, Fat-Restricted ; Diet, Sodium-Restricted ; Dietary Fiber ; Dyslipidemias ; Eating Disorders ; Elder Nutritional Physiological Phenomena ; Food Safety ; Hypertension ; Malnutrition ; Motor Activity ; Neoplasms ; Nutrition Assessment ; Nutritional Physiological Phenomena ; Obesity ; Osteoporosis ; Overweight ; Potassium, Dietary ; Pregnancy ; Vitamin D "/><FieldValue Value="MTH: Breast Feeding ; Calcium, Dietary ; Cardiovascular Diseases ; Cholesterol-lowering diet (finding) ; Chronic disease ; Constipation ; Diabetes Mellitus, Non-Insulin-Dependent ; Diet ; Diet therapy ; Dietary Fiber ; Dietary Potassium ; Eating Disorders ; Fat-Restricted Diet ; Hypertensive disease ; Iron deficiency anemia ; Low sodium diet ; Malignant Neoplasms ; Malnutrition ; Neoplasms ; Nutrition Assessment ; Obesity ; Osteoporosis ; OVERWEIGHT ; Physical activity ; Pregnancy ; Vitamin D ; Weight maintenance regimen "/><FieldValue Value="PDQ: cancer ; malnutrition ; obesity ; osteoporosis "/><FieldValue Value="SNOMEDCT_US: Assessment of nutritional status  (1759002); Assessment of nutritional status  (310243009); Breast fed  (169741004); Cholesterol-lowering diet  (160672004); Chronic disease  (27624003); Constipation  (129585003); Constipation  (14760008); Diet good  (226234005); Diet good  (310500000); Diet poor  (310502008); Dietary fats and oils  (226887002); Dietary fiber  (116272000); Dietary finding  (41829006); Disorder of cardiovascular system  (49601007); Dyslipidemia  (370992007); Eating disorder  (72366004); Hypertensive disorder  (38341003); Iron deficiency anemia  (87522002); Low cholesterol-low saturated fat diet  (39545002); Low fat diet  (16208003); Low fat diet  (436861000124104); Low sodium diet  (386619000); Low sodium diet  (437421000124105); Malignant neoplastic disease  (363346000); Neoplasm  (108369006); Obesity  (414915002); Obesity  (414916001); Oil - dietary  (226905009); Osteoporosis  (64859006); Overweight  (238131007); Physical activity  (48761009); Physical activity  (68130003); Pregnancy  (289908002); Type 2 diabetes mellitus  (44054006); Undernutrition  (248325000); Undernutrition  (47563007); Undernutrition  (65404009); Undernutrition  (70241007); Vitamin D  (11563006); Vitamin D  (30178006); Weight maintenance regimen  (388962008)"/></Field></Section><Section SecID="396" OrdBy="300" Name="Scope"><Field FieldID="140" OrdBy="305" ID="397" Name="Disease/Condition(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Overall health &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Chronic diseases and conditions linked to a poor diet or physical inactivity including:&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Cardiovascular disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Hypertension &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Type 2 diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Osteoporosis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Some types of cancer &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Overweight and obesity &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="103" OrdBy="310" ID="398" Name="Guideline Category" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Prevention" /></Field><Field FieldID="113" OrdBy="315" ID="399" Name="Clinical Specialty" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Family Practice" /><FieldValue Value="Geriatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Internal Medicine" /><FieldValue Value="Nutrition" /><FieldValue Value="Obstetrics and Gynecology" /><FieldValue Value="Pediatrics" /><FieldValue Value="Preventive Medicine" /></Field><Field FieldID="114" OrdBy="320" ID="400" Name="Intended Users" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Advanced Practice Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Dietitians" /><FieldValue Value="Health Care Providers" /><FieldValue Value="Nurses" /><FieldValue Value="Physicians" /><FieldValue Value="Public Health Departments" /></Field><Field FieldID="129" OrdBy="325" ID="401" Name="Guideline Objective(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To promote eating and physical activity patterns that are focused on consuming fewer calories, making informed food choices, and being physically active, which can help people attain and maintain a healthy weight, reduce the risk of chronic disease, and promote overall health &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To summarize and synthesize knowledge regarding individual nutrients and food components into an interrelated set of recommendations for healthy eating that can be adopted by the public &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To maximize the nutritional content of meals of those who are unable to acquire adequate food to meet their needs &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To promote health and help to decrease the risk of chronic diseases, and prevent foodborne illness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;To improve the health of our Nation's current and future generations by facilitating and promoting healthy eating and physical activity choices so that these behaviors become the norm among all individuals &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="132" OrdBy="330" ID="402" Name="Target Population" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;All Americans aged 2 years and older, including those at increased risk of chronic disease&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="133" OrdBy="335" ID="403" Name="Interventions and Practices Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ol style=&quot;list-style-type: decimal;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Balancing calories to manage weight (calorie intake and physical activity) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reducing certain foods and food components (sodium, saturated fatty acids, cholesterol, trans fats, refined grains, sugar, alcohol) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increasing certain foods and nutrients (fruits, vegetables, whole grains, fat-free or low-fat milk, protein, seafood, oils, potassium, dietary fiber, calcium, and vitamin D)&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Considerations for women capable of becoming pregnant &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Considerations for women who are pregnant or breastfeeding &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Considerations for individuals aged 50 and older &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Building healthy eating patterns, including precautions for food safety &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="134" OrdBy="340" ID="404" Name="Major Outcomes Considered" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Rates of overweight and obesity (weight management) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Rates of premature (early) death &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incidence of cancers &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Occurrence of diseases&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Coronary heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Type 2 diabetes &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;Osteoporosis &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Diet-related health outcomes and overall health &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Incidence of foodborne illness &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Risk factors for disease&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;High blood pressure &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;li&gt;High blood cholesterol &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="405" OrdBy="400" Name="Methodology"><Field FieldID="109" OrdBy="405" ID="406" Name="Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Primary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Hand-searches of Published Literature (Secondary Sources)" /><FieldValue Value="Searches of Electronic Databases" /></Field><Field FieldID="135" OrdBy="410" ID="407" Name="Description of Methods Used to Collect/Select the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee (DGAC) subcommittee generated a list of topic areas to explore to update the 2005 Dietary Guidelines. These lists were based on the evolution of the science, public comment received, and whether controversy existed about a given topic or guideline. After developing an initial list of research questions, the subcommittees set priorities for questions to be answered using the Nutrition Evidence Library (NEL) systematic review methodology. The wording and intent of specific questions evolved and additional questions were considered in an iterative process. Frequently, multiple questions were needed to fully address a topic of interest. This cluster of questions was referred to as a &quot;family of questions.&quot; Limitations in time and resources prevented the review of all questions using the NEL systematic review methodology.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As needed, NEL staff conducted exploratory literature searches and developed analytical frameworks to assist Committee members in framing NEL systematic review questions. The scope of topic areas addressed was very broad, so subcommittee members were required to make critical decisions related to the comprehensiveness of reviews, such as determining literature search date ranges. Any available systematic reviews (e.g., 2009 Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality [AHRQ] report &lt;em&gt;Vitamin D and Calcium: A Systematic Review of Health Outcomes)&lt;/em&gt; or reports based on systematic reviews (e.g., &lt;em&gt;Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee Report, 2008&lt;/em&gt;) that were deemed to be current and comprehensive representations of available literature were not duplicated by the NEL team. Results from the 2007 &lt;em&gt;World Cancer Research Fund/American Institute for Cancer Research; Food, Nutrition, Physical Activity, and the Prevention of Cancer: A Global Perspective&lt;/em&gt; report were used to substantiate recommendations related to food, nutrient, and diet intake and cancer-related outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature Search and Sort Plans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A method, referred to as PICO, was used to identify the Population or Participants, Intervention (or Exposure in observational studies), Comparator, and Outcomes of interest to be addressed by a specific question or family of questions. The PICO method aided the generation of a literature search and sort plan, which defined the eligibility criteria for studies selected for inclusion in each systematic review. All searches were limited to human studies, developed countries, English language, and peer-reviewed publications. Unpublished data, including abstracts and conference proceedings, were not included. General eligibility criteria included factors, such as:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Age &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Health status of subjects (inclusion of subjects with type 2 diabetes or other prevalent chronic diseases varied by topic) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study setting &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Number of subjects per study arm (typically a minimum of 10 subjects per study arm) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Attrition rate (typically less than 20 percent; rate was modified for long-term studies) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Characteristics of the intervention (e.g., dose or duration of intervention, food based nutrients) &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Outcome measures and timing of measures &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Study design &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The subcommittees tailored inclusion and exclusion criteria by question or family of questions. Each subcommittee carefully considered the date range from which to extract the evidence, based upon whether the systematic review was designed to update 2005 &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines&lt;/em&gt;, update a comprehensive systematic review, or examine an area not previously addressed by the &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines&lt;/em&gt;. Many searches initially included all study designs. However, for a number of questions, cross-sectional studies were eventually excluded from review when sufficient evidence from studies with a stronger design was available.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Existing systematic reviews were frequently incorporated into the portfolio of evidence used to answer a question. Comprehensive systematic reviews, with well-documented methodology and rigorous criteria for judging methodological quality of included studies and grading the body of evidence, were occasionally selected to serve as a baseline for a review in cases where the seminal research on a question was considered to be &quot;settled science.&quot; Numerous published systematic reviews conducted by the American Dietetic Association were updated for this report, using DGAC criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The committee used an iterative, step-wise process to determine which research designs were considered to examine a question. Study designs included intervention trials, observational studies, ecological studies, systematic reviews, and meta-analyses. If systematic reviews were used, primary studies included in these reviews were excluded. If multiple systematic reviews considered an overlapping body of primary studies, this was noted in the evidence summary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each search and sort plan specified the databases and search terms used to guide the search. PubMed/Medline and the Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews were searched for all of the NEL systematic review questions, supplemented by BIOSIS, CAB Abstracts, Food Science &amp;amp; Technology Abstracts, Scopus, ScienceDirect, Embase, Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries Abstracts, Fish and Fisheries Worldwide, and AGRICOLA, as dictated by the question topics. A wide variety of search terms and key words were used, including subject headings such as MeSH and thesauri terms. Because some databases do not have full text search capabilities, key word/subject terms searches were limited to certain fields (e.g., titles and abstracts), which may have limited identification of potentially relevant articles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Electronic searches were augmented by hand searches of references from primary and review articles, as well as articles identified for consideration by committee members. If new search terms were identified, the electronic searches were rerun to ensure completeness of the search. The Committee monitored the search process including review of the search terms and results. The search was expanded or modified based on their feedback and knowledge of the field.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selecting the Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The literature search plan was implemented collaboratively by the research librarian, the NEL nutrition scientist staff, and the DGAC members. The research librarian conducted a title screen and identified abstracts to be reviewed by the NEL staff. All abstracts identified by the research librarian were evaluated by the NEL staff, in accordance with criteria outlined in the search and sort plan. Articles that potentially met the eligibility criteria were reviewed in full-text version. Two lists were compiled for review by subcommittee members: a list of citations meeting the inclusion criteria and a list of citations recommended for exclusion (with the specific rationale for exclusion noted). When an article could not be clearly included or excluded based on the eligibility criteria, it was highlighted for subcommittee review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once the subcommittee reached agreement on the final list of articles to be included in the review, the NEL staff assigned each included manuscript to a National Service Volunteer to prepare an evidence worksheet. Information on the search terms used, search date, number of included and excluded citations identified by the search, final list of included citations, and a table with the excluded citations, including reason for exclusion, are provided in the NEL, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nutritionevidencelibrary.com&quot; title=&quot;Nutrition Evidence Library Web site&quot;&gt;www.nutritionevidencelibrary.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="136" OrdBy="415" ID="408" Name="Number of Source Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="115" OrdBy="420" ID="409" Name="Methods Used to Assess the Quality and Strength of the Evidence" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /><FieldValue Value="Weighting According to a Rating Scheme (Scheme Given)" /></Field><Field FieldID="149" OrdBy="425" ID="410" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Strength of the Evidence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong evidence&lt;/strong&gt; reflects consistent, convincing findings derived from studies with robust methodology relevant to the population of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderate evidence&lt;/strong&gt; reflects somewhat less evidence or less consistent evidence. The body of evidence may include studies of weaker design and/or some inconsistency in results. The studies may be susceptible to some bias, but not enough to invalidate the results, or the body of evidence may not be as generalizable to the population of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limited evidence&lt;/strong&gt; reflects either a small number of studies, studies of weak design, and/or inconsistent results.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The complete conclusion grading chart used to grade the strength of the body of evidence supporting conclusion statements can be found in Table C1 of the Report of the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee on the Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010 (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="116" OrdBy="430" ID="411" Name="Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Review of Published Meta-Analyses" /><FieldValue Value="Systematic Review with Evidence Tables" /></Field><Field FieldID="150" OrdBy="435" ID="412" Name="Description of the Methods Used to Analyze the Evidence" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical Review of Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;National Service Volunteers, a cadre of highly qualified nutrition and health professionals, were trained and served as evidence abstractors to support the systematic review process. They: (1) classified the study by design type; (2) extracted key evidence from each individual study into a comprehensive, templated evidence worksheet (made available to committee members and posted on the Nutrition Evidence Library [NEL]); and (3) applied predefined criteria from Research Design and Implementation Checklists for each primary research study and review study to critically appraise the methodological quality of the study. Evidence abstractors received training on how to apply the criteria to studies differing in design.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Each study received a quality rating of positive, neutral, or negative, based upon a predefined scoring system (these quality grades are available for each article in the NEL). In the chapter text, for clarity, these ratings are described as studies which are methodologically strong (positive), methodologically neutral (neutral), and methodologically weak (negative). The appraisal of study quality is a critical component of the systematic review methodology because in a highly transparent manner, it indicates the Committee's judgment regarding the relevance (external validity/generalizability) and validity of each study's results. This rating, referred to as the &quot;quality rating,&quot; indicates the extent to which the design and conduct of a study is shown to be protected from systematic bias, nonsystematic bias, and inferential error. Studies were not excluded on the basis of quality rating. However, the quality rating was taken into consideration by the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee (DGAC) as they reviewed the literature and formed conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summaries of the Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The NEL staff drafted evidence summary paragraphs and evidence tables for all included articles on a question or family of questions to aid analysis and synthesis of the complete body of evidence. These paragraphs and tables provided key information about the study design, quality rating, study subjects, the intervention or exposure, comparators, and key outcomes. Using this information, and going back to the original articles when necessary, Committee members then drafted an evidence overview summary, which included an overall summary statement, comparison of findings between studies, discussion of relevant issues related to methodologies used, and definitions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formulating and Grading the Conclusion Statement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The final step in the DGAC's systematic review process was writing and grading a Conclusion statement, based upon the body of scientific evidence evaluated. This step was characterized by careful consideration of the qualitative and quantitative findings. Each Conclusion statement briefly answered the research question, focusing on the general agreement among studies. When the evidence addressed only one sex, age group, ethnicity, or level of health risk, such as children or subjects without cardiovascular disease, this was reflected in the Conclusion statement. Conclusions also included a statement regarding distinct subgroups, if findings for that population were different than for the overall conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Developing and grading each Conclusion was a deliberative and time-consuming process that benefited from group interaction. The strength of the evidence supporting the conclusion statement was graded using the DGAC's predetermined criteria, which assessed the quality (relevance and validity) and size of the studies, the quantity of studies, the consistency and agreement across studies, the generalizability to the population of interest, and the magnitude of the effect or public health impact. Each subcommittee deliberated on each Conclusion statement and grade, and proposed Conclusions and grades were then brought to the full Committee for consideration and discussion. Due to the challenge of grading such a broad range of conclusions within one report, the Committee decided to use the following qualitative word grades rather than numerical grades: Strong; Moderate; Limited; Expert Opinion; Grade Not Assignable.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For some research questions, the DGAC's systematic review generated recommendations for future research.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use of the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) Food Patterns for Special Analyses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The 2010 DGAC identified specific questions that they felt could best be addressed through a food pattern modeling approach, using the USDA food patterns and the modeling process developed to address similar requests by the 2005 DGAC.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Briefly, the USDA food patterns describe types and amounts of food to consume that will provide a nutritionally satisfactory diet. They include recommended intakes for five major food groups and for subgroups within several of the groups. They also recommend an allowance for intake of oils and limits on intake of calories from solid fats and added sugars. The calories and nutrients that would be expected from consuming a specified amount from each component of the patterns are determined by calculating nutrient profiles. A nutrient profile is the consumption-weighted average nutrient content for nutrient-dense forms of foods within each group. These nutrient profiles can be modified based on the assumptions for each food pattern modeling analysis. Additional details on the USDA food patterns can be found in the report for the food pattern modeling analysis, Adequacy of the USDA Food Patterns, which is available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A food pattern modeling process was developed for and used by the 2005 DGAC to determine the hypothetical impact on nutrients in and adequacy of the food patterns when specific changes are made. The structure of the USDA food patterns allows for modifications that test the overall impact on diet quality of various dietary recommendation scenarios. Most analyses involved identifying the impact of specific changes in amounts or types of foods that might be recommended by the Committee or selected by consumers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Five 2010 DGAC subcommittees identified a total of 18 questions that they felt could be addressed through food pattern modeling. Several questions were merged or dropped, resulting in 12 modeling analyses that were completed and provided as reports to the relevant subcommittees. For each question, a specific approach was drafted by USDA staff and provided to the subcommittee for comment. After the approach was discussed and accepted, USDA staff completed the analytical work and drafted a full report for the subcommittee's consideration. Each report was discussed by the relevant subcommittee, and the analysis and report were revised as needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="112" OrdBy="440" ID="413" Name="Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="Expert Consensus" /></Field><Field FieldID="145" OrdBy="445" ID="414" Name="Description of Methods Used to Formulate the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Committee Appointment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Beginning with the 1985 edition, the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) and U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) have appointed a Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee (DGAC) of prominent experts in nutrition and health to assist in preparing the &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans&lt;/em&gt;. This Committee has been an effective mechanism for obtaining a comprehensive review of the science, recommendations from experts, and broad public acceptance of the &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines&lt;/em&gt;. The 2010 DGAC was established for the single, time-limited task of reviewing the 2005 edition of &lt;em&gt;Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans&lt;/em&gt; and determining whether, on the basis of current scientific and medical knowledge, revision was warranted. The Committee determined that a revision was needed and developed nutrition and health recommendations in this Advisory Report to the Secretaries of USDA and HHS. The Committee was dissolved upon delivery of this report.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Committee Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The 13-member Committee served without pay and worked under the regulations of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (FACA). The Committee held six public meetings in Washington, DC over the course of 1&amp;frac12; years. Meetings were held in October 2008; January, April, and November 2009; and April and May 2010. Members of the general public were able to attend the Committee's first two meetings in person in Washington, DC. For the remaining meetings, members of the public were able to participate by webinar. All meetings were announced in the &lt;em&gt;Federal Register&lt;/em&gt;. Meeting minutes and transcripts were posted for each meeting at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;. Archived recordings of the third through sixth meetings were made available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;. All documents pertaining to Committee deliberations were made available for public viewing at the first two meetings, and thereafter, were made available through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt; and at the National Agricultural Library Reference Desk.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Written public comments were received throughout the Committee's deliberations through a newly developed electronic database designed for collecting public comments. This database allowed for the generation of public comment reports as a result of a query by key topic areas. Comments received on and before April 29, 2010, were compiled into these reports and shared with all Committee members. A general description of the types of comments received and the process used for collecting public comments is described in &lt;em&gt;Appendix E-5. Public Comments&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;Report of the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee on the Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010&lt;/em&gt; (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). Comments can be viewed by the public at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;. In response to a solicitation for oral comments, 51 of the 58 organizations or individuals who registered presented oral testimony during the January 29-30, 2009, meeting of the Committee. These comments are summarized in the January Public Meeting Minutes at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guielines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Committee used a newly developed, state-of-the-art, web-based electronic system and methodology to address the majority of the science-based research questions posed by the Committee. These reviews are publicly available in the Nutrition Evidence Library (NEL) at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nutritionevidencelibrary.com&quot; title=&quot;Nutrition Evidence Library Web site&quot;&gt;www.nutritionevidencelibrary.com&lt;/a&gt;. Remaining questions were answered by data analyses, modeling analyses, and consideration of other evidence-based reviews or existing reports, such as the 2008 edition of the &lt;em&gt;Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans&lt;/em&gt;. Topic areas that were addressed for this report were similar to those for the 2005 &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines&lt;/em&gt;, but this new methodology and web-based system allowed the Committee to ask and process more questions in a systematic, transparent, evidence-based manner. These research questions were developed and assessed by seven subcommittees: Energy Balance and Weight Management; Nutrient Adequacy; Fatty Acids and Cholesterol; Carbohydrates and Protein; Sodium, Potassium, and Water; Alcohol (initially called Ethanol); and Food Safety and Technology. One main difference from 2005 was that protein was added as a topic area, thus resulting in the Carbohydrates and Protein subcommittee. Food technology was also added as a topic area and was incorporated into the Food Safety and Technology subcommittee. Each subcommittee was made up of three to five Committee members, with one Committee member appointed as the lead. Although the lead member was responsible for communicating and coordinating all the work that needed to be accomplished within the subcommittees, draft conclusions reached on the scientific evidence reviewed, ultimately reflected the consensus of the entire Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more information on the committee process, refer to the &quot;Methodology&quot; section of the &lt;em&gt;Report of the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee on the Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010&lt;/em&gt; (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="146" OrdBy="450" ID="415" Name="Rating Scheme for the Strength of the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="148" OrdBy="460" ID="417" Name="Cost Analysis" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal cost analysis was not performed and published cost analyses were not reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="104" OrdBy="465" ID="418" Name="Method of Guideline Validation" Type="picklist-choice"><FieldValue Value="External Peer Review" /></Field><Field FieldID="130" OrdBy="470" ID="419" Name="Description of Method of Guideline Validation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written public comments were received throughout the Committee's deliberations through a newly developed electronic database designed for collecting public comments. This database allowed for the generation of public comment reports as a result of a query by key topic areas. Comments received on and before April 29, 2010, were compiled into these reports and shared with all Committee members. A general description of the types of comments received and the process used for collecting public comments is described in Appendix E-5 of the &lt;em&gt;Report of the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee on the Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010&lt;/em&gt; (see the &quot;Availability of Companion Documents&quot; field). Public Comments. Comments can be viewed by the public at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;. In response to a solicitation for oral comments, 51 of the 58 organizations or individuals who registered presented oral testimony during the January 29-30, 2009, meeting of the Committee. These comments are summarized in the January Public Meeting Minutes at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dietaryguidelines.gov&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dietaryguidelines.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Members of an Independent Scientific Review Panel peer reviewed the recommendations of the document to ensure they were based on the preponderance of the scientific evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="420" OrdBy="500" Name="Recommendations"><Field FieldID="151" OrdBy="505" ID="421" Name="Major Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Balancing Calories to Manage Weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Prevent and/or reduce overweight and obesity through improved eating and physical activity behaviors. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Control total calorie intake to manage body weight. For people who are overweight or obese, this will mean consuming fewer calories from foods and beverages. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increase physical activity and reduce time spent in sedentary behaviors. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Maintain appropriate calorie balance during each stage of life&amp;mdash;childhood, adolescence, adulthood, pregnancy and breastfeeding, and older age. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Foods and Food Components to Reduce&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reduce daily sodium intake to less than 2,300 milligrams (mg) and further reduce intake to 1,500 mg among persons who are 51 and older and those of any age who are African American or have hypertension, diabetes, or chronic kidney disease. The 1,500 mg recommendation applies to about half of the U.S. population, including children, and the majority of adults. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume less than 10 percent of calories from saturated fatty acids by replacing them with monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fatty acids. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume less than 300 mg per day of dietary cholesterol. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Keep trans fatty acid consumption as low as possible by limiting foods that contain synthetic sources of trans fats, such as partially hydrogenated oils, and by limiting other solid fats. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Reduce the intake of calories from solid fats and added sugars. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Limit the consumption of foods that contain refined grains, especially refined grain foods that contain solid fats, added sugars, and sodium. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;If alcohol is consumed, it should be consumed in moderation&amp;mdash;up to one drink per day for women and two drinks per day for men&amp;mdash;and only by adults of legal drinking age.* &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;* See Chapter 3 in the original guideline document, Foods and Food Components to Reduce, for additional recommendations on alcohol consumption and specific population groups. There are many circumstances when people should not drink alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Foods and Nutrients to Increase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Individuals should meet the following recommendations as part of a healthy eating pattern while staying within their calorie needs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increase vegetable and fruit intake. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Eat a variety of vegetables, especially dark-green and red and orange vegetables and beans and peas. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume at least half of all grains as whole grains. Increase whole-grain intake by replacing refined grains with whole grains. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increase intake of fat-free or low-fat milk and milk products, such as milk, yogurt, cheese, or fortified soy beverages.** &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Choose a variety of protein foods, which include seafood, lean meat and poultry, eggs, beans and peas, soy products, and unsalted nuts and seeds. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Increase the amount and variety of seafood consumed by choosing seafood in place of some meat and poultry. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Replace protein foods that are higher in solid fats with choices that are lower in solid fats and calories and/or are sources of oils. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Use oils to replace solid fats where possible. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Choose foods that provide more potassium, dietary fiber, calcium, and vitamin D, which are nutrients of concern in American diets. These foods include vegetables, fruits, whole grains, and milk and milk products. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;** Fortified soy beverages have been marketed as &quot;soymilk,&quot; a product name consumers could see in supermarkets and consumer materials. However, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration's (FDA's) regulations do not contain provisions for the use of the term soymilk. Therefore, in this document, the term &quot;fortified soy beverage&quot; includes products that may be marketed as soymilk.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations for Specific Population Groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Women Capable of Becoming Pregnant&amp;dagger;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Choose foods that supply heme iron, which is more readily absorbed by the body, additional iron sources, and enhancers of iron absorption such as vitamin C-rich foods. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume 400 micrograms (mcg) per day of synthetic folic acid (from fortified foods and/or supplements) in addition to food forms of folate from a varied diet.&amp;Dagger; &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Women Who are Pregnant or Breastfeeding&amp;dagger;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume 8 to 12 ounces of seafood per week from a variety of seafood types. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Due to their high methyl mercury content, limit white (albacore) tuna to 6 ounces per week and do not eat the following four types of fish: tilefish, shark, swordfish, and king mackerel. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;If pregnant, take an iron supplement, as recommended by an obstetrician or other health care provider. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&amp;dagger; Includes adolescent girls.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&amp;Dagger; &quot;Folic acid&quot; is the synthetic form of the nutrient; whereas, &quot;folate&quot; is the form found naturally in foods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individuals Ages 50 Years and Older&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Consume foods fortified with vitamin B12, such as fortified cereals, or dietary supplements. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Building Healthy Eating Patterns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Select an eating pattern that meets nutrient needs over time at an appropriate calorie level. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Account for all foods and beverages consumed and assess how they fit within a total healthy eating pattern. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Follow food safety recommendations when preparing and eating foods to reduce the risk of food borne illnesses. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="138" OrdBy="515" ID="423" Name="Clinical Algorithm(s)" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;None provided&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="424" OrdBy="600" Name="Evidence Supporting the Recommendations"><Field FieldID="139" OrdBy="610" ID="426" Name="Type of Evidence Supporting the Recommendations" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of evidence supporting the recommendations is not specifically stated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="427" OrdBy="700" Name="Benefits/Harms of Implementing the Guideline Recommendations"><Field FieldID="152" OrdBy="705" ID="428" Name="Potential Benefits" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A growing body of scientific evidence demonstrates that the dietary and physical activity recommendations described in the &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans&lt;/em&gt; may help people attain and maintain a healthy weight, reduce the risk of chronic disease, and promote overall health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="153" OrdBy="710" ID="429" Name="Potential Harms" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not stated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="434" OrdBy="1000" Name="Implementation of the Guideline"><Field FieldID="131" OrdBy="1010" ID="436" Name="Description of Implementation Strategy" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of Educational Materials and Communications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The information in this edition of &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans&lt;/em&gt; is used in developing nutrition education and communication messages and materials. For example, Federal dietary guidance publications are required by law to be consistent with the Dietary Guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of Nutrition-Related Programs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Dietary Guidelines aid policymakers in designing and implementing nutrition-related programs. For example, the Federal Government uses the Dietary Guidelines in developing nutrition assistance programs such as the National Child Nutrition Programs and the Elderly Nutrition Program. The Dietary Guidelines also provide the foundation for the Healthy People national health promotion and disease prevention objectives related to nutrition, which set measurable targets for achievement over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of Authoritative Statements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010&lt;/em&gt; has the potential to offer authoritative statements as a basis for health and nutrient content claims, as provided for in the Food and Drug Administration Modernization Act (FDAMA). Potential authoritative statements should be phrased in a manner that enables consumers to understand the claim in the context of the total daily diet. FDAMA upholds the &quot;significant scientific agreement&quot; standard for authorized health claims. By law, this standard is based on the totality of publicly available scientific evidence. Therefore, for FDAMA purposes, statements based on, for example, evidence that is moderate, limited, inconsistent, emerging, or growing, are not authoritative statements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="117" OrdBy="1015" ID="437" Name="Implementation Tools" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Foreign Language Translations" /><FieldValue Value="Patient Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Quick Reference Guides/Physician Guides" /><FieldValue Value="Resources" /><FieldValue Value="Slide Presentation" /><FieldValue Value="Staff Training/Competency Material" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="439" OrdBy="1100" Name="Institute of Medicine (IOM) National Healthcare Quality Report Categories"><Field FieldID="50" OrdBy="1105" ID="440" Name="IOM Care Need" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Staying Healthy" /></Field><Field FieldID="51" OrdBy="1110" ID="441" Name="IOM Domain" Type="picklist-many"><FieldValue Value="Effectiveness" /><FieldValue Value="Patient-centeredness" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="442" OrdBy="1200" Name="Identifying Information and Availability"><Field FieldID="97" OrdBy="1201" ID="392" Name="Bibliographic Source(s)" Type="citation"><FieldValue Value="&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010. Washington (DC): U.S. Government Printing Office; 2010 Dec. 99 p. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="124" OrdBy="1205" ID="443" Name="Adaptation" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not applicable: The guideline was not adapted from another source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="128" OrdBy="1215" ID="445" Name="Date Released" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="2005 (revised 2010 Dec)" /></Field><Field FieldID="158" OrdBy="1225" ID="447" Name="Guideline Developer(s)" Type="orglist-p"><FieldValue Value="Department of Agriculture (U.S.) - Federal Government Agency [U.S.]" /><FieldValue Value="Department of Health and Human Services (U.S.) - Federal Government Agency [U.S.]" /></Field><Field FieldID="125" OrdBy="1235" ID="449" Name="Source(s) of Funding" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;United States Government&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="126" OrdBy="1240" ID="450" Name="Guideline Committee" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="127" OrdBy="1245" ID="451" Name="Composition of Group That Authored the Guideline" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee Members&lt;/em&gt;: Linda Van Horn, PhD, RD, LD; Naomi K. Fukagawa, MD, PhD; Cheryl Achterberg, PhD; Lawrence J. Appel, MD, MPH; Roger A. Clemens, DrPH; Miriam E. Nelson, PhD; Sharon (Shelly) M. Nickols-Richardson, PhD, RD; Thomas A. Pearson, MD, PhD, MPH; Rafael P&amp;eacute;rez-Escamilla, PhD; F. Xavier Pi-Sunyer, MD, MPH; Eric B. Rimm, ScD; Joanne L. Slavin, PhD, RD; Christine L. Williams, MD, MPH&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="147" OrdBy="1250" ID="452" Name="Financial Disclosures/Conflicts of Interest" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 13-member Committee served without pay and worked under the regulations of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (FACA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="120" OrdBy="1256" ID="393" Name="Guideline Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the current release of the guideline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This guideline updates a previous version: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture. Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2005. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2005. 84 p.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="118" OrdBy="1260" ID="454" Name="Guideline Availability" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic copies: Available from the United States Department of Agriculture Center for Nutrition Policy and Promotion &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/dietaryguidelines.htm&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="119" OrdBy="1265" ID="455" Name="Availability of Companion Documents" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Report of the Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee on the Dietary Guidelines for Americans, 2010. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2010. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/DGAs2010-DGACReport.htm&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010. Executive summary. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2010. 4 p. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/Publications/DietaryGuidelines/2010/PolicyDoc/ExecSumm.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010. Slide presentation. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2010. Available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/DGAs2010-SlidePresentation.htm&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dietary guidelines for Americans, 2010. Continuing Professional Education (CPE) activity available from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/Publications/DietaryGuidelines/2010/CPEcredit.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;USDA 2010 dietary guidelines communications message calendar. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture; 2011 Jun. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/Publications/DietaryGuidelines/2010/DGCommunicationsMessageCalendar.pdf&quot; title=&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dietary Guidelines for Americans Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="143" OrdBy="1275" ID="457" Name="Patient Resources" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following are available:&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type: disc;&quot;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Dietary guidelines, 2010. Selected messages for consumers. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2011 June. 1 p. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the U.S. Department of Agriculture's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.choosemyplate.gov/downloads/MyPlate/SelectedMessages.pdf&quot; title=&quot;My Plate Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;My Plate Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;li&gt;Let's east for the health of it. Washington (DC): U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2011 June. 4 p. Available in Portable Document Format (PDF) from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.choosemyplate.gov/downloads/MyPlate/DG2010Brochure.pdf&quot; title=&quot;My Plate Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;My Plate Web site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, a variety of tools and resources on healthy eating are available in both Spanish and English from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.choosemyplate.gov/index.html&quot; title=&quot;My Plate Web site&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;My Plate Web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p class=&quot;Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Please note: This patient information is intended to provide health professionals with information to share with their patients to help them better understand their health and their diagnosed disorders. By providing access to this patient information, it is not the intention of NGC to provide specific medical advice for particular patients. Rather we urge patients and their representatives to review this material and then to consult with a licensed health professional for evaluation of treatment options suitable for them as well as for diagnosis and answers to their personal medical questions. This patient information has been derived and prepared from a guideline for health care professionals included on NGC by the authors or publishers of that original guideline. The patient information is not reviewed by NGC to establish whether or not it accurately reflects the original guideline's content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="142" OrdBy="1280" ID="458" Name="NGC Status" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NGC summary was completed by ECRI on February 11, 2005. This NGC summary was updated by ECRI Institute on November 3, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field><Field FieldID="141" OrdBy="1290" ID="460" Name="Copyright Statement" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;div class=&quot;content_para&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;No copyright restrictions apply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;" /></Field></Section><Section SecID="99999" OrdBy="99999" Name="Disclaimer"><Field FieldID="99999" OrdBy="99999" ID="99999" Name="NGC Disclaimer" Type="text"><FieldValue Value="&lt;p&gt;The National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC) does not develop, produce, approve, or endorse the guidelines represented on this site.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All guidelines summarized by NGC and hosted on our site are produced under the auspices of medical specialty societies, relevant professional associations, public or private organizations, other government agencies, health care organizations or plans, and similar entities.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines represented on the NGC Web site are submitted by guideline developers, and are screened solely to determine that they meet the NGC Inclusion Criteria which may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.guideline.gov/about/inclusion-criteria.aspx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC, AHRQ, and its contractor ECRI Institute make no warranties concerning the content or clinical efficacy or effectiveness of the clinical practice guidelines and related materials represented on this site. Moreover, the views and opinions of developers or authors of guidelines represented on this site do not necessarily state or reflect those of NGC, AHRQ, or its contractor ECRI Institute, and inclusion or hosting of guidelines in NGC may not be used for advertising or commercial endorsement purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Readers with questions regarding guideline content are directed to contact the guideline developer.&lt;/p&gt;" /></Field></Section></Version>
